[
    {
        "id": 1,
        "Question": "The general structure of all amino acids are same except for ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lysine",
            "b) Glycine",
            "c) Proline",
            "d) Alanine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In general, all α-amino acid consists of an amino group, a hydrogen atom, and a distinctive side chain, all bonded to α-carbon. Proline is the only amino acid which has a cyclic distinctive side chain which differs from all other amino acids."
    },
    {
        "id": 2,
        "Question": "Which of these amino acids are not optically active?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cysteine",
            "b) Lysine",
            "c) Arginine",
            "d) Glycine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When an amino acid dissolved in water, it acts as acid or base and called as the zwitterion or dipolar ion. Hence, an amino acid is an amphoteric molecule."
    },
    {
        "id": 3,
        "Question": "Which of these are used to measure optical activity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polarimeter",
            "b) Planometer",
            "c) Psychrometer",
            "d) Photometer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When a carbon atom has four different constituents, it is said to be chiral. All amino acids have chiral carbon except glycine and hence they are optically active."
    },
    {
        "id": 4,
        "Question": "A solution of L-alanine (4.0g/50 ml of 6 N HCl) has a rotation of +1.61° in a 2dm polarimeter tube. Calculate the specific rotation of L-alanine in 6 N HCl.",
        "Options": [
            "a) +15.1°",
            "b) +10.1°",
            "c) +11.1°",
            "d) +16.1°"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Polarimeter is used to measure the rotation of polarized light while planometer is used for area measurement and psychrometer measure humidity. Similarly, photometer measures illuminance or irradiance."
    },
    {
        "id": 5,
        "Question": "Name the amino acid, which exists in two non-superimposable mirror images of each other.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Epimer",
            "b) Anomer",
            "c) Enantiomer",
            "d) Chiral carbon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: [α] = Α°/ l×C; +1.61/2×0.08\n                        [α]= +10.1°."
    },
    {
        "id": 6,
        "Question": "Which of these are rare amino acid in a protein?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Leucine and serine",
            "b) Lysine and glutamic acid",
            "c) Tryptophan and methionine",
            "d) Leucine and lysine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When an amino acid with a chiral carbon exists in two non-superimposable mirror images of each other, it is called enantiomers. It can be easily identified by its configuration."
    },
    {
        "id": 7,
        "Question": "In which amino acid Imidazole group, an aromatic ring found?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lysine",
            "b) Arginine",
            "c) Histidine",
            "d) Glutamate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Tryptophan and methionine are rare in protein as they have only one codon for each while lysine, leucine, serine and glutamic acid have more than one codon for each protein. "
    },
    {
        "id": 8,
        "Question": "What is the maximum wavelength that Tryptophan and tyrosine absorb?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 280nm",
            "b) 260nm",
            "c) 257nm",
            "d) 230nm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Histidine contains imidazole group which can be uncharged or positively charged, depending on its local environment. Lysine & arginine contains positively charged R group while glutamate has negatively charged R group."
    },
    {
        "id": 9,
        "Question": "How is the secondary structure of a protein stabilized?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Van der wall forces",
            "b) Hydrogen bonding",
            "c) Covalent bond",
            "d) Hydrophobic bond"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Tryptophan, tyrosine, and phenylalanine are aromatic amino acids and absorbs ultraviolet light (UV). Absorption at 280nm is used for quantification and detection of purified proteins. The absorbance of proteins is dependent on number and position of aromatic amino acid residues."
    },
    {
        "id": 10,
        "Question": "How many amino acid residues are there in per turn of α-helix?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3.6",
            "b) 4.6",
            "c) 3.0",
            "d) 2.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Hydrogen bonding can bring together two chains which are at distance in terms of a sequence. Depending on hydrogen bonding, proteins have two structural conformations α-helix and β-sheets."
    },
    {
        "id": 11,
        "Question": "What is the fundamental unit of collagen?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tropocollagen",
            "b) Hydroxyproline",
            "c) Hydroxylysine",
            "d) Glycine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A typical collagen is long, stiff, inelastic and triple-stranded helical structure and is made up of tropocollagen. Tropocollagen consists of 3-coiled α chains. While hydroxylysine, hydroxyproline, and glycine are the amino acid sequence of tropocollagen."
    },
    {
        "id": 12,
        "Question": "Name the vitamins which cause scurvy.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vitamin B",
            "b) Vitamin B3",
            "c) Vitamin C",
            "d) Vitamin K"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Scurvy is a disease that affects the structure of collagen. It occurs due to impaired synthesis of collagen which results due to deficiencies of prolyl and lysyl hydroxylases."
    },
    {
        "id": 13,
        "Question": "Name the protein which is responsible for extensibility and elasticity of connective tissues.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Collagen",
            "b) Elastin",
            "c) Actin",
            "d) Keratin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Biosynthesis of collagen starts with the entry of polypeptides which further involves the formation tropocollagen by hydroxylation of prolyl and lysyl residues. Once tropocollagen is formed, it is packed in to transport vesicle and undergo exocytosis. Fibrils are formed by the lateral covalent cross-linking of tropocollagens."
    },
    {
        "id": 14,
        "Question": "Which of these type of curve shows the oxygen binding capacity of hemoglobin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hyperbolic curve",
            "b) Sigmoidal curve",
            "c) Exponential curve",
            "d) Linear curve"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Elastin is the second major protein present in the extracellular matrix, due to its high hydrophobic nature it constitutes extensibility and elasticity to the connective tissues. It is also considered as the main component of elastic fibers found in a ligament."
    },
    {
        "id": 15,
        "Question": "What is the function of myoglobin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oxygen storage",
            "b) Oxygen carrier",
            "c) Antioxidant",
            "d) Oxidant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A single molecule of hemoglobin binds up to four molecules of oxygen (Hb+4O2 = Hb(O2)4). The sigmoidal curve shows the cooperativity in binding of oxygen and hemoglobin. This curve is a plot between the fractional saturation of hemoglobin versus the partial pressure of oxygen."
    },
    {
        "id": 16,
        "Question": "What is the name of protein which is found in nail, hair, and horns?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Myoglobin",
            "b) Hemoglobin",
            "c) Keratin",
            "d) Collagen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: PH has a strong effect on the oxygen affinity of hemoglobin. Lowering of Ph reduces the oxygen affinity of hemoglobin which shifts the sigmoidal curve to the right which and it shows that more partial pressure of oxygen is required for hemoglobin to bind the given amount of oxygen."
    },
    {
        "id": 17,
        "Question": "In which iron(Fe) state myoglobin binds to the oxygen?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fe2+",
            "b) Fe3+",
            "c) Fe",
            "d) Fe4+"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Myoglobin bind with one oxygen molecule and functions as an oxygen storage protein.  Dissociation of myoglobin from oxygen is given by\n                                                     MbO2 = Mb + O2."
    },
    {
        "id": 18,
        "Question": "What is the shape of the oxygen dissociation curve of myoglobin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Linear",
            "b) Hyperbola",
            "c) Sigmoid",
            "d) Parabola"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Keratin is the fibrous protein present in the eukaryotes. They have been further classified into α-keratin and β-keratin, in which α-keratin is tough and insoluble and constitute almost the entire dry weight of hair, wool, nail, claws, horn, hooves etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 19,
        "Question": "Which of these are the possible cause of sickle cell anemia with respect to hemoglobin:",
        "Options": [
            "a) Defect in β-chain of hemoglobin",
            "b) Defect in α-chain of hemoglobin",
            "c) One copy of an abnormal β-globin gene",
            "d) Two copies of an abnormal β-globin gene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Myoglobin only in the Fe2+ state can bind with oxygen as the iron atom has six co-ordination bonds, 4 in the flat and two in a perpendicular state to the porphyrin ring. The oxygen binding site is present on the other side of six coordination position."
    },
    {
        "id": 20,
        "Question": "Protein folding is a process in which a polypeptide folds in to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2-D structure",
            "b) Globular form",
            "c) 3-D structure",
            "d) Linear form"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Protein folding is a process in which a polypeptide is folded into a 3-dimensional conformation which is necessary for proper protein function. Failure to fold can produce inactive protein. A protein molecule folds during or after its biosynthesis. "
    },
    {
        "id": 21,
        "Question": "Which of them contains all the information required to fold the polypeptide chain in its 3-D structure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DNA sequences",
            "b) RNA",
            "c) Histone protein",
            "d) Amino acid sequences"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Molecular chaperones are proteins which binds to incompletely folded protein to assist their proper folding. These proteins also assist the formation of oligomeric structures and for transport of proteins by membranes."
    },
    {
        "id": 22,
        "Question": "Which sentence is INCORRECT regarding molten globule state of protein?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hydrophobic interaction among non-polar residues",
            "b) The collapsed state",
            "c) It is less compact",
            "d) The denatured state"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The native conformation of a protein is determined by its amino acid sequences. This hypothesis was proved by an experiment, in which denaturation followed by renaturation folds the chain in its native structure."
    },
    {
        "id": 23,
        "Question": "Which of the following name is given to molecular chaperones?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Allosteric protein",
            "b) Heat shock protein",
            "c) Denaturation protein",
            "d) Ribonuclease"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Molten globule is a state in which interior side chains remain mobile, less compact and there is no proper packing. This state is completely different from the native and denatured state."
    },
    {
        "id": 24,
        "Question": "Which of these heat shock proteins prevent protein misfolding and maintain polypeptide chain in the unfolded state.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hsp60",
            "b) Hsp28",
            "c) Hsp70",
            "d) Hsp32"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The ability of chaperones to synthesis in large amount after a brief exposure to elevated temperature(42°C) makes them heat shock protein(Hsp). Basically, the eukaryotic cell has two major families of chaperones called Hsp60 and Hsp70. "
    },
    {
        "id": 25,
        "Question": "Among all the heat shock proteins which one is known as chaperonins?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hsp70",
            "b) Hsp32",
            "c) Hsp60",
            "d) Hsp30"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hsp70 is induced by stress and these are the primary proteins which prevent polypeptide chain from misfolding and maintained it in an unfolded state. It also helps in translocation of the protein from the cytosol into ER or mitochondria."
    },
    {
        "id": 26,
        "Question": "Which one of the following reagent is also known a Sanger’s reagent?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1-fluoro-2,4-dinitrobenzene (FDNB)",
            "b) Phenylisothiocyanate",
            "c) Cyanogen bromide",
            "d) β-mercaptoethanol"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hsp60 family of chaperones forms a large barrel-shaped structure that acts later when protein is being fully synthesized. Chaperonins bind incorrectly folded, partly folded or unfolded protein but not in their native state."
    },
    {
        "id": 27,
        "Question": "Proteolytic enzyme trypsin cleaves protein at which of these specific sites?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Carboxyl side of Alanine, Glycine",
            "b) Carboxyl side of Lysin or Arginine",
            "c) Carboxyl side of aromatic amino acid",
            "d) The amino side of aromatic amino acid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: FDNB reacts with a free amino group of N-terminal amino acid in alkaline solution to form yellow dinitrophenol. This reaction was first used by Sanger to determine the primary structure of the polypeptide hormone."
    },
    {
        "id": 28,
        "Question": "Mark the correct statement which depicts the correct statement of protein assay?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To determine the amount of protein",
            "b) To characterize the function of the protein",
            "c) To determine the structure of the protein",
            "d) To determine the sequence of the protein"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The specificity of these enzymes determined by the side chain of amino acid on either side of a peptide bond. This cleavage is necessary to sequence protein which is made up of more than 50 amino acid residues. "
    },
    {
        "id": 29,
        "Question": "In a living organism, strong interactions between molecules are formed by a certain type of bond. Name that?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hydrogen bonding",
            "b) Covalent bond",
            "c) Electrostatic interactions",
            "d) Van der Waals forces"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Protein assay is a technique to determine the amount of protein in an unknown solution. It is done by measuring the absorbance at 280nm. Aromatic side chain containing amino acids like tyrosine, tryptophan, and phenylalanine exhibit strong UV light absorbance. "
    },
    {
        "id": 30,
        "Question": "The monomeric unit of nucleic acid are called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nucleotides",
            "b) Nucleosides",
            "c) Pyrimidines",
            "d) Purines"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Nucleotides are the monomeric unit of nucleic acid; therefore, these are considered as polynucleotides. It is made up of three components i.e. nitrogenous base, sugar, and an ion of phosphoric acid. Nucleotides are phosphate easters of the nucleoside."
    },
    {
        "id": 31,
        "Question": "Who discovered nucleic acid?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Watson and Crick",
            "b) Griffith",
            "c) Friedrich Miescher",
            "d) Walter Gilbert"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Friedrich Miescher first discovered nucleic acid from nuclei of pus cells from discarded bandages and called it nuclein. It was later revealed as a mixture of basic protein and phosphorus-containing acid, now called nucleic acid."
    },
    {
        "id": 32,
        "Question": "Name the pyrimidine base which is found in RNA but not in DNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thymine",
            "b) Uracil",
            "c) Adenine",
            "d) Guanine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Uracil is considered like thymine, but it lacks methyl group at the C5 position. Uracil is a component of RNA whereas it is not found in DNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 33,
        "Question": "Name those purine bases which are commonly found in DNA and RNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Adenine and guanine",
            "b) Cytosine and thymine",
            "c) Adenine and thymine",
            "d) Cytosine and guanine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There are two types of nitrogenous bases in both RNA and DNA, purines and pyrimidines. Adenine and guanine are purines while cytosine and thymine come under pyrimidines."
    },
    {
        "id": 34,
        "Question": "Which of these statements are TRUE for a glycosidic bond?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The bond between sugar and the nitrogenous base",
            "b) The bond between the two sugar residues",
            "c) The bond between sugar and phosphate",
            "d) The bond between base and phosphate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ribose sugar is found in RNA, if the hydroxyl group(OH) at the 2nd position of ribose sugar is replaced by hydrogen (H) it will convert to deoxyribose which is DNA’s sugar."
    },
    {
        "id": 35,
        "Question": "What is the energy currency of the living cell?",
        "Options": [
            "a) GTP",
            "b) NADH",
            "c) FADH",
            "d) ATP"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The glycosidic bond formed between sugar and nitrogenous base during the formation of a nucleoside. This bond is held to be in β-configuration with respect to the ribose sugar leaving it’s base free to rotate around the bond."
    },
    {
        "id": 36,
        "Question": "The primary structure of DNA and RNA proceeds in which direction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3’  —–>   5҆’",
            "b) 5’  —–>   3’",
            "c) 4’  —–>   6’",
            "d) 3’  —–>   6’"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: ATP is the energy currency of the cell as it acts as a donor of high energy phosphate. It also acts as a chemical link between catabolism and anabolism. In its active form ATP is complexed with Mg2+ or Mn2+."
    },
    {
        "id": 37,
        "Question": "Which bond is used to stabilize the double helix of DNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hydrophobic bond",
            "b) Hydrogen bond",
            "c) Covalent bond",
            "d) Ionic bond"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The primary structure is described by the order in which bases occur in a polypeptide. The convention is to arrange them from left to right from 5’ end to 3’ end. 5’ end of the polypeptide is attached to phosphate while 3’ end is usually a free hydroxyl group."
    },
    {
        "id": 38,
        "Question": "Which of these statements are INCORRECT according to chargaff’s rules?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The molar ratio of A to T or C to G = 1",
            "b) The sum of purine = sum of pyrimidine",
            "c) The % C+G ≠ % A+T",
            "d) The composition of DNA remains the same in all the species"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Polynucleotide runs on the backbone of the phosphate-sugar chain. The base pairing of these nucleotide gives secondary structure. The secondary structure of DNA is its double helix which held together by hydrogen bonding between the bases. "
    },
    {
        "id": 39,
        "Question": "A purified DNA sample of leaf contains 20.0 mole of guanine. Calculate the approximate percentage of purine residues?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30%",
            "b) 40%",
            "c) 60%",
            "d) 20%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Erwin Chargaff proposed two rules which played a significant role in the discovery of the double helix structure of DNA. According to its second rule, the composition of DNA varies from one species to other. Statement composition of DNA remains the same in all the species is incorrect."
    },
    {
        "id": 40,
        "Question": "Who described the structure of DNA double helix?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Peter Mitchell",
            "b) Andre Jagendorf",
            "c) Ernest Uribe",
            "d) Watson and Crick"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: DNA double helix was first described in 1953 by Watson and Crick using X-ray diffraction. DNA fibers were obtained by Franklin and Wilkins. Watson, Crick, and Wilkins were awarded a noble prize in 1962."
    },
    {
        "id": 41,
        "Question": "Which form of DNA is described by Watson-Crick model?",
        "Options": [
            "a) B-DNA",
            "b) Z-DNA",
            "c) A-DNA",
            "d) Quadraplex DNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There are many forms of DNA which are biologically important, out of which Watson-Crick double helix model describes the B form of DNA. The confirmation of DNA would depend on the hydration level, base modification etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 42,
        "Question": "How many base pairs are there in every helical turn of Watson-Crick double helix model?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 32.3",
            "b) 11.6",
            "c) 20",
            "d) 10.4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Watson-Crick double helix model consists of 10.4 base pairs per helical turn. Since one helical turn formed by 360° and there would be 34.3° twist angle per residue among adjacent base pair."
    },
    {
        "id": 43,
        "Question": "Which one of the following statement is INCORRECT for Z-DNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Left-handed DNA",
            "b) Mostly found in alternating purine-pyrimidine sequences",
            "c) Only one deep, narrow groove",
            "d) Anti glycosidic bond conformation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Anti glycosidic bond conformation is incorrect as in Z-DNA the sugar and glycosidic bond conformations alternate, anti for C and syn for G while in B form there is only anti glycosidic bond conformation."
    },
    {
        "id": 44,
        "Question": "The third strand of triple helix is paired in which scheme?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hoogsteen base pair scheme",
            "b) Intermolecular base pair scheme",
            "c) Intramolecular base pair scheme",
            "d) G-quartet scheme"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Triple helix formed by three strands polypurine, polypyrimidine and the third strand which lay in the major groove of DNA and makes a hydrogen bond to duplex. The third strand is paired in hoogsteen base pairing scheme where the central strand is purine rich."
    },
    {
        "id": 45,
        "Question": "Name the nitrogenous base which is found in abundance in G-quadruplex?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Adenine",
            "b) Guanine",
            "c) Cytosine",
            "d) Thymine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When nucleic acid sequences are rich in guanine and can form four-stranded structure, it will term as G-quadruplex. It is a square arrangement of guanine, stabilized by hoogsteen hydrogen bonding."
    },
    {
        "id": 46,
        "Question": "The stability and formation of G-quadruplex depends on __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Monovalent cation",
            "b) Divalent cation",
            "c) Bivalent cation",
            "d) Pentavalent ion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A monovalent cation is responsible for the stability of G-quadruplex as it is present in the center of the tetrad. It can be formed in either DNA or RNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 47,
        "Question": "Which of this factor is not responsible for thermal denaturation of DNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) PH",
            "b) Temperature",
            "c) Ionic strength",
            "d) Humidity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When DNA duplex is laid open to the specific conditions like temperature, pH, or ionic strength it will interrupt the hydrogen bond between strands and they are no longer held together. After denaturation, the strand separates as individual coils and the double helix is denatured."
    },
    {
        "id": 48,
        "Question": "What is the term given to the supercoiling of circular DNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Twist number",
            "b) Linking number",
            "c) Writhe number",
            "d) Cross-linking"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There is three hydrogen bond in G:C while only two between A: T, this shows higher no of hydrogen bonds and interaction in G:C than A:T. Higher G:C content has a higher melting temperature. So, it has more thermal stability as compared to A:T."
    },
    {
        "id": 49,
        "Question": "Which of them is used to introduce negative supercoiling in DNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Type 1 topoisomerase",
            "b) Ethidium bromide",
            "c) Gyrase/ type 2 topoisomerase",
            "d) SYBR gold"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Linking number defines the no. of times one strand crosses other in closed circular DNA. It is the sum of twist number (total number of helical turn) and writhe number (supercoiling in the helix).\n                                                 Lk = Tw + Wr."
    },
    {
        "id": 50,
        "Question": "Molecules which play the key role in the transfer of genetic information during protein synthesis are ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) DNA",
            "b) RNA",
            "c) Nucleic acid",
            "d) Lipids"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: DNA has all the information which is confined to the nucleus, it is only transferred with the help of RNA during protein synthesis. RNA also has a diverse function in the body which includes the enzymatic activity of ribozyme and storage of genetic information in RNA viruses."
    },
    {
        "id": 51,
        "Question": "Which form of structure has been adopted by RNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A-form",
            "b) B-form",
            "c) Z-form",
            "d) D-form"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The difference in their thermal stability is not clearly known but double-stranded helical RNA needs higher temperature for denaturation than DNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 52,
        "Question": "Name the RNA molecules which is used to carry genetic information copied from DNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) tRNA",
            "b) mRNA",
            "c) rRNA",
            "d) snRNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Double helical track in RNA is generally short and formed by an A-form structure which differs from B-form adopted by DNA double helix."
    },
    {
        "id": 53,
        "Question": "Which of the following RNA molecule convert information stored in the nucleic acid to protein?",
        "Options": [
            "a) mRNA",
            "b) snRNA",
            "c)  rRNA",
            "d) tRNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Each type of RNA functions differently, among them mRNA which is also known as messenger RNA carries genetic information from DNA in the form of series of a three-base codon, which specifies the amino acid."
    },
    {
        "id": 54,
        "Question": "Name the secondary structure of tRNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cloverleaf",
            "b) L-shaped",
            "c) Duplex",
            "d) Triple Helix"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Transfer RNA (tRNA) plays a key role in protein biosynthesis and known as adapter tRNA. It acts as an interface between nucleic acid language and protein language. Additionally, it also participates in reverse transcription as a primer."
    },
    {
        "id": 55,
        "Question": "Name the RNA molecule which takes part in the formation of the ribosome?",
        "Options": [
            "a) mRNA",
            "b) tRNA",
            "c) rRNA",
            "d) gRNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Based on their primary sequence tRNA folds into cloverleaf like secondary structure with well-defined loops and stems while tertiary structure further modified into the L-shaped structure."
    },
    {
        "id": 56,
        "Question": "Which of the following rRNA molecules have peptidyl transferase activity in prokaryotes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 23S rRNA",
            "b) 28S rRNA",
            "c) 5S rRNA",
            "d) 18S rRNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: rRNA is also known as ribosomal RNA which is a key component in the formation of a ribosome. rRNA molecules along with the ribosomal proteins in the nucleolus form pre-ribosomal subunit 40S and 60S respectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 57,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is Incorrect about SnRNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is small nuclear RNA",
            "b) It helps in RNA splicing",
            "c) It is also called snurps",
            "d) It functions in RNA editing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: rRNA molecules have several roles in protein synthesis, one of them is peptidyl transferase activity. In prokaryotes, 50 subunit has 23S rRNA which has a catalytic role and forms a part of peptidyl transferase activity. Similarly, eukaryotes have 28S rRNA in 60 subunits."
    },
    {
        "id": 58,
        "Question": "What is the role of snoRNA in eukaryotes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chemical modification",
            "b) RNA splicing",
            "c) Act as adaptor RNA",
            "d) Forms component of the ribosome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: SnRNA is small nuclear RNA mainly found in the nucleus of eukaryotic cells. It takes part in RNA splicing and always remain associated with other proteins and referred to as snurps or snRNP. It functions in RNA editing is incorrect as RNA editing is done by guide RNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 59,
        "Question": "Name the class of RNA which takes part in RNA Editing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) snRNA",
            "b) tRNA",
            "c) gRNA",
            "d) SiRNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: snoRNA takes part in chemical modification like methylation of rRNA and other forms of RNA in eukaryotes. It forms a snoRNP complex with the proteins and guides it to the modification site of RNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 60,
        "Question": "Carbohydrates are also known as___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hydrates of carbon",
            "b) Carbonates",
            "c) Glycolipids",
            "d) Polysaccharides"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Basically, carbohydrates are polyhydroxy aldehyde or ketones, or compounds that can be break down to them. Mostly carbohydrates contain hydrogen and oxygen in the same ratio as in water, hence it is also called as hydrates of carbon."
    },
    {
        "id": 61,
        "Question": "Class of carbohydrate which cannot be hydrolyzed further, is known as?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Disaccharides",
            "b) Polysaccharides",
            "c) Proteoglycan",
            "d) Monosaccharide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Monosaccharides are single polyhydroxy aldehyde or ketone unit with general formula CnH2nOn. These are simple sugars which cannot be hydrolyzed further in a simpler form."
    },
    {
        "id": 62,
        "Question": "Which class of carbohydrates is considered as non-sugar?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Monosaccharides",
            "b) Disaccharides",
            "c) Polysaccharides",
            "d) Oligosaccharides"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When hundreds or thousands of monosaccharides condense together, it will form polysaccharides. These are not sweet in taste hence they are called non-sugars."
    },
    {
        "id": 63,
        "Question": "A molecule of amylopectin which contains 1500 glucose residues and is branched after every 30 residues. How many reducing ends are there?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Mostly common sugars are similar, the basic difference among them is at a single carbon atom i.e. differing by stereochemistry, these types of sugars which differ from each other only at a single carbon atom are called epimers. For e.g. D-glucose and D-mannose differ only at second carbon position."
    },
    {
        "id": 64,
        "Question": "What is the name of the drug which inhibits Na+/K+ pump across the cell membrane?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Taxol",
            "b) Vinblastine",
            "c) Quinone",
            "d) Ouabain"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Correct answer is 1 as no matter how many residues are there but a molecule of amylopectin has only one reducing end."
    },
    {
        "id": 65,
        "Question": "Mark the INCORRECT statement about sugar alcohol?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Addition of -itol as a suffix",
            "b) A linear molecule that cannot cyclize",
            "c) Carbonyl groups reduced to a hydroxyl group",
            "d) Terminal -OH group oxidizes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Ouabain is a common glycoside which inhibits the action of enzymes that pump Na+/k+ ions across cell membranes. Glycosides are formed by condensation between monosaccharides. "
    },
    {
        "id": 66,
        "Question": "Which of the following amino sugar are present in the bacterial cell wall?",
        "Options": [
            "a) N-acetylmuramic acid",
            "b) Sialic acid",
            "c) Aminoglycoside",
            "d) Azide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Sugar alcohol or alditols are formed by reduction of the carbonyl group in aldoses and ketoses to a hydroxyl group. These are designated by the addition of -itol and are linear molecules. So, terminal -OH group oxidizes is incorrect."
    },
    {
        "id": 67,
        "Question": "Which of the following glycosidic linkage found in maltose?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glucose (α-1 – 2β) Fructose",
            "b) Glucose (α1 – 4) Glucose",
            "c) Galactose (β1 – 4) Glucose",
            "d) Glucose (β1 – 4) Glucose"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: N-acetylmuramic acid is a derivative of glucosamine in which lactic acid is linked to oxygen at C-3 of N-acetylglucosamine which is a part of many structural polymers."
    },
    {
        "id": 68,
        "Question": "Which of the following is also known as invert sugar?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sucrose",
            "b) Fructose",
            "c) Dextrose",
            "d) Glucose"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In maltose, α- anomeric form of C-1 on one sugar and hydroxyl oxygen atom on C-4 of other sugar are joined by glycosidic linkage. Such linkage is also called the α-1, 4-glycosidic bond."
    },
    {
        "id": 69,
        "Question": "Name the major storage form of carbohydrates in animals?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cellulose",
            "b) Chitin",
            "c) Glycogen",
            "d) Starch"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sucrose is also known as invert sugar as during hydrolysis of sucrose with hot dilute acid it produces an equimolar combination of D-glucose and D-fructose. This phenomenon is also called inversion of sucrose or invertose."
    },
    {
        "id": 70,
        "Question": "What is the solubility of lipids in water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Soluble",
            "b) Partially soluble",
            "c) Insoluble",
            "d) Partially insoluble"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In general, lipids are hydrophobic in nature due to the presence of hydrocarbon chains in their structure. These are poorly soluble in water but highly soluble in a nonpolar solvent like ether, chloroform, or benzene."
    },
    {
        "id": 71,
        "Question": "Find the INCORRECT statement about the biological functions of lipids.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Storage form of metabolic fuel",
            "b) Have a protective function in bacteria, plant, and insects",
            "c) The structural component of membranes",
            "d) Exhibit increased catalytic activity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Fatty acids are long-chain hydrocarbons and are the simplest form of lipids. Fatty acids are said to be amphipathic by nature as they have both polar and nonpolar ends."
    },
    {
        "id": 72,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an example of unsaturated fatty acids?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lauric or Dodecanoic",
            "b) Linoleic or octadecatrienoic",
            "c) Palmitic or hexadecanoic",
            "d) Myristic or tetradecanoic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Exhibit increased catalytic activity is incorrect as all other options are correct. Lipids take part in a structural component of the membrane of animals, plants, or bacteria where it has protective functions. Lipid is also considered as the metabolic fuel of the body."
    },
    {
        "id": 73,
        "Question": "Name the two essential fatty acids?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Linoleate and linolenate",
            "b) Oleic and linoleic",
            "c) Lauric and myristic",
            "d) Arachidonic and oleic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The name of fatty acids is given by the number of carbons, and presence of a double bond, with the suffix -anoic in saturated fatty acid and -enoic in unsaturated fatty acids."
    },
    {
        "id": 74,
        "Question": "The melting point of fatty acids depends upon chain length and _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The shape of the fatty acids",
            "b) The position of the double bond",
            "c) Charge on the carbon",
            "d) Degree of unsaturation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Due to the unavailability of enzymes which induce double bond after C-9 is absent in mammals, they do not synthesize linoleate and linolenate. Hence, these two fatty acids are considered as essential fatty acids."
    },
    {
        "id": 75,
        "Question": "Which of the following form of lipids are also referred as neutral lipids?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Triacylglycerol",
            "b) Steroid",
            "c) Phospholipids",
            "d) Wax"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The melting point of fatty acids is determined by the length of the chain and number of the double bond. The longer the chain, the higher the melting point and the larger the number of double bonds the lesser the melting point."
    },
    {
        "id": 76,
        "Question": "Name the reagent which is used in Saponification?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ammonia",
            "b) Acetic acid",
            "c) NaOH/KOH",
            "d) Butanone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Triacylglycerols are the major form of stored lipids, it is hydrophobic, nonpolar, and do not have any charge; due to that it is also referred to as neutral lipid."
    },
    {
        "id": 77,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a component of a phospholipid?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Phosphate",
            "b) Alcohol",
            "c) Glycerol",
            "d) Protein"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Triacylglycerol is hydrolyzed by alkali treatment which is known as saponification. The amount of KOH/NaOH is required to saponify one-gram of weight is known as saponification number. Saponification number measures the average weight of fat."
    },
    {
        "id": 78,
        "Question": "Which of the following phospholipid is considered as a major constituent of nervous tissue?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glycerophospholipid",
            "b) Plasmalogen",
            "c) Inositol",
            "d) Sphingomyelin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A phospholipid is composed of four components: a fatty acid platform, phosphate, alcohol attached to a phosphate and a platform of glycerol on which phospholipid built. Protein is incorrect as protein does not take part in phospholipid formation."
    },
    {
        "id": 79,
        "Question": "Which of the following sterol is present in the cell membrane of fungi?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ergosterol",
            "b) Stigmasterol",
            "c) Sitosterol",
            "d) Campesterol"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Sphingomyelin is a type of sphingophospholipids where phosphocholine group is attached to sphingosine. It is the major constituent in the nervous tissue of higher animals."
    },
    {
        "id": 80,
        "Question": "Identify the lowest density lipoprotein among the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) HDL",
            "b) LDL",
            "c) VLDL",
            "d) Chylomicrons"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ergosterol is present in the cell membrane of fungi while rest stigmasterol, sitosterol, and campesterol are the types of sterol found in plants."
    },
    {
        "id": 81,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a fat-soluble vitamin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vitamin D",
            "b) Vitamin K",
            "c) Vitamin C",
            "d) Vitamin A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In general, there are only four fat-soluble vitamins (Vitamin A, D, E, K). Vitamin C is an ascorbic acid which is water soluble and precursors of all the coenzymes."
    },
    {
        "id": 82,
        "Question": "Deficiency of which vitamin causes Beri-Beri?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vitamin B12",
            "b) Vitamin B2",
            "c) Vitamin B6",
            "d) Vitamin B1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Deficiency of thiamine (Vitamin B1) can lead to Beri-Beri. It is mostly found in the area where polished rice is a major component of the diet."
    },
    {
        "id": 83,
        "Question": "Name the disease caused by the deficiency of Niacin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pellagra",
            "b) Rickets",
            "c) Scurvy",
            "d) Pernicious anemia"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Deficiency of niacin causes pellagra, it is a disease of the skin and central nervous system. Its symptoms included three Ds: Dementia, Dermatitis, and Diarrhea."
    },
    {
        "id": 84,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a component of the coenzyme A?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Retinol",
            "b) Pantothenic acid",
            "c) Pyridoxine",
            "d) Retinoic acid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pantothenic acid is used in the synthesis of coenzyme A, which is also an acyl group carrier. It performs two main functions, activation of an acyl group for transfer and activation of hydrogen of the acyl group."
    },
    {
        "id": 85,
        "Question": "Megaloblastic anemia is caused due to deficiency of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cobalamin",
            "b) Pyridoxine",
            "c)  Niacin",
            "d) Folic acid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Deficiency of folic acid leads to megaloblastic anemia, where synthesis of purine and thymidine get diminished which makes cells unable to make DNA and divide."
    },
    {
        "id": 86,
        "Question": "Which of the following vitamin is also known as cobalamin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vitamin B11",
            "b) Vitamin B12",
            "c) Vitamin B6",
            "d) Vitamin B2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Vitamin B12 is also known as cobalamin, it is a part of vitamin B complex along with vitamin B11 (Folic acid), vitamin B6 (Pyridoxine), vitamin B2 (Riboflavin)."
    },
    {
        "id": 87,
        "Question": "Mark the INCORRECT statement about Ascorbic acid.",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a strong reducing agent",
            "b) It can have synthesized in the body",
            "c) Involves in hydroxylation of prolyl- and lysyl- residues of collagen",
            "d) Shows antioxidant activity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It can have synthesized in the body is incorrect as vertebrates such as birds, fishes, and humans are not able to synthesize vitamin C, due to lack of enzyme gulono-lactone oxidase."
    },
    {
        "id": 88,
        "Question": "Name the vitamin which functions as hormone as well as visual pigment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thiamine",
            "b) Riboflavin",
            "c) Retinol",
            "d) Folic acid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Not all fat-soluble vitamin has coenzyme function, only vitamin K shows such activity. Fat-soluble vitamins released, absorbed and transported with the fat in the body."
    },
    {
        "id": 89,
        "Question": "Which of the following vitamin serves as a hormone precursor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vitamin C",
            "b) Vitamin A",
            "c) Vitamin K",
            "d) Vitamin D"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Vitamin A is also known as retinol, it is isoprenoid alcohol and essential for vision, growth, reproduction, and maintenance of epithelial tissues."
    },
    {
        "id": 90,
        "Question": "Name the vitamin which takes part in blood clotting?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vitamin E",
            "b) Vitamin K",
            "c) Vitamin D",
            "d) Folic acid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Vitamin D acts as a hormone precursor. UV component of sunlight falls on 7-dehydrocholesterol and gets converted to cholecalciferol (Vitamin D3) in the skin. Vitamin D3 absorbed into the blood and transported to liver and kidney where with the help of enzyme it formed calcitriol (a steroid hormone)."
    },
    {
        "id": 91,
        "Question": "Name the structure analog of vitamin K, which is used as anticoagulant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Warfarin",
            "b) Tocopherol",
            "c) Ergocalciferol",
            "d) β-carotene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Vitamin K plays role in post-translational modification of various blood clotting factors. It is a fat-soluble vitamin which requires complete synthesis of blood coagulation protein."
    },
    {
        "id": 92,
        "Question": "A __________is a biocatalyst that increases the rate of the reaction without being changed.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aluminum oxide",
            "b) Silicon dioxide",
            "c) Enzyme",
            "d) Hydrogen peroxide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Among these options, an enzyme is an only option which is a biocatalyst that catalyzes the chemical reaction without being changed while all other options are of the catalyst which increases or decrease the rate of reaction based on their concentration."
    },
    {
        "id": 93,
        "Question": "What is the nature of an enzyme?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vitamin",
            "b) Lipid",
            "c) Carbohydrate",
            "d) Protein"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Activation energy is the difference in free energy between the reactants and transition state. To complete a reaction, enzyme lowers the activation energy and crosses the transition state."
    },
    {
        "id": 94,
        "Question": "What is an apoenzyme?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a protein portion of an enzyme",
            "b) It is a non-protein group",
            "c) It is a complete, biologically active conjugated enzyme",
            "d) It is a prosthetic group"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All enzymes are protein except Catalytic RNA molecule. The native protein conformation of an enzyme defines its catalytic activity. Once the enzyme is denatured, its catalytic activity is also lost."
    },
    {
        "id": 95,
        "Question": "Name the coenzyme of riboflavin (B2)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) NAD or NADP",
            "b) FAD and FMN",
            "c)  Coenzyme A",
            "d) Thiamine pyrophosphate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Removal of cofactor from a conjugated enzymes forms apoenzyme which is a protein component. A cofactor is a non-protein group while a complete conjugated enzyme is known as a holoenzyme."
    },
    {
        "id": 96,
        "Question": "Which of this vitamin is associated with the coenzyme Biocytin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nicotinic acid",
            "b) Thiamine",
            "c) Biotin",
            "d) Pyridoxine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Riboflavin is a part of vitamin B complex, its coenzyme form is a FAD (Flavin adenine dinucleotide) which involves a redox reaction. NAD is a coenzyme form of nicotinic acid, and thiamine pyrophosphate is a coenzyme of thiamine. "
    },
    {
        "id": 97,
        "Question": "Name the enzyme secreted by pancreas?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pepsin",
            "b) Chymotrypsin",
            "c) Trypsin",
            "d) Alcohol dehydrogenase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Biocytin is a coenzyme of biotin which involves in carboxylation reaction while thiamine takes part in decarboxylation reaction."
    },
    {
        "id": 98,
        "Question": "Name the enzyme which catalyzes the oxidation-reduction reaction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Transaminase",
            "b) Glutamine synthetase",
            "c) Phosphofructokinase",
            "d) Oxidoreductase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Trypsin is a proteolytic enzyme, secreted by the pancreas. It is one of the three digestive proteinases along with pepsin and chymotrypsin which breaks down dietary protein molecules into simpler forms."
    },
    {
        "id": 99,
        "Question": "What is the function of phosphorylase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Transfer inorganic phosphate",
            "b) Transfer a carboxylate group",
            "c) Use H2O2 as the electron acceptor",
            "d) Transfer amino group"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Oxidoreductase is a class of enzyme which catalyze the oxidation-reduction reaction. Some of the oxidoreductase enzymes are oxidases, dehydrogenases, peroxidases etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 100,
        "Question": "Mark the CORRECT function of enzyme, Peptidase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cleave phosphodiester bond",
            "b) Cleave amino bonds",
            "c) Remove phosphate from a substrate",
            "d) Removal of H2O"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Phosphorylase is a transferase enzyme which involves a transfer of inorganic phosphate to a substrate while transcarboxylase transfer a carboxylate group and transaminase transfer amino group from amino acid to the keto acid."
    },
    {
        "id": 101,
        "Question": "Which of the following reaction is catalyzed by Lyase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Breaking of bonds",
            "b) Formation of bonds",
            "c) Intramolecular rearrangement of bonds",
            "d) Transfer of group from one molecule to another"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Hydrolases are the enzymes which cleave the bond by adding water. Peptidases belong to hydrolase class and it is used to cleave amide bonds of proteins."
    },
    {
        "id": 102,
        "Question": "Which of the following function is catalyzed by Racemases?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Removal of water",
            "b) Intramolecular transfer of a functional group",
            "c) Interconversion of L and D stereoisomers",
            "d) Inversion of asymmetric carbon atom"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Racemases are the class of Isomerases which catalyzes the intramolecular rearrangement and interconvert L and D stereoisomers. Like racemases another isomerase which catalyzes the intramolecular transfer of functional group is mutases."
    },
    {
        "id": 103,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an example of ligases enzyme?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mutases",
            "b) Epimerases",
            "c) Racemases",
            "d) Carboxylases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Inactive precursor is first cleaved to form active enzyme and this inactive precursor is known as a zymogen. Many proteolytic enzymes are first synthesized as an inactive precursor which further cleaved to form the active enzyme."
    },
    {
        "id": 104,
        "Question": "What is the binding energy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Free energy released in the formation of enzyme-substrate interaction",
            "b) The energy required to form a bond",
            "c) The energy required to bind substrate",
            "d) It is the activation energy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Carboxylases are the example of ligases enzyme. Ligases are the class of enzyme which deals with the formation of C-C, C-S, C-O and C-N bonds."
    },
    {
        "id": 105,
        "Question": "Which of the following is INCORRECT for the lock-and-key model?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is used to describe the binding process",
            "b) The active site of the enzyme is complementary to the substrate",
            "c) It demonstrates enzyme-substrate complex",
            "d) The binding of the substrate produces a conformational change in enzyme"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Binding energy is the free energy released when the enzyme-substrate complex is formed. This energy is used to lessen the activation energy. Binding energy can be maximum when the only correct substrate binds to the enzyme."
    },
    {
        "id": 106,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a catalytic strategy for an enzyme to perform specific reaction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Covalent catalysis",
            "b) Metal ion catalysis",
            "c) Michaelis constant",
            "d) Acid-base catalysis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Lock-and-key model is used to describe the enzyme-substrate complex. It is the binding process where the active site of an enzyme is complementary to the shape of the substrate. The binding of the substrate produces a conformational change in the enzyme is incorrect as the confirmation of enzyme changes only in the induced fit model. "
    },
    {
        "id": 107,
        "Question": "What is the SI unit of enzyme activity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Km",
            "b) Kat",
            "c) Kcat",
            "d) Vmax"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Enzymes involves more than one strategies to catalyze specific reactions. Acid-base catalysis, metal ion catalysis, and covalent catalysis are best-characterized mechanisms employed by an enzyme."
    },
    {
        "id": 108,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an example of irreversible enzyme inhibitor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cyanide",
            "b) Sarin",
            "c) Diisopropyl phosphoflouridate (DIPF)",
            "d) Statin drugs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Kat stands for katal, SI unit of enzyme activity. One katal is equals to the amount of enzyme that catalyzes the transformation of 1 mole of substrate per second. 1 katal = 1 mol sec-1."
    },
    {
        "id": 109,
        "Question": "Lineweaver-Burk plot is also known as______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Double reciprocal plot",
            "b) Hanes-Woolf plot",
            "c) Eadie-Hofstee plot",
            "d) Steady-state equation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Irreversible inhibitor binds to the active site of the enzyme and destroys the functional group. These inhibitors are mostly toxic in nature. Statin drugs are the example of competitive inhibitors which is used to control cholesterol."
    },
    {
        "id": 110,
        "Question": "Name the enzyme which is found in tears, sweat, and an egg white?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ribozyme",
            "b) Lysozyme",
            "c) Zymogen",
            "d) Isozymes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Lineweaver-Burk plot is a double reciprocal plot as it is the reciprocal of Michaelis-Menten equation represented in the graphical form.\n                                          1/V = Km/Vmax [S] + 1/Vmax."
    },
    {
        "id": 111,
        "Question": "What is an Isozyme?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Same structure, different function",
            "b) Different structure, the same function",
            "c) Same structure, the same function",
            "d) Different structure, different function"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Lysozyme is an enzyme which is present in secretions such as tears, sweat and found in egg white. Lysozyme cleaves the glycosidic bond that connects NAG and NAM of peptidoglycan cell wall."
    },
    {
        "id": 112,
        "Question": "Law of thermodynamics which states that energy can neither be created nor be destroyed is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The second law of thermodynamics",
            "b) Third law of thermodynamics",
            "c) First law of thermodynamics",
            "d) Zero-order kinetics"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: First law of thermodynamics depicts that energy can neither be created nor be destroyed but it can transform from one form to another. This shows that the energy remains constant in the system and in surroundings. "
    },
    {
        "id": 113,
        "Question": "Which of the following equation shows the relationship between free energy change (∆G) and the change in entropy (∆S), under constant temperature and pressure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ∆G = T∆H – ∆S",
            "b) ∆G = T∆H/∆S",
            "c) ∆G = ∆H/T∆S",
            "d) ∆G = ∆H – T∆S"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Gibb’s free energy is also known as chemical potential and is denoted by ∆G. It is the portion of total energy in a system which is available for work."
    },
    {
        "id": 114,
        "Question": "What is the value of ∆G, when a system is in equilibrium?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ∆G = 0",
            "b) ∆G = 1",
            "c) ∆G = -1",
            "d) ∆G = ∆G֯"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The relationship between free energy change and change in entropy of a reacting system under constant temperature and pressure is given by equation ∆G = ∆H – T∆S, where ∆H is the change in enthalpy and T is temperature."
    },
    {
        "id": 115,
        "Question": "Which of the following factor is not responsible for the actual change in free energy (∆G)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Temperature",
            "b) Pressure",
            "c) The initial concentration of reactant and products",
            "d) pH"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Under equilibrium, both forward and reverse reactions occur at equal rates which make a change in free energy zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 116,
        "Question": "Which of the following equation gives the relationship between ∆G֯ and Keq?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ∆G֯ = -RT ln Keq",
            "b) ∆G֯ = ln Keq",
            "c) ∆G = ∆G֯ (-RT Keq)",
            "d) ∆G = -RT ln Keq"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: During a reaction, the actual change in free energy is influenced by temperature, pressure, and the concentration of reactant and product at an initial level while ph does not affect the rate of reaction."
    },
    {
        "id": 117,
        "Question": "What is the standard free energy change of ATP?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Small and negative",
            "b) Large and positive",
            "c) Large and negative",
            "d) Small and positive"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Equation ∆G֯ = -RT ln Keqis correct as Keq is the equilibrium constant, R is the gas constant and T is the absolute temperature. This equation shows the simple prediction about the rate of reaction as if it proceeds forward, reverse or is at equilibrium. "
    },
    {
        "id": 118,
        "Question": "Which of the following act as a storage form of high energy phosphate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glucose-6-phosphate",
            "b) Phosphoenolpyruvate",
            "c) Phosphagens",
            "d) Glycerol phosphate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The phosphoryl transfer potential determines the negative free energy values. ATP has a higher tendency to transfer its terminal phosphoryl group to water during hydrolysis and generate large and negative free energy change."
    },
    {
        "id": 119,
        "Question": "What is the name of the molecule which donates its electrons?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reducing agent",
            "b) Oxidative agent",
            "c) Standard reduction potential",
            "d) Oxidant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: High energy phosphate stored as the phosphagens. It is of two types, creatine phosphate in vertebrates and arginine phosphate in invertebrates. Phosphagens maintains the concentration of ATP when it is utilized as a source of energy.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 120,
        "Question": "What is reduction potential?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The molecule loses an electron",
            "b) An atom/molecule gains an electron",
            "c) Reducing the power of an electron",
            "d) Oxidation power of an electron"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: An electron-donating molecule in an oxidation-reduction reaction is called the reducing agent while an electron accepting molecule is called an oxidizing agent or oxidant. "
    },
    {
        "id": 121,
        "Question": "Chemical compounds involved in the process of metabolism is known as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Metabolites",
            "b) Radicals",
            "c) Catabolites",
            "d) Intermediates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Metabolites are the chemical compounds which take part in the process of metabolism. Metabolism involves discrete pathways which proceed in a stepwise manner and transform substrate to end product."
    },
    {
        "id": 122,
        "Question": "Which of the following has a spiral metabolic pathway?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glycolysis",
            "b) Citric acid cycle",
            "c) Glyoxylate cycle",
            "d) Fatty acid biosynthesis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Catabolic pathway is the type of a metabolic pathway in which oxidative breakdown of larger complex molecules generates a huge amount of energy. Releasing energy is exergonic process while consuming energy is an endergonic process which can be seen in an anabolic pathway."
    },
    {
        "id": 123,
        "Question": "Name the type of the pathway which is involved in the synthesis of compounds?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Anabolic pathways",
            "b) Catabolic pathways",
            "c) Amphibolic pathway",
            "d) Anapleurotic pathway"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Metabolism involves the generation of energy and synthesis of biological molecules. It can follow several paths like a spiral pathway for fatty acid synthesis, the linear pathway for glycolysis, and cyclic pathway for the citric acid cycle."
    },
    {
        "id": 124,
        "Question": "Which of the following cycle shows amphibolic pathway?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glyoxylate",
            "b) Citric acid cycle",
            "c) Glycolysis",
            "d) Lipid metabolism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Anabolic pathway involves the synthesis of compounds, and it is endergonic in nature. This pathway works just opposite to catabolic pathway where molecules are broken down. Amphibolic is a combination of both anabolic and catabolic pathway."
    },
    {
        "id": 125,
        "Question": "Mark the INCORRECT statement about metabolic pathway.",
        "Options": [
            "a) They show the irreversible pathway",
            "b) Each one of them has first committed step",
            "c) They follow the only oxidative process",
            "d) They are regulated"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Amphibolic pathway combines both anabolic and catabolic pathway, it acts as a link or ‘crossroad’ between the two pathways. The amphibolic pathway can be seen in the citric acid cycle."
    },
    {
        "id": 126,
        "Question": "Regulation of metabolic pathway is done by following ways except one, mark the one?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Substrate concentration",
            "b) Allosteric regulation of enzymes",
            "c) Availability of oxygen",
            "d) Extracellular signals i.e. hormones or growth factors"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Each one of them has first committed step is incorrect as the metabolic pathway can follow both oxidation and reduction. Metabolic pathways are irreversible, regulated and have first committed step in each pathway."
    },
    {
        "id": 127,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an enzyme-catalyzed reaction in metabolism?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Isomerization and elimination",
            "b) Internal rearrangement",
            "c) Maillard reaction",
            "d) Free radical reaction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Metabolic pathways depend on the substrate concentration as well as extracellular signals. Coenzymes or certain metabolic intermediate also regulate the metabolism while not all the metabolic pathways depend on the oxygen. Oxygen is required only for aerobic reactions."
    },
    {
        "id": 128,
        "Question": "Name the inhibition where end products of biosynthesis pathway inhibit the activity of the first enzyme?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Feedback inhibition",
            "b) Feedback repression",
            "c) Allosteric inhibition",
            "d) Competitive inhibition"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Metabolic reactions fall into five categories: group transfer, making or breaking carbon bonds, internal rearrangement, free radical reactions, and isomerizations while the Maillard reaction is a non-enzymatic reaction in which amino group-containing compounds react with sugar molecules. "
    },
    {
        "id": 129,
        "Question": "In which of the following phenomenon the end product act as co-repressor and repress the synthesis of metabolic enzymes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Allosteric regulation",
            "b) Feedback repression",
            "c) Feedback inhibition",
            "d) Regulation by phosphorylation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Feedback inhibition is also known as end-product inhibition, the unique feature in this is the inhibition of the first enzyme in a biosynthetic pathway by the end product which in turn control its production."
    },
    {
        "id": 130,
        "Question": "Respiration is a ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oxidative process",
            "b) Reductive process",
            "c) Catabolite repression",
            "d) Intermediate process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Living organisms need free energy to survive; this free energy is supplied to them in the form of ATP. ATP is formed by the oxidation of organic compounds during respiration. So, respiration is an oxidative process."
    },
    {
        "id": 131,
        "Question": "What is respiratory substrate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The compounds which are reduced during respiration",
            "b) The compounds which are oxidized during respiration",
            "c) The intermediate compounds of respiration",
            "d) The end product of respiration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Respiratory substrates are the organic compounds which are oxidized during respiration and releases energy in the form of free energy. The respiratory substrate may be carbohydrates, fats, proteins, and organic acids. Carbohydrates are the most commonly used respiratory substrate."
    },
    {
        "id": 132,
        "Question": " Which of the following condition occur by incomplete oxidation of respiratory substrate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Feedback inhibition",
            "b) Feedback repression",
            "c) Aerobic condition",
            "d) Anaerobic condition"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Anaerobic condition arises due to the absence of oxygen where incomplete oxidation of respiratory substrate takes place while aerobic reaction takes place in the presence of oxygen and undergoes in complete oxidation."
    },
    {
        "id": 133,
        "Question": " Which of the following is not an aerobic reaction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glycolysis",
            "b) Citric acid cycle",
            "c) Oxidative phosphorylation",
            "d) Fermentation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Among all the options fermentation is anaerobic process while all other reactions take place in the presence of oxygen. Glycolysis takes place in the cytosol, the citric acid cycle takes place in mitochondrial matrix and site of oxidative phosphorylation is an inner mitochondrial membrane."
    },
    {
        "id": 134,
        "Question": " Which of these enzymes in glycolysis do not take part in an irreversible reaction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hexokinase",
            "b) Phosphofructokinase",
            "c) Pyruvate kinase",
            "d) Glucokinase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Glycolysis is an oxidative process where one molecule of glucose is partially oxidized into two molecules of pyruvate in the series of an enzyme-catalyzed reaction. It is also known as an Embden-Meyerhof pathway."
    },
    {
        "id": 135,
        "Question": " Name the inhibitor of glycolysis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fluoroacetate",
            "b) Iodoacetate",
            "c) Malonate",
            "d) Actinomycin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Hexokinase, phosphofructokinase, and pyruvate kinase catalyzed reactions in glycolysis is irreversible while rest reactions are reversible in nature. So, the regulation of glycolysis is also done by allosteric regulation of these three enzymes."
    },
    {
        "id": 136,
        "Question": " Name the site of pyruvate oxidation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cytosol",
            "b) Mitochondrial matrix",
            "c) Mitochondrial membrane",
            "d) Nucleus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Iodoacetate is an inhibitor of glyceraldehydes-3 phosphate dehydrogenase which reacts with its –SH group of cys residue and stops the glycolysis pathway."
    },
    {
        "id": 137,
        "Question": " Which of these following enzymes does not take part in pyruvate –dehydrogenase complex?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glyceraldehyde-3 phosphate dehydrogenase",
            "b) Pyruvate dehydrogenase",
            "c) Dihydrolipoyl transacetylase",
            "d) Dihydrolipoyl dehydrogenase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pyruvate oxidation takes place in the presence of oxygen inside the mitochondrial matrix and oxidized to acetyl Co-A. Pyruvate is produced in the glycolysis from where it enters to mitochondria with the help of transport protein. "
    },
    {
        "id": 138,
        "Question": "How many molecules of Co2 are produced by an acetyl group of acetyl-Co-A in a citric acid cycle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) 5",
            "c) 1",
            "d) 2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pyruvate dehydrogenase complex consists of three individual enzymes: E1, E2, and E3, where E1 is pyruvate dehydrogenase, E2 is dihydrolipoyl transacetylase and E3 is dihydrolipoyl dehydrogenase. Oxidation of pyruvate to acetyl-Co-A is done along with coenzymes."
    },
    {
        "id": 139,
        "Question": "Which of the following enzyme is inhibited by Fluoroacetate in Krebs cycle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Citrate synthase",
            "b) Aconitase",
            "c) Isocitrate dehydrogenase",
            "d) Fumarase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The citric acid cycle is also known as Krebs cycle in which the condensation of oxaloacetate and an acetyl group of acetyl Co-A take place and produced two molecules of Co2."
    },
    {
        "id": 140,
        "Question": "What is Respirasome?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The supramolecular complex of complex I, II, and III",
            "b) Respiratory center of the body",
            "c) Complex III and IV of the electron transport chain",
            "d) The intermediate complex formed during oxidative phosphorylation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Repirasome is the supramolecular complex formed by the complex I, II, and III of electron transport chain. This supramolecular complex consists of complexes along with their prosthetic groups, only complex IV would not take part in the formation of respirasome. "
    },
    {
        "id": 141,
        "Question": "FeS and FAD are the prosthetic groups of ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Complex I",
            "b) Complex II",
            "c) Complex III",
            "d) Complex IV"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: All the complexes of the electron transport chain comprise of a prosthetic group in order to act as an electron carrier. These prosthetic groups may be flavins, heme, Fe-S cluster and copper."
    },
    {
        "id": 142,
        "Question": " Mark the INCORRECT statement about Coenzyme Q?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It shows ubiquitous in nature",
            "b) It is also known as ubiquinone",
            "c) Q refers to the quinone chemical group",
            "d) It has a protein bound prosthetic group"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: It has a protein bound prosthetic group is incorrect as it is the election carrier in the electron transport chain which does not bind to the protein. It can be a carrier of hydrogen atoms that are an electron in addition to proton."
    },
    {
        "id": 143,
        "Question": " Out of the following, which one is not the inhibitor of the electron transport chain?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rotenone",
            "b) Antimycin A",
            "c) Cyanide",
            "d) Malonate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Malonate is not the inhibitor of the electron transport chain; it is a competitive inhibitor which inhibits the citric acid cycle by blocking the conversion of succinate to fumarate."
    },
    {
        "id": 144,
        "Question": " Name the physiological uncoupler which stops ATP synthesis.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2, 4-dinitrophenol",
            "b) Dicoumarol",
            "c) FCCP",
            "d) Thermogenin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Uncoupling agents are those agents which uncouple oxidation from phosphorylation and do not permit ATP synthesis. Thermogenin is only physiological uncoupler while rest is chemical uncoupler."
    },
    {
        "id": 145,
        "Question": " What is the total yield of ATP from complete oxidation of one molecule of glucose?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 32",
            "b) 10",
            "c) 8",
            "d) 40"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: ATP produced after complete oxidation of one molecule of glucose is 30 or 32 based on the type of shuttle system required to transport. Complete oxidation of glucose takes place by glycolysis, pyruvate dehydrogenase complex reaction, Krebs cycle, and oxidative phosphorylation."
    },
    {
        "id": 146,
        "Question": " What is the Cori cycle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glyoxylate cycle",
            "b) Gluconeogenesis",
            "c) Lactic acid cycle",
            "d) Citric acid cycle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Fermentation and anaerobic respiration differ from each other on the basis of the final electron acceptor. In fermentation, the final electron acceptor is organic molecules while in anaerobic respiration the final electron acceptor is inorganic molecule like nitrate, sulfate, carbonate etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 147,
        "Question": " Which of the following is CORRECT for the Pasteur Effect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Utilization of glucose for fermentation",
            "b) Increased glucose consumption by yeast in anaerobic condition",
            "c) Fermentation favors aerobic condition more than anaerobic",
            "d) Increased consumption of glucose by yeast in aerobic condition"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cori cycle is also known as the lactic acid cycle, given after by Carl and Gerty Cori. It is a metabolic pathway where lactic acid produced by fermentation in muscles moves to the liver and is converted to glucose, which returns to the muscle and again converted to lactate."
    },
    {
        "id": 148,
        "Question": "What is the Warburg effect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shows increased glycolysis in Cancer cell",
            "b) Disease caused by pesticide",
            "c) Blockage of ATP synthesis",
            "d) Inhibitor of glycolysis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Lois Pasteur observed that yeast does not show good ethanol production or glucose consumption when they are exposed to the aerobic condition. This shows that yeast consumes more glucose anaerobically than aerobically."
    },
    {
        "id": 149,
        "Question": "Mark the correct equation for Respiratory quotient?",
        "Options": [
            "a) RQ = O2 produced/Co2 consumed",
            "b) RQ = Co2 produced/ O2 consumed",
            "c) RQ = H2O produced/ Co2 consumed",
            "d) RQ = H2O produced/ O2 consumed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This is a phenomenon used for the condition exhibited by cancerous cells for generation of ATP as the main source of energy by increasing glycolysis and using its metabolic pathway."
    },
    {
        "id": 150,
        "Question": "Name the physiochemical process in which chemical energy is produced by light energy with the help of a photosynthetic organism?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Photosynthesis",
            "b) Respiration",
            "c) Oxidative decarboxylation",
            "d) Oxidative phosphorylation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Photosynthesis is the physiochemical process in which chemical energy is produced by light energy in the form of reducing power (NADPH, ATP) which is used for carbon dioxide fixation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 151,
        "Question": "Classification of organisms as oxygenic or anoxygenic during photosynthesis is based on ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) The presence of Co2",
            "b) The generation of oxygen",
            "c) The presence of light",
            "d) The presence of water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Photosynthetic organisms are classified on the basis of generation of oxygen during photosynthesis, it may be oxygenic or anoxygenic. Oxygenic organisms include both prokaryotes and eukaryotes while anoxygenic organisms are only prokaryotes."
    },
    {
        "id": 152,
        "Question": " Which of the following is an anoxygenic photosynthetic organism?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Plants",
            "b) Photosynthetic protists",
            "c) Cyanobacteria",
            "d) Green and Purple photosynthetic organism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Green and Purple photosynthetic organism is an anoxygenic photosynthetic organism while rests are oxygenic in nature. Anoxygenic photosynthetic organisms work under the absence of light and take part in light-independent reactions. "
    },
    {
        "id": 153,
        "Question": " Which of the following is not a lipid-soluble photosynthetic pigment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Phycobilins",
            "b) Carotenoids",
            "c) Chlorophyll",
            "d) Xanthophylls"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Among all the photosynthetic pigments, only phycobilins are water soluble. This unique feature of phycobilins is due to the presence of water-soluble proteins in their structure."
    },
    {
        "id": 154,
        "Question": " Which of these features are not of chlorophyll?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It has Mg2+ as the central metal ion",
            "b) It has cyclopentanone ring fused with a pyrrole ring",
            "c) It has a planer tetrapyrrole ring structure",
            "d) It is water-soluble pigment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Water-soluble pigment is not the feature of chlorophyll as it is a lipid-soluble pigment. It consists of a hydrophobic phytol tail which makes it hydrophobic in nature. Due to the hydrophobic character, it is not soluble in water. "
    },
    {
        "id": 155,
        "Question": " Name the pigment which is responsible for the yellow color of leaves in autumn and orange color of carrots?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Phycobilins",
            "b) Chlorophylls",
            "c) Carotenoids",
            "d) Bacteriochlorophyll"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Carotenoids distinguished from one another by their end group, these are long-chain, conjugated hydrocarbons whose absorption spectrum lies between 400-500nm which is responsible for yellow as well as orange color in leaves and carrots."
    },
    {
        "id": 156,
        "Question": " Name the mechanism which prevents photo-oxidative damage in plants?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Photosynthesis",
            "b) Photorespiration",
            "c) Photoprotection",
            "d) Phytoprotection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The presence of conjugated double bond, the isomeric configuration and the end group of accessory pigments makes it absorb light at more wavelength than chlorophyll. The two accessory pigments are phycobilins and carotenoids."
    },
    {
        "id": 157,
        "Question": "Name the photosynthetic pigment which is structurally similar to bile pigment bilirubin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chlorophyll",
            "b) Carotene",
            "c) Xanthophyll",
            "d) Phycobilins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Carotenoids are the accessory pigments which protect the plant from oxidative damage, and this phenomenon is known as photoprotection. Lipids and some cellular components get damaged by high-intensity light where carotenoid helps to remove excess energy."
    },
    {
        "id": 158,
        "Question": "What is the location of photosynthetic pigment in an oxygenic photosynthetic organism?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Plasma membranes",
            "b) Thylakoid membranes",
            "c) Chromatophores",
            "d) Chlorosome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Phycobilins have non-cyclic, linear tetrapyrroles structure which shows the structural similarity to the bile pigment called bilirubin. This is unique photosynthetic pigment which is covalently bound to water-soluble protein, phycobiliprotein."
    },
    {
        "id": 159,
        "Question": "What is the absorption spectrum?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The graph produced by absorption of light",
            "b) The graph shows the photochemical reaction",
            "c) The graph produced by absorption of oxygen",
            "d) The graph shows oxygen evolution at a different wavelength"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Absorption spectrum is the graph showing the absorption of light by the pigment as the function of the wavelength. Photosynthetic pigment absorbs light in the visible and infrared region. "
    },
    {
        "id": 160,
        "Question": "Photosynthetic reaction in an oxygenic photosynthetic organism is performed by pigment ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chlorophyll b",
            "b) Chlorophyll a",
            "c) Bacteriochlorophyll a",
            "d) Bacteriochlorophyll c"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Chlorophyll a most effectively absorbs the wavelength and drive photochemical reactions in oxygenic organisms. The spectrum which shows the activity of wavelength on photochemical reaction is the action spectrum."
    },
    {
        "id": 161,
        "Question": " Name the filamentous fungi which are used in Engelmann’s experiment to show photosynthetic activity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rhizopus stolonifer",
            "b) Penicillium",
            "c) Cyanobacteria",
            "d) Spirogyra"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Engelmann determined the first action spectrum by illuminating filamentous fungus (Spirogyra) with white light that had been passed through the prism and showed the evolution of oxygen at a different wavelength. "
    },
    {
        "id": 162,
        "Question": " Which of the following term defines the production of heat and light when excited molecule returns to its original state?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fluorescence",
            "b) Luminescence",
            "c) Intersystem crossing",
            "d) Phosphorescence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When extra energy converted to heat and light it is called fluorescence while luminescence is the term given to radioactive decay. Intersystem crossing is the conversion of an excited singlet state to the excited triplet state. In phosphorescence light emitted by triplet to ground state transition."
    },
    {
        "id": 163,
        "Question": "What is resonance energy transfer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Transfer of electrons between the molecules",
            "b) The transfer of energy as well as electrons",
            "c) The transfer of electrons but not the energy",
            "d) The transfer of energy but not the electron"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Resonance energy transfer is also known as a forster transfer where only energy is transferred directly to the neighboring chlorophyll but not the electrons. "
    },
    {
        "id": 164,
        "Question": " Which of the following is a Hill reagent?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sugar",
            "b) Chlorophylls",
            "c) 2, 6- dichlorophenolindophenol",
            "d) Nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide phosphate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When the electrons transferred from water to non-physiological oxidant by the effect of light it is known as Hill reaction and the non-physiological oxidant is called Hill reagent (2, 6- dichlorophenolindophenol). "
    },
    {
        "id": 165,
        "Question": " How many photons are absorbed to produce one molecule of oxygen?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Two",
            "b) Ten",
            "c) Twelve",
            "d) Eight"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: One molecule of oxygen is produced by the absorption of a minimum eight photos. For the production of oxygen about 300 or more chlorophyll molecules operate together as one photosynthetic unit."
    },
    {
        "id": 166,
        "Question": "What is red drop phenomenon?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Falling of red color in the spectrum",
            "b) Drop in quantum yield in the red region of the spectrum",
            "c) Drop in quantum yield in the far-red region of the spectrum",
            "d) Falling of far-red color in the spectrum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Water does not act as an electron donor in anoxygenic photosynthesis as oxygen is not produced by the light energy; it is only converted to ATP while in oxygenic photosynthesis light energy is used to produce oxygen along with ATP."
    },
    {
        "id": 167,
        "Question": "Which of the following correctly defines the yield of oxygen by the no. of photons absorbed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Emerson enhancement effect",
            "b) Quantum requirement",
            "c) Photochemical reaction",
            "d) Quantum Yield"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Red drop phenomenon describes the drop of quantum yield in far-red region i.e. above 680nm wavelength. It was observed that quantum yield remain same till 680nm and after that, it declined sharply."
    },
    {
        "id": 168,
        "Question": "Name the pathway for glucose synthesis by non-carbohydrate precursors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glycogenesis",
            "b) Glycolysis",
            "c) Gluconeogenesis",
            "d) Glycogenolysis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Synthesis of glucose from non-carbohydrate sources is carried out by gluconeogenesis. It is the universal pathway, found in all plants, animals, and microorganisms."
    },
    {
        "id": 169,
        "Question": "What is the site for gluconeogenesis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Liver",
            "b) Blood",
            "c) Muscles",
            "d) Brain"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Gluconeogenesis in animals takes place in the liver as well as some extent in the kidney cortex. The kidney is capable of making glucose during the condition of starvation and can make up to 50% of glucose."
    },
    {
        "id": 170,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the precursor of gluconeogenesis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glycolytic products",
            "b) Citric acid cycle intermediates",
            "c) Glucogenic amino acid",
            "d) Lysine or leucine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Only leucine or lysine is the substrate which is not used for gluconeogenesis as these amino acids produce only acetyl-CoA upon degradation. Animals cannot carry out gluconeogenesis by two acetyl carbon of acetyl-CoA."
    },
    {
        "id": 171,
        "Question": "Name the enzyme which is responsible for the conversion of pyruvate to phosphoenolpyruvate (PEP)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pyruvate carboxylase",
            "b) Pyruvate carboxykinase",
            "c) Glucose 6-phosphatase",
            "d) Phosphofructokinase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The conversion of pyruvate to PEP takes place in two stages, the first reaction is catalyzed by pyruvate carboxylase which converts pyruvate to oxaloacetate and in second reaction oxaloacetate is converted by pyruvate carboxykinase to PEP."
    },
    {
        "id": 172,
        "Question": "Which of the following are major sites for glycogen storage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Adipose tissue",
            "b) Bones",
            "c) Muscle and liver",
            "d) Kidney and liver"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Gluconeogenesis cannot be carried out in muscle and brain as they do not have glucose 6-phosphatase enzyme which is required to convert glucose 6-phosphate to glucose. Glucose 6-phosphatase can only be established in the endoplasmic reticulum of kidney and liver cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 173,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the precursor of glycogen?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glycerol 3-phosphate",
            "b) Malate",
            "c) UDP-glucose",
            "d) Leucine and lysine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Glycogen is stored in muscle and liver only.  The amount of glycogen is high in the liver but a larger amount of glycogen stored in the greater bunch of skeletal muscles. The liver uses its glycogen for the synthesis of glucose for all of the body while muscles use its glycogen for its own energy."
    },
    {
        "id": 174,
        "Question": "The priming function in glycogen synthesis is carried out by_________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lysine",
            "b) Arginine",
            "c) Glycogenin",
            "d) Glutamate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Glucose 1-phosphate and uridine triphosphate work together to activate UDP-glucose which acts as a precursor of glycogen. "
    },
    {
        "id": 175,
        "Question": "Name the enzyme which is used for branching of glycogen?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Branching enzyme",
            "b) Hexokinase",
            "c) Phosphoglucomutase",
            "d) Glycogen synthase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Glycogen synthesis is carried out with the help of a primer by its priming action. Glycogenin is a primer which adds glucosyl residue in the polypeptide chain that already has more than four residues."
    },
    {
        "id": 176,
        "Question": "Which of the following hormone maintain blood glucose level by activation of gluconeogenesis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nor-epinephrine",
            "b) Glucagon",
            "c) Insulin",
            "d) Epinephrine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Branching enzyme is also known as amylo-1, 4 —–> 1, 6 transglycosylase which adds a branch at four residues away from the existing branch. Enzymes in hexokinase, phosphoglucomutase, and glycogen synthase are used in glycogen synthesis but not in branching."
    },
    {
        "id": 177,
        "Question": "Name the hormone which is secreted in an emergency or in stress condition?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Epinephrine",
            "b) Glucagon",
            "c) Insulin",
            "d) Melanin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Glucagon acts opposite to insulin, and is secreted by the α-cells of the pancreatic islets. It maintains blood glucose level by the activation of glycogenolysis and gluconeogenesis."
    },
    {
        "id": 178,
        "Question": "Name the most active organs in the animal body which have the ability to synthesize triacylglycerol?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spleen",
            "b) Kidney",
            "c) Liver and intestines",
            "d) Adipose tissues"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In general, all plants and animals have the ability to synthesize triacylglycerol (TAG). In animals, liver and intestines are two most active sites for TAG synthesis. Adipose tissues are the storage site for fat."
    },
    {
        "id": 179,
        "Question": "Which of the following pathway is not used for triacylglycerol synthesis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glycerol 3-phosphate pathway",
            "b) Glyoxylate pathway",
            "c) Monoacylglycerol pathway",
            "d) Kennedy pathway"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Triacylglycerol is stored as the cytoplasmic lipid droplets like fat globules, oil bodies, lipid particles, adiposomes etc. These triacylglycerols are enclosed by a monolayer of phospholipids and hydrophobic proteins."
    },
    {
        "id": 180,
        "Question": "Which of the following enzyme is not used in the synthesis of triacylglycerol?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glycerol-3-phosphate acyltransferase",
            "b) Acylglycerophophate acyltransferase",
            "c) Phosphatidic acid phosphohydrolase",
            "d) Glycogen phosphorylase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Except glyoxylate pathway, all three pathways have been used for the synthesis of triacylglycerol. Kennedy pathway and glycerol 3-phosphate pathway are same which predominates in the liver and adipose tissue while the monoacylglycerol pathway used in intestines."
    },
    {
        "id": 181,
        "Question": "What is lipolysis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hydrolysis of triacylglycerol",
            "b) Formation of lipids",
            "c) Breakdown of ketone bodies",
            "d) Formation of ketone bodies"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Triacylglycerol biosynthetic pathway involves the formation of triacylglycerol by glycerol-3-phosphate. It involves four steps catalyzed by all the above enzymes except glycogen phosphorylase. The fourth enzyme is Diacylglycerol acyltransferase which converts diacylglycerol to triacylglycerol."
    },
    {
        "id": 182,
        "Question": "Which of the following hormone is not used in the hydrolysis of triacylglycerol into the fatty acids in adipose tissues?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Epinephrine",
            "b) Norepinephrine",
            "c) Glucagon",
            "d) Insulin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  Hydrolysis of triacylglycerol by lipase is called lipolysis. Triacylglycerol stored in adipose tissues of animals in an insoluble form where they constantly synthesized and broken down again."
    },
    {
        "id": 183,
        "Question": "Mark the INCORRECT statement about the bile salt.",
        "Options": [
            "a) These are detergent substances",
            "b) Stored in the gallbladder",
            "c) It is hydrophobic in nature",
            "d) It is made up of cholic acid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Triacylglycerols are converted to free fatty acids and glycerol under the influence of certain hormones. Hormones which control hydrolysis of the TAG are epinephrine, norepinephrine, and glucagon."
    },
    {
        "id": 184,
        "Question": "Triacylglycerol packed with the apolipoprotein and cholesterol in lipoprotein aggregate is called_________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chylomicrons",
            "b) VLDL",
            "c) HDL",
            "d) LDL"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The surface of bile salt molecule is both hydrophobic and hydrophilic in nature. Bile salts are made up of bile acids, synthesized in the liver and stored in the gallbladder. It facilitates the digestion of lipids."
    },
    {
        "id": 185,
        "Question": "What is the outcome of the accumulation of acetyl-CoA in the mitochondria of the liver?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is used as an energy source",
            "b) It has broken down in to free fatty acids",
            "c) It gets converted to oxaloacetate",
            "d) It forms ketone bodies"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Triacylglycerol packed with cholesterol and apolipoprotein and forms chylomicron which moves through lymphatic system where lipoprotein lipase breaks it in fatty acids and glycerol. Finally, fatty acids absorbed as a fuel or stored."
    },
    {
        "id": 186,
        "Question": "Name the energy source of the brain during starvation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fat",
            "b) Ketone bodies",
            "c) Protein",
            "d) Lipids"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Most of the acetyl-CoA has been used by citric acid cycle but during starvation acetyl-CoA accumulated in the mitochondria of liver and forms ketone bodies. Formation of ketone bodies by acetyl-CoA is known as ketogenesis."
    },
    {
        "id": 187,
        "Question": "What is the biosynthetic source of all steroid hormones?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cholesterol",
            "b) Ketone bodies",
            "c) Carbohydrate",
            "d) Protein"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the absence of glucose or during prolonged starvation, the brain gets energy from ketone bodies by converting it to acetyl-CoA. This mechanism is absent in liver so, it cannot utilize ketone bodies as an energy source. "
    },
    {
        "id": 188,
        "Question": "Which of the following is non-essential amino acid?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lysine",
            "b) Leucine",
            "c) Serine",
            "d) Methionine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Non-essential amino acids are those which are produced by the body and need not be supplied in the diet while essential amino acids are not produced in the body so these must be the part of the diet."
    },
    {
        "id": 189,
        "Question": " Which of these amino acids are essential for infants?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Methionine",
            "b) Arginine and Histidine",
            "c) Valine",
            "d) Lysine and Leucine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Only arginine and histidine are considered essential for infants as arginine is required for proper growth and development while histidine provides inflammatory response and the production of hydrochloric acid in the stomach. These are not produced in the body and must be supplemented in the diet."
    },
    {
        "id": 190,
        "Question": "In which form the nitrogen is incorporated into an amino acid?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nitrite",
            "b) Glutamate",
            "c) Nitrate",
            "d) Ammonium ion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Source of nitrogen in all amino acid is ammonium ion. It is the key component of amino acids. The ammonium ion is first incorporated in amino acids and then in other biomolecules."
    },
    {
        "id": 191,
        "Question": "Transamination reaction in amino acid synthesis is catalyzed by enzyme_________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nitric oxide synthase",
            "b) Decarboxylase",
            "c) Aminotransferase",
            "d) Glutamate decarboxylase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Transamination is the reaction of an amino acid biosynthetic pathway in which α-amino group from one amino acid is transferred to an α-keto acid and produce new amino acid. This reaction is catalyzed by aminotransferases also known as transaminases."
    },
    {
        "id": 192,
        "Question": "Intermediates of which of the following metabolic pathway have not been used in the synthesis of amino acids?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glycolysis",
            "b) Fatty acid biosynthesis",
            "c) Citric acid cycle",
            "d) Pentose phosphate pathway"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: All amino acids are derived from the intermediates of metabolic pathways like glycolysis, citric acid cycle, and the pentose phosphate pathway. 20 amino acids have been divided into 6 families on the basis of the primary carbon source of each amino acid."
    },
    {
        "id": 193,
        "Question": "Name the amino acid which does not take part in transamination during amino acid catabolism.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Proline",
            "b) Threonine",
            "c) Lysine",
            "d) Serine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Except serine rest three amino acids i.e. proline, threonine, and lysine take part in transamination during amino acid catabolism. Amino group donor is specific and called aminotransferase while acceptor is almost always α-ketoglutarate."
    },
    {
        "id": 194,
        "Question": "Name those living organisms which secrete nitrogen in the form of urea?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ureotelic",
            "b) Uricotelic",
            "c) Ammonotelic",
            "d) Nitroso compounds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: All living organisms excrete nitrogen in three ways i.e. ureotelic which excrete in the form of urea; ammonotelic emit nitrogen in the form of ammonia, and uricotelic excrete uric acid."
    },
    {
        "id": 195,
        "Question": " Name the type of cell in which synthesis of urea cycle takes place?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pancreatic cell",
            "b) Hepatocyte",
            "c) Bowman’s gland cell",
            "d) Urinary epithelium cell"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Urea cycle was discovered by Krebs and Henseleit, so, it is also known as Krebs-Henseleit cycle. The urea cycle is formed by aspartate, Co2, and ammonia in the cyclic pathway."
    },
    {
        "id": 196,
        "Question": "Which of these is a hereditary disease caused due to an error in amino acid metabolism?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Homocystinuria",
            "b) Albinism",
            "c) Phenylketonuria",
            "d) Branched-chain ketoaciduria"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Hepatocytes are liver cells in which urea synthesis take place in five enzymatic reactions, first two reactions occur in mitochondria while the rest three reactions take place in the cytosol."
    },
    {
        "id": 197,
        "Question": "Salvage pathway is used in the synthesis of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Amino acid",
            "b) Carbohydrate",
            "c) Nucleotide",
            "d) Fatty acid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Nucleotide synthesis takes place by two pathways: salvage pathways and de novo pathways. In de novo pathway pyrimidine base is assembled first and then attached to ribose while in the salvage pathway preformed base is recovered and reconnected to a ribose sugar."
    },
    {
        "id": 198,
        "Question": "Name the precursor of RNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glutamine",
            "b) Cytidine",
            "c) Orotidylate",
            "d) Uridylate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Deoxyribonucleotide cannot be synthesized directly from de novo and salvage pathway but it is generated by the reduction of ribose from the corresponding ribonucleotide."
    },
    {
        "id": 199,
        "Question": "The activity of which of the following enzyme is inhibited by the chemotherapeutic agent during deoxyribonucleotide synthesis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dihydrofolate reductase",
            "b) Ribonucleotide reductase",
            "c) Thymidylate synthase",
            "d) CTP synthetase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Uridylate or UMP is a major pyrimidine nucleotide formed by the decarboxylation of orotidylate (OMP) during pyrimidine synthesis. UMP further gets converted to a ribonucleotide, and act as a precursor of RNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 200,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the precursor of a purine ring?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glutamine",
            "b) Lysine",
            "c) Glycine",
            "d) Aspartate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Methotrexate and aminopterin are two anticancer drugs which inhibits the activity of dihydrofolate reductase. This will stop the formation of deoxyribonucleotide or DNA and the growth of the cell stops."
    },
    {
        "id": 201,
        "Question": "During purine synthesis the activity of amidotransferase enzyme is inhibited by the antitumor agent, mark the correct one.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aminopterin",
            "b) Methotrexate",
            "c) Texol",
            "d) Azaserine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Purine ring is derived from various precursors like glutamine (N2 and N9), glycine (C4, C5, and N7), aspartate (N1), Co2 (C6), folate (C2 and C8). Except for lysine, all are the precursor of purine ring."
    },
    {
        "id": 202,
        "Question": "What is the final product of purine degradation in mammals?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Guanine",
            "b) Inosine",
            "c) Uric acid",
            "d) Hypoxanthine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Azaserine is the structural analog of glutamine and works as an antitumor agent by preventing the activity of enzyme amidotransferase which in turn block purine synthesis."
    },
    {
        "id": 203,
        "Question": "Name the deficiency in which T and B lymphocyte do not develop properly?",
        "Options": [
            "a) XLA",
            "b) CVID",
            "c) SCID",
            "d) Multiple myeloma"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Punine nucleotides are sequentially degraded from inosine to hypoxanthine and guanine and finally to the uric acid which is excreted with the urine in the human being while in some other animals it is further degraded to urea and ammonia."
    },
    {
        "id": 204,
        "Question": "Which of the following disorder is caused due to the high serum level of urate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gout",
            "b) Galectosemia",
            "c) Cystic fibrosis",
            "d) Maple syrup urine disease"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Severe combined immunodeficiency syndrome (SCID) is caused by the deficiency of adenosine deaminase which leads to increase in the cellular concentration of dATP. High level of dATP reduces dNTPs in T-lymphocytes."
    },
    {
        "id": 205,
        "Question": "Name the genetic disorder which is caused by the deficiency of enzyme HGPRT?",
        "Options": [
            "a) SCID",
            "b) Lesch-Nyhan syndrome",
            "c) Cystic fibrosis",
            "d) Down syndrome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Gout is caused due to the high amount of uric acid, which is the product of purine degradation. It involves precipitation of sodium urate crystals in the joints and causes inflammation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 206,
        "Question": "What is the basic functional and structural unit of organisms?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nucleus",
            "b) DNA",
            "c) Cell",
            "d) Gene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cell is the basic structural and functional unit of life. It is a compartment filled with an aqueous solution along with several organelles which perform the essential function of life and is surrounded by the cell membrane."
    },
    {
        "id": 207,
        "Question": "Name the Scientists who first discovered the cell in the piece of cork?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Louis Pasteur",
            "b) Anton van Leeuwenhoek",
            "c) Robert Hooke",
            "d) Rudolf Virchow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Viruses are only living organisms which do not follow the cell theory. These are noncellular organisms as they lack cell wall or cell-like structure."
    },
    {
        "id": 208,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the part of modern cell theory?",
        "Options": [
            "a) All living things are made up of one or more cells",
            "b) The cell is a functional and structural unit of life",
            "c) Energy flow takes place within the cell",
            "d) All cells do not have the same chemical composition"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Robert Hooke was the first scientist who discovered the cells in the piece of cork and also given the term of the cell. He published his work in his famous book, Micrographia."
    },
    {
        "id": 209,
        "Question": "What is the permeability of the plasma membrane?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Selectively permeable",
            "b) Impermeable",
            "c) Single phase flow",
            "d) Highly permeable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: According to modern cell theory all cells are basically the same in chemical composition. The modern theory also states that the hereditary information passed from cell to cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 210,
        "Question": "Which of the following is described by the fluid mosaic model?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nucleus",
            "b) Plasma membrane",
            "c) Endoplasmic reticulum",
            "d) Ribosome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Plasma membrane is selectively permeable as it does not allow every solute to pass through it. Hydrophobic molecules and small molecules can easily traverse the plasma membrane while large molecules and ions cannot cross the membrane without the help of transporters."
    },
    {
        "id": 211,
        "Question": "Mark the component which is not the part of lipid bilayer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glycerol or Sphingosine",
            "b) Fatty acids",
            "c) Tryptophan and methionine",
            "d) Phosphate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Jonathan Singer and Garth Nicolson in 1972, proposed a fluid mosaic model for the structure and composition of the plasma membrane. This model is now accepted worldwide for the plasma membrane study."
    },
    {
        "id": 212,
        "Question": "What is the name of the hollow sphere formed by lipid bilayer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cholesterol",
            "b) Lipid raft",
            "c) Micelle",
            "d) Liposome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Phospholipids are composed of two types of components one is hydrophobic and other is hydrophilic. The fatty acid component is only hydrophobic while rest of the molecules is hydrophilic i.e. glycerol, phosphate, and alcohol attached to phosphate."
    },
    {
        "id": 213,
        "Question": "Which of the following is ABC transport protein that transport lipid in opposite direction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ATPase",
            "b) Scramblase",
            "c) Floppases",
            "d) Flippase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Liposomes are closed, solvent filled and self-sealing vesicle which is bound only by a single bilayer and forms a hollow sphere. "
    },
    {
        "id": 214,
        "Question": "Out of the following, which is not an ATP dependent transporter of lipid?",
        "Options": [
            "a) V-type ATPase",
            "b) Scramblase",
            "c) Flippase",
            "d) Floppases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Floppases is ATP dependent ABC transporter protein which transports lipids in an opposite direction while flippase is P-type ATPase which transports glycerophospholipid from outer layer to inner membrane."
    },
    {
        "id": 215,
        "Question": "Name the technique which is used to visualize the lateral movement of lipids?",
        "Options": [
            "a) FRAP",
            "b) Microscopy",
            "c) Electrophoresis",
            "d) Spectrometry"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Scramblase does not require ATP but it is activated by calcium. It moves phospholipids along its concentration gradient, non-specifically in either direction and ensures the monolayer to be equally populated with phospholipids."
    },
    {
        "id": 216,
        "Question": "Spectrin and ankyrin are the example of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polytopic",
            "b) Monotopic",
            "c) Peripheral protein",
            "d) Integral protein"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Spectrin and ankyrin are the peripheral proteins present in the membrane of RBC. Peripheral proteins are extrinsic proteins bound to membranes by electrostatic and hydrogen bond interactions."
    },
    {
        "id": 217,
        "Question": "Name the technique which is used to visualize the distribution of the protein in the membrane?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Patch clamp technique",
            "b) FRAP",
            "c) Freeze-etching",
            "d) Freeze-fracture technique"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Glycophorin is a single pass transmembrane protein of RBC. It was the first transmembrane protein whose complete amino acid sequence was determined. These are present in abundance on the plasma membrane of RBC."
    },
    {
        "id": 218,
        "Question": "Which of the following transport protein allows the transport of single solute from one side of the membrane to other?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Active transport",
            "b) Passive transport",
            "c) Uniporters",
            "d) Co-transporter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Freeze-fracture technique is used to visualize the protein distribution in the membrane by quickly frozen the specimen at -196°C and then split with a cold knife to expose the interior of the lipid bilayer and its embedded proteins."
    },
    {
        "id": 219,
        "Question": "What is the function of antiporters?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Transfer of the second solute in the same direction",
            "b) Transfer of the second solute in the opposite direction",
            "c) Transfer of single solute",
            "d) Transfer of solute through pores"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Uniporters are uniport which mediates single noncoupled transport of single solute from one side of the membrane to other. Examples: glucose transporter (GLUT)."
    },
    {
        "id": 220,
        "Question": "Name the type of antibodies which are present in blood group ‘O’?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Anti-A and anti-B",
            "b) Anti-A",
            "c) Anti-B",
            "d) H-antigen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Antiporters are the co-transporter protein i.e. coupled transport of two solutes in opposite direction.  Example: transport of calcium ion out of cardiac muscle cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 221,
        "Question": "Which of the following transport mechanism does not use metabolic energy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Secondary active transport",
            "b) Primary active transport",
            "c) Active transport",
            "d) Passive transport"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Blood group O does not have A or B antigen on the surface of their RBC, so their blood plasma contains both the antibodies anti-A and anti-B."
    },
    {
        "id": 222,
        "Question": "Which of the following glucose transporter works on the liver?",
        "Options": [
            "a) GLUT-1",
            "b) GLUT-2",
            "c) GLUT-3",
            "d) GLUT-5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Passive transport takes place along the concentration gradient without the use of metabolic energy while active transport takes place against the concentration gradient by using metabolic energy."
    },
    {
        "id": 223,
        "Question": "Name the family of transport protein which allows the water to cross the membrane?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Facilitated diffusion",
            "b) Ion channels",
            "c) Aquaporins",
            "d) Active transport"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: GLUT is the glucose transporters; a carrier protein mediates the movement of glucose. GLUT-2 works on liver while GLUT-1 on erythrocyte, GLUT-3 on the brain, and GLUT-5 on the small intestine."
    },
    {
        "id": 224,
        "Question": "Which of the following ATPases are used to maintain the acidic pH of lysosomes and other vesicles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) P-ATPases",
            "b) V-ATPases",
            "c) F-ATPases",
            "d) ABC transporters"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Aquaporins are the water channels in the plasma membrane of the plants and animals which allow water and other small uncharged molecules to cross the membrane."
    },
    {
        "id": 225,
        "Question": "Which of the following process is also known as cell drinking?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pinocytosis",
            "b) Phagocytosis",
            "c) Clathrin-mediated endocytosis",
            "d) Caveolae-mediated endocytosis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: V-ATPase is found in vacuolar membranes and is used to transport proton against a concentration gradient. These pumps maintain low pH by pumping protons from cytosolic face to exoplasmic face of the membrane."
    },
    {
        "id": 226,
        "Question": "Genetic information stored in mRNA is translated to polypeptide by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ribosome",
            "b) Nucleus",
            "c) Endoplasmic reticulum",
            "d) Golgi apparatus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ribosomes are ribonucleoproteins which are made up of RNAs and protein. These are used to translate genetic information stored in mRNA to polypeptides. These are globular in structure."
    },
    {
        "id": 227,
        "Question": "Which of the following ribosomal RNA does not take part in rDNA organization of E.coli?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5S RNA",
            "b) 23S RNA",
            "c) 16S RNA",
            "d) 5.8S RNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Eukaryotes have 80S ribosome, each consisting of small subunit (40S) and large subunit (60S) while prokaryotes have 70S ribosome with small subunit (30S) and large subunit (50S)."
    },
    {
        "id": 228,
        "Question": "What is the sedimentation coefficient of mitochondrial ribosome of humans?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 70S",
            "b) 55S",
            "c) 80S",
            "d) 60S"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The transcription unit of prokaryotes is made up of three ribosomal RNAs i.e. 16S, 23S, and 5S. The organization of ribosomal RNAs is similar in eukaryotes also but the size of RNA varies."
    },
    {
        "id": 229,
        "Question": "Which of the following Scientist discovered ribosome for the first time?",
        "Options": [
            "a) George Emil Palade",
            "b) Theodor Schwann",
            "c) Antonie van Leeuwenhoek",
            "d) Robert Hook"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Eukaryotes consists of two types of the ribosome, cytosolic and organellar. The cytosolic ribosome is of 80S while organellar ribosome of mitochondria and chloroplast is smaller in size than cytosolic ribosome and bear resemblance to bacterial ribosome."
    },
    {
        "id": 230,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a sorting signal present of protein?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Signal patch",
            "b) Signal peptide",
            "c) Carbohydrate sequence",
            "d) Amino acid sequence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: George Emil Palade, Romanian-American cell biologist has first observed ribosome as dense particles using an electron microscope."
    },
    {
        "id": 231,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is defines polysomes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lysosomal aggregation",
            "b) Multiple units of ribosomes",
            "c) Attachment of many ribosomes to common mRNA",
            "d) Attachment of many mRNA to ribosomes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Sorting signals present on proteins help them to transport and target to specific organelles such as ER, mitochondria, nucleus, plastids etc. Sorting signals present on protein can be a signal patch or signal peptide which is in the form of an amino acid sequence."
    },
    {
        "id": 232,
        "Question": "Which of the following transport involves translocation of the protein from cytosol to the nucleus?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Transmembrane transport",
            "b) Vesicular transport",
            "c) Non-gated transport",
            "d) Gated transport"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Polysome is also known as polyribosome, it is a structure where a single mRNA holds a number of ribosomes translocating in 5’ to 3’ direction."
    },
    {
        "id": 233,
        "Question": "Name the site where secreted protein synthesized?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ER membrane bound ribosomes",
            "b) Mitochondrial ribosome",
            "c) Membrane free ribosome",
            "d) Chloroplast ribosome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Translocation of protein from cytosol to nucleus takes place by nuclear pore complex which is a gated channel. Nuclear pore complex works as a selective gate which allows transport of specific macromolecules."
    },
    {
        "id": 234,
        "Question": "Name the antibiotic which inhibits protein synthesis in eukaryotes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Penicillin",
            "b) Cycloheximide",
            "c) Cinhonine",
            "d) Chlorophenicol"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Secreted proteins pass through ER-Golgi system, so, these are synthesized on ER membrane-bound ribosomes while proteins that are imported into organelles like mitochondria, nucleus, and chloroplast are synthesized on membrane free ribosomes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 235,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the largest single membrane-bound intracellular compartment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ribosome",
            "b) Golgi apparatus",
            "c) Nucleus",
            "d) Endoplasmic reticulum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Endoplasmic reticulum is a network of closed and flattened single membrane-bound intracellular structure.  ER lumen is the enclosed compartment between ER membranes which are physiologically active."
    },
    {
        "id": 236,
        "Question": "What is microsome?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Compartment of Golgi",
            "b) Smaller ribosomes",
            "c) Small ER compartments",
            "d) Small vesicles of fragmented ER"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: After the synthesis of protein, it undergoes various modifications before reaching their final destination i.e. Glycosylation, protein folding, the formation of disulfide bridges, and specific proteolytic cleavage. "
    },
    {
        "id": 237,
        "Question": "Endoplasmic reticulum membrane which is associated with ribosomes is called_______",
        "Options": [
            "a) ER lumen",
            "b) Smooth endoplasmic reticulum",
            "c) Rough endoplasmic reticulum",
            "d) Endosome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Microsomes are small vesicles formed by the breakdown of ER membrane into fragments.  Microsomes which are derived from RER are known as rough microsomes while microsomes lacking ribosomes are called smooth microsome."
    },
    {
        "id": 238,
        "Question": "Name the antibiotic which inhibits the synthesis of oligosaccharides?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tunicamycin",
            "b) Cephalosporins",
            "c) Penicillins",
            "d) Ofloxacin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Endoplasmic reticulum membrane has been divided into rough or smooth based on the association of ribosome with their cytoplasmic surface. The region of ER that is bounded with ribosomes is called rough endoplasmic reticulum or RER."
    },
    {
        "id": 239,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the function of Glycosylation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Helps in proper folding of the protein",
            "b) Confer stability in proteins",
            "c) Helps in cell-cell adhesion",
            "d) Synthesis of membrane lipid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Tunicamycin is an antibiotic which inhibits the synthesis of oligosaccharides by blocking the first step in glycosylation of proteins."
    },
    {
        "id": 240,
        "Question": "Name the site where detoxification of xenobiotic compounds takes place?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cytosol",
            "b) RER",
            "c) SER",
            "d) Ribosome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Glycosylation is the process of attachment of sugars molecule to the nitrogen atom in an amino acid residue of the protein. synthesis of membrane lipid is incorrect, SER produces membrane lipids."
    },
    {
        "id": 241,
        "Question": "Name the sequence which allows the resident protein to retain in ER lumen?",
        "Options": [
            "a) KDEL",
            "b) KKXX",
            "c) KLDE",
            "d) KXXK"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: SER is smooth endoplasmic reticulum which is a part of endoplasmic reticulum membrane where ribosome is not attached. It is the major site for removal of xenobiotics, and the reaction is catalyzed by cytochrome P-450."
    },
    {
        "id": 242,
        "Question": "Which of the following coated vesicle transport protein from ER to Golgi?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Clathrin",
            "b) COP II",
            "c) COP I",
            "d) COP III"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: KDEL stands for lys-asp-glu-leu sequences, present at the C-terminus of resident proteins. These sequences act as a sorting signal which is necessary for retention of protein in the ER."
    },
    {
        "id": 243,
        "Question": "Name the coated vesicle which is used to transfer protein from plasma membrane to endosome?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Clathrin",
            "b) COP I",
            "c) COP II",
            "d) COP III"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: COP II vesicles form for an anterograde pathway from ER to the Golgi. These transport vesicles arise from specialized coated regions of the membrane."
    },
    {
        "id": 244,
        "Question": "Name the scientist who discovered Golgi apparatus?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Robert Remake",
            "b) Rudolf Virchow",
            "c) Camillo Golgi",
            "d) Theodor Schwann"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Camillo Golgi was an Italian physician who first discovered Golgi complex, which is a single membrane-bound organelle. It consists of five to eight membrane-bound sacs called cisternae."
    },
    {
        "id": 245,
        "Question": "Which of the following organelle takes part in the secretion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cytoplasm",
            "b) Ribosomes",
            "c) ER compartments",
            "d) Golgi apparatus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Golgi stack or dictyosome is the stack of flattened membrane bound sacs called cisternae. The cisternae in stack vary in number, shape, and organization and represented as cis, medial and transform."
    },
    {
        "id": 246,
        "Question": "The chemical products of the cell are shipped and distributed by_______",
        "Options": [
            "a) ER lumen",
            "b) Golgi apparatus",
            "c) Lysosome",
            "d) Endosome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Golgi apparatus is prominent in cells that are specialized for secretion like goblet cell of intestinal epithelium secrete a large amount of mucus. Cell secretion takes place from trans-Golgi through exocytosis."
    },
    {
        "id": 247,
        "Question": " Which type of glycosylation takes place in the g=Golgi apparatus?",
        "Options": [
            "a) T-linked glycosylation",
            "b) N-linked glycosylation",
            "c) O-linked glycosylation",
            "d) G-glycosylation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Golgi apparatus modifies and transport proteins and lipids that have been built in the endoplasmic reticulum to the outside of the cell or to other locations in the cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 248,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the function of the Golgi apparatus?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Processing and shorting of glycoprotein",
            "b) Lipid metabolism",
            "c) Carbohydrate metabolism",
            "d) Amino acid metabolism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: O-linked glycosylation occurs by the linking of O-linked oligosaccharides to the hydroxyl group of amino acid via N-acetylglucosamine. Proteins undergo O-linked glycosylation in the cisternae of Golgi."
    },
    {
        "id": 249,
        "Question": "Name the complex polysaccharide which does not synthesize in the Golgi apparatus?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Starch",
            "b) Hemicellulose",
            "c) Glycosaminoglycans",
            "d) Pectins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Golgi apparatus involves the metabolism of carbohydrates, and lipids, but not of amino acid, so, amino acid metabolism is incorrect. Synthesis of glycolipids and sorting of glycoprotein also takes place in Golgi apparatus."
    },
    {
        "id": 250,
        "Question": "Which of the following hypothesis explain vesicle fusion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lipid raft hypothesis",
            "b) SNARE hypothesis",
            "c) Cell adhesion hypothesis",
            "d) Cell kill hypothesis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Complex polysaccharides are also synthesized in the Golgi apparatus such as hemicellulose and pectin in the cell wall of plant and glycosaminoglycans in the extracellular matrix of animals."
    },
    {
        "id": 251,
        "Question": "Name the GTPase which control the recognition of interactions between v-SNARE and t-SNARE?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rac protein",
            "b) Ras protein",
            "c) Rab protein",
            "d) Rho protein"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Snare hypothesis explains the vesicle fusion with target mediated by the interaction of specific proteins called SNAREs (Snape receptors). V-SNARE is present on vesicle while t-SNARE is present on the target. "
    },
    {
        "id": 252,
        "Question": "Which of the following ATPase dissociate SNARE apart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) V-ATPase",
            "b) F-ATPase",
            "c) P-ATPase",
            "d) NSF"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Rab protein attached with the surface of the vesicle; when vesicle encounter with target membrane, the binding of v-SNARE and t-SNARE causes vesicle to bound the membrane and allow the Rab protein to hydrolyze its bound GTP."
    },
    {
        "id": 253,
        "Question": "Which of the following organelle control intracellular digestion of macromolecules with the help of hydrolytic enzymes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Plastid",
            "b) Peroxisome",
            "c) Lysosome",
            "d) Actin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Lysosomes are membrane-bound compartment filled with hydrolytic enzymes which control intracellular digestion in the macromolecules. It contains about 40 types of different hydrolytic enzymes."
    },
    {
        "id": 254,
        "Question": "Which of these are not the hydrolytic enzymes of lysosome?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lipases",
            "b) Sulfatases",
            "c) Phosphatases",
            "d) Aldolase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The acidic nature of lysosome is maintained by a hydrogen pump in the lysosomal membrane which pumps hydrogen ion into lysosome and maintains pH of about 5.0 in its interior."
    },
    {
        "id": 255,
        "Question": "Digestion of cell’s own component is known as__________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Autophagy",
            "b) Heterophagy",
            "c) Phagocytosis",
            "d) Pinocytosis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Lysosomes contain 40 types of hydrolytic enzymes which include lipases, sulphatases, phosphatases, glycosidases etc. These enzymes work optimally in the acidic environment and the lysosome provides an acidic environment for these enzymes."
    },
    {
        "id": 256,
        "Question": "What is amphisome?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Early endosome",
            "b) Fusion of endosome and autophagosome",
            "c) Vacuole",
            "d) The bigger size of lysosome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Autophagy is the process of self-digestion, autophagic vacuoles contain cells own components, known as autophagosome which further fuse to the lysosome where digestion of components takes place."
    },
    {
        "id": 257,
        "Question": "The release of melanosomes from melanocytes is mediated by which of the following process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Autophagy",
            "b) Endocytosis",
            "c) Exocytosis",
            "d) Pinocytosis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Amphisome is formed when autophagosome fused with the endosomes. This amphisome further fused with lysosome for digestion. It will result in the release of macromolecules into the cytosol."
    },
    {
        "id": 258,
        "Question": "Name the single membrane which surrounded the vacuoles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Contractile vacuole",
            "b) Meninges",
            "c) Tonoplast",
            "d) Sarcolemma"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the condition of stress, cell releases undigested content by exocytosis of lysosomes. It is a minor pathway. Melanocyte in skin stores its pigment in lysosomes which releases it into the extracellular space of the epidermis."
    },
    {
        "id": 259,
        "Question": "Which of the following organelle works as a lysosome in the plants?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Contractile vacuole",
            "b) Peroxisome",
            "c) Plastid",
            "d) Vacuole"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Vacuoles are large, fluid-filled vesicles, present in most of the plants and fungal cells. These are surrounded by a single-membrane called tonoplast."
    },
    {
        "id": 260,
        "Question": "Which of the following pumps excess water out of the cell?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Contractile vacuole",
            "b) Lysosome",
            "c) Peroxisome",
            "d) Vacuoles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Like a lysosome in animal cells, vacuoles are present in plants and fungi contain a variety of hydrolytic enzymes. The pH of vacuole is also acidic and is maintained by transport protein in the vacuolar membrane."
    },
    {
        "id": 261,
        "Question": "Name the control center of the eukaryotic cell?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nucleus",
            "b) Ribosome",
            "c) Cytoplasm",
            "d) Golgi complex"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Nucleus contains most of the genetic material of the cell and is called the control center of the eukaryotic cell. Eukaryotic cell may have a single nucleus (uninucleate) or have many nuclei (multinucleate)."
    },
    {
        "id": 262,
        "Question": "Which of the following microorganism have two nuclei?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slime molds",
            "b) Cyanobacteria",
            "c) Amoeba",
            "d) Paramecium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Mature red blood cells do not have a nucleus, so, these cells are neither multinucleate nor uninucleate. "
    },
    {
        "id": 263,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a component of the nucleus?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chromosome",
            "b) Nucleolus",
            "c) Cytoplasm",
            "d) Nuclear envelope"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Paramecium is unicellular ciliate protozoa which have two nuclei, one is macronucleus and other is micronucleus. Genes for everyday function of the cell is stored in macronucleus and sexual reproduction is controlled by micronucleus."
    },
    {
        "id": 264,
        "Question": "Mark the INCORRECT statement about nuclear lamina.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Filaments present in the inner membrane of the nucleus",
            "b) Made up of lamin proteins",
            "c) Provide mechanical support to the nucleus",
            "d) It has bounded with the ribosomes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cytoplasm is not the component of the nucleus but the nucleus is found in the cytoplasm. The four components of the nucleus are nucleoplasm, nuclear envelope, nucleolus, and chromosomes."
    },
    {
        "id": 265,
        "Question": "Name the structure which is used to transfer macromolecules between the cytoplasm and nucleus.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Microtubules",
            "b) Nuclear pores",
            "c) Cilia",
            "d) Centrioles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Bounded with the ribosomes is incorrect for nuclear lamina as ribosomes present on the outer membrane of nucleus while nuclear lamina is a network of an intermediate filament which is present on the nuclear side of the inner membrane of the nucleus."
    },
    {
        "id": 266,
        "Question": "Name the signal which helps protein to move in or out of the nucleus?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Notch signal",
            "b) Paracrine signal",
            "c) Nuclear localization signal",
            "d) Chemical signals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Nuclear pores are present on the nuclear envelope which helps in transport of macromolecules among nucleus and cytoplasm. Nuclear pores are the part of a nuclear pore complex which includes inner and outer membranes of the nucleus."
    },
    {
        "id": 267,
        "Question": "Non-membrane bound body of the nucleus which disappears in the late prophase and reappears in telophase_______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nucleolus",
            "b) Chromosome",
            "c) Nucleoplasm",
            "d) Nuclear pore"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Nuclear localization signals are also known as a nuclear-export signal which helps protein to import and export in the nucleus through nuclear pores. These signals are specific amino acid sequences present on the proteins."
    },
    {
        "id": 268,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true for chromatin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Organized structure of DNA and protein",
            "b) These are highly condensed DNA",
            "c) It is found in the nucleus",
            "d) It contains a single dsDNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Nucleolus is the component of the nucleus which is a non-membrane bound body produced by Nucleolar-organizing region of a chromosome. It disappears in the late prophase and then appears again in the telophase stage of cell division."
    },
    {
        "id": 269,
        "Question": "Which region of chromatin is transcriptionally silent?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nucleoid",
            "b) Centromere",
            "c) Euchromatin",
            "d) Heterochromatin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Organized structure of DNA and protein is incorrect as chromatin is less condensed and extended DNA while highly condensed DNA is of chromosomes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 270,
        "Question": "The site of aerobic respiration in eukaryotic cells is___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Peroxisome",
            "b) Plastid",
            "c) Mitochondria",
            "d) Cilia"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In general, mitochondria are present nearly all eukaryotic cells and known as the power house of the cell. It acts as the site of aerobic respiration and produces cellular energy in the form of ATP."
    },
    {
        "id": 271,
        "Question": "How do the small molecules pass through the outer membrane of mitochondria?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ATP pump",
            "b) Carrier protein",
            "c) Channels",
            "d) Porins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The inner membrane of mitochondria is highly convoluted while its outer membrane is fairly smooth. These convoluted folds are also called cristae which make the membrane impermeable to many solutes and increase its surface area."
    },
    {
        "id": 272,
        "Question": "Which of the following division technique is similar in mitochondria and bacteria?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Binary fission",
            "b) Budding",
            "c) Binary fusion",
            "d) Meiosis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Mitochondrial porins are voltage-dependent anion-selective channels (VDAC). Being present on the outer membrane of mitochondria it allows small molecules to pass."
    },
    {
        "id": 273,
        "Question": "Which of the following is INCORRECT evidence to support the endosymbiotic theory?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mitochondria are self-repeating bodies like microscopic organisms",
            "b) Mitochondria have their own particular DNA",
            "c) Mitochondrial ribosomes, and enzymes are similar to the bacteria",
            "d) Mitochondria and bacteria differ in size"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Mitochondria are semi-self-ruling organelle and separation by binary fission simply like bacteria. This similarity between bacteria and mitochondria suggest that it evolved from bacteria and is proved by endosymbiotic theory."
    },
    {
        "id": 274,
        "Question": "Name the organelle which is used for aerobic respiration and ATP synthesis in Entamoeba histolytica.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hydrogenosome",
            "b) Mitochondria",
            "c) Mitosome",
            "d) Peroxisome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Endosymbiotic theory had supported the fact that mitochondria have evolved in eukaryotes by the symbiotic association of bacteria. Mitochondria and bacteria differ in size is incorrect as the size of mitochondria and bacteria is approximately same."
    },
    {
        "id": 275,
        "Question": "Which of these are not from plastid family?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chloroplast",
            "b) Tonoplast",
            "c) Chromoplast",
            "d) Leucoplast"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Mitosomes are originated from mitochondria and is present only in aerobic organisms that do not have mitochondria. These are double-membrane bound organelle which is mainly found in unicellular organisms. "
    },
    {
        "id": 276,
        "Question": "Which of the following is responsible for pigment synthesis and storage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Leucoplast",
            "b) Chloroplast",
            "c) Chromoplast",
            "d) Etioplast"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Tonoplast is an outer membrane of vacuoles while chloroplast, chromoplast, and leucoplast belong to plastid family. The chloroplast is considered a most important member of the family as it helps in photosynthesis."
    },
    {
        "id": 277,
        "Question": "Which class of leucoplast is responsible for fat storage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Amyloplast",
            "b) Proteinoplasts",
            "c) Aleuroplasts",
            "d) Elaioplasts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Chromoplast is well-off in carotenoids which are accountable for orange, yellow, or red color in many fruits and flowers. "
    },
    {
        "id": 278,
        "Question": "Name the plant organelle which acts as a major site for an oxidative reaction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Peroxisomes",
            "b) Mitochondria",
            "c) Chloroplast",
            "d) Thylakoid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Leucoplast is colourless or non-pigmented in nature and is used to for storage. Amyloplast store starch, proteinoplast, and Aleuroplast store and modify proteins."
    },
    {
        "id": 279,
        "Question": "Cell shape and cellular motility is determined by the ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Centrioles",
            "b) Intermediate filament",
            "c) Microtubule",
            "d) Microfilaments"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Microtubules are a cylindrical, hollow structure which plays a crucial role in determining the shape of the cell. Microtubule is resulted by the combination of 13 protofilaments into a tube-like structure."
    },
    {
        "id": 280,
        "Question": "What is treadmilling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Depolymerization of microtubule",
            "b) The breaking of heterodimer chain",
            "c) Arrangement of microtubules",
            "d) Addition of tubulin heterodimer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Motile cell appendages like cilia and flagella are formed by the doublet microtubule. Another 10 or 11 protofilaments combined to form second microtubule, this second microtubule fused with 13 protofilaments of first microtubule and forms doublet microtubules."
    },
    {
        "id": 281,
        "Question": "Which of the following feature is the same in cilia and flagella?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Help in locomotion",
            "b) Wave-like motion",
            "c) Occurring all over the surface of the cell",
            "d) Very small in size"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Treadmilling is the process of adding tubulin heterodimer at one end and dissociating another heterodimer from other ends. This will keep the polymer length same or unchanged."
    },
    {
        "id": 282,
        "Question": "Name the drug which depolymerizes microtubule to tubulin subunit.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cytochalasin D",
            "b) Nocodazole",
            "c) Latrunculin",
            "d) Phalloidin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cilia and flagella differ from each other as cilia are smaller in size and many in numbers while flagella are larger in size and very less in numbers. Only the function of them is same as they both help in locomotion."
    },
    {
        "id": 283,
        "Question": "What is the role of vinblastine and vincristine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Causes depolymerization",
            "b) Prevent depolymerization",
            "c) Prevent polymerization",
            "d) Prevent nucleation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Nocodazole causes depolymerization of microtubule into tubulin subunits while all the other drugs affect actin filaments. "
    },
    {
        "id": 284,
        "Question": "What is the name of the cell membrane of muscle cells?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sarcoplasm",
            "b) Perimysium",
            "c) Endomysium",
            "d) Sarcolemma"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Vinblastine and vincristine are also known for their role in cancer, these drugs act by interfering with the polymerization and stop the growth of microtubule."
    },
    {
        "id": 285,
        "Question": "What is the basic functional unit of myofibril?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sarcomere",
            "b) Tropomyosin",
            "c) Troponin",
            "d) Nebulin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Sarcolemma is the cell membrane of muscle cells while sarcoplasm is the cytoplasm of muscle fiber. Sarcoplasm also contains a modified endoplasmic reticulum which is known as sarcoplasmic reticulum."
    },
    {
        "id": 286,
        "Question": "Which of the following take part in relaxation of muscles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nebulin",
            "b) Titin",
            "c) Tropomodulin",
            "d) Myomesin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Myofibril consists of thick and thin filaments i.e. myosin and actin which are arranged into a linear chain of an ordered structure known as a sarcomere."
    },
    {
        "id": 287,
        "Question": "Which of the following is occluding junction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Adherence junction",
            "b) Desmosomes",
            "c) Tight junction",
            "d) Gap junction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Titin is the considered as largest protein in the body, and plays a role in the relaxation of muscles. It is present opposite to the Z disc and thick filament."
    },
    {
        "id": 288,
        "Question": "Which of the following signal molecule is NOT used for extracellular signaling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Autocrine",
            "b) Endocrine",
            "c) Paracrine",
            "d) Cyclic AMP"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Extracellular signaling in animals is carried out by four categories of signal molecules endocrine, paracrine, autocrine, and juxtacrine signaling. Cyclic AMP is a secondary messenger used for intracellular signaling."
    },
    {
        "id": 289,
        "Question": "Which of the following signaling pathway is followed by T-lymphocytes in response to antigenic stimulation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Autocrine signaling",
            "b) Juxtacrine signaling",
            "c) Paracrine signaling",
            "d) Endocrine signaling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Endocrine signaling always acts on the distant target cell or that cell which located distantly from their site of synthesis while paracrine signaling is used for the cells which are located in close proximity. "
    },
    {
        "id": 290,
        "Question": "Name the signaling which requires physical contacts between the cells involved.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Paracrine signaling",
            "b) Intracellular signaling",
            "c) Autocrine signaling",
            "d) Juxtacrine signaling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Specific extracellular signaling molecules are defined for each cell. Extracellular signaling involves the synthesis and release of signal molecules, which bind to the specific receptor and initiate signal transduction pathway."
    },
    {
        "id": 291,
        "Question": "Mark the signal molecule which does not interact with cell surface receptor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Insulin",
            "b) Glucagon",
            "c) Testosterone",
            "d) Gastrin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Signaling pathway in which signal molecules affect the same cell that produces it is called autocrine signaling. In response to antigenic stimulation, T-lymphocytes synthesize a growth factor which derives its own proliferation and amplifies the immune response."
    },
    {
        "id": 292,
        "Question": "Name the largest family of cell surface receptor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) GPCR",
            "b) Ion-channel receptor",
            "c) Enzyme-linked receptor",
            "d) Nuclear receptor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Juxtracrine signaling is different from another signaling as it requires physical contact between the cells, these signals neither travel to distant target nor act on the same cell. "
    },
    {
        "id": 293,
        "Question": "Which of the following G-protein takes part in the regulation of vision?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gs family",
            "b) Gi family",
            "c) Gq family",
            "d) Golf"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Testosterone is a steroid hormone which can easily traverse cytosolic membrane and interact with a nuclear receptor or cytosolic receptor."
    },
    {
        "id": 294,
        "Question": "Name the family of monomeric G-protein which regulates the growth of the cell?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ras",
            "b) Rab",
            "c) Ran",
            "d) Rho"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: GPCR is a G-protein coupled receptor; it requires G-protein for transmission of signals to the intracellular receptor. It is present in all eukaryotes and it includes receptors which are responsible for smell, light, and taste."
    },
    {
        "id": 295,
        "Question": "Resting phase of the cell, where it undergoes growth and DNA replication is called_________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mitosis phase",
            "b) G1 phase",
            "c) Interphase",
            "d) M phase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Interphase is also known as resting phase, time in the cell cycle where a cell is preparing for division by undergoing the cell growth. Interphase is further divided into three stages."
    },
    {
        "id": 296,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the part of Interphase in the cell cycle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) S phase",
            "b) G1 phase",
            "c) G2 phase",
            "d) M phase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: S phase is synthesis phase, characterized as the period of DNA replication. DNA replication is the process of duplication of cell’s genome."
    },
    {
        "id": 297,
        "Question": "Name the state where never dividing cells of neurons and skeletal muscle present?",
        "Options": [
            "a) G0",
            "b) G1",
            "c) G2",
            "d) M"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Interphase is the period before division while M phase is mitosis phase where actual division takes place. G1, S, and G2 phase are the part of Interphase."
    },
    {
        "id": 298,
        "Question": "How many hours does the M phase take to complete a cycle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8hr",
            "b) 1 hr",
            "c) 4 hr",
            "d) 11 hr"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: G0 is the state where cell division never occurs; cells can remain in this state for days, weeks, and even a year. It is terminally differentiated state and most of the cell in our body like neurons and skeletal muscle cells are in G0 state."
    },
    {
        "id": 299,
        "Question": "Name the process of nuclear division?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ubiquitylation",
            "b) Polymerization",
            "c) Karyokinesis",
            "d) Cytokinesis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A cell cycle of the eukaryotic cell takes 24 hr to divide. In total 24 hrs, the G1 phase takes 11 hr, S phase completed in 8 hrs, G2 about 4 hrs, and M phase about 1 hr."
    },
    {
        "id": 300,
        "Question": "Name the regulatory component of the cell cycle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cyclin",
            "b) CDK",
            "c) DNA",
            "d) APC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Nuclear division is the formation of two daughter nuclei and this process known as karyokinesis. M phase starts with the nuclear division followed by a division of cytoplasm (cytokinesis)."
    },
    {
        "id": 301,
        "Question": "Cyclin dependent kinases are activated by which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Binding to cyclin",
            "b) Binding to cyclin and CDK activating protein kinases",
            "c) Phosphorylation with CDK activating kinase",
            "d) Phosphorylation with tyrosine kinase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cyclin is the regulatory component of the cell cycle as it undergoes synthesis and degradation in each division of the cell cycle. CDK is cyclin-dependent kinases which are catalytic in nature."
    },
    {
        "id": 302,
        "Question": "Name the cyclin which takes part in M phase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cyclin E",
            "b) Cyclin A",
            "c) Cyclin D",
            "d) Cyclin B"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The activation of CDK is triggered by the association of cyclin and phosphorylation with associated kinases. Kinases are the enzymes which add a phosphate group to the target substrate."
    },
    {
        "id": 303,
        "Question": "Name the enzyme which causes ubiquitylation and destruction of cyclin.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acid hydrolases",
            "b) Hyaluronidase",
            "c) Ubiquitin ligase",
            "d) Phosphatase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Different events of the cell cycle are controlled by the association of CDK with different cyclins. Cyclin B is mitotic cyclin which works in M phase while cyclin E is S phase cyclin, and cyclin D is G1 cyclin."
    },
    {
        "id": 304,
        "Question": "Name the cells which lost their control of the regulated division, differentiation, and apoptosis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tumor cell",
            "b) Immune cell",
            "c) Platelets",
            "d) Stem cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Tumor cells work opposite to normal cells; a normal cell has regulated division, differentiation, and programmed cell death. When the normal cell loses its ability to undergo apoptosis and regulated cell division, it becomes a tumor cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 305,
        "Question": "Name the process by which a malignant cell spread throughout normal cells?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Transformation",
            "b) Metastasis",
            "c) Invasiveness",
            "d) Progression"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Tumor cells are of two types, benign tumor, and malignant tumor. The only malignant tumor is considered as cancerous cell while the benign tumor is clustered cells and cannot spread to other sites."
    },
    {
        "id": 306,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT the type of cancer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Carcinomas",
            "b) Sarcomas",
            "c) Leukemia",
            "d) Caspases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Malignant tumor is particularly considered as cancerous cell as they multiply through the normal cells and make them a cancerous cell, this process is called invasiveness."
    },
    {
        "id": 307,
        "Question": "What is the origin of the cancerous cells?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Monoclonal",
            "b) Polyclonal",
            "c) Stem cells",
            "d) Mesodermal cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Caspases is incorrect as caspases are protease enzyme which causes apoptosis, which is opposite to tumor formation. Carcinoma is endodermal/ectodermal tissue tumor, sarcoma is a tumor of mesodermal connective tissue, and leukemia is blood cancer."
    },
    {
        "id": 308,
        "Question": "Name the process of transition from normal cells to cancerous cells?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ubiquitylation",
            "b) Polymerization",
            "c) Transformation",
            "d) Metastasis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cancer arises from a single abnormal cell or it has a monoclonal origin. It is initiated by the change in DNA sequences or change in the pattern of gene expression."
    },
    {
        "id": 309,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the characteristic of a cancer cell?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Density dependent inhibition",
            "b) Contact inhibition",
            "c) Loss of anchorage dependence",
            "d) Apoptosis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Normal cells are transformed into a cancer cell by a multistep process including genetic/epigenetic changes, proliferation, invasion, and metastasis."
    },
    {
        "id": 310,
        "Question": "What is angiogenesis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Differentiation process",
            "b) Growth factors",
            "c) Contact inhibition",
            "d) Blood vessel formation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cancer cell loses contact inhibition, anchorage dependence, does not undergo apoptosis, become immortal, invasive and invade normal tissue in the body."
    },
    {
        "id": 311,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT the example of proto-oncogenes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rb",
            "b) Src",
            "c) Myc",
            "d) Abl"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Tumor initiation starts with the change of normal cell to the cancerous cell then these cancerous cells travel to other cell and invade them, it comes under promotion and progression and then finally tumor is established."
    },
    {
        "id": 312,
        "Question": "Which of the following mutation causes Burkitt’s lymphoma?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Point mutation",
            "b) Chromosomal translocation",
            "c) Deletion",
            "d) Duplication"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Angiogenesis is the process of formation of new blood vessels in the cancerous cells. This process is needed to support the growth of a tumor by the supply of oxygen and growth factors."
    },
    {
        "id": 313,
        "Question": "Which of the following chromosomal alteration causes retinoblastoma?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Deletion in chromosome 11",
            "b) Translocation between chromosome 9 and 22",
            "c) Deletion in chromosome 13",
            "d) Translocation between chromosome 8 and 21"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Rb is a tumor suppressor gene, which inhibits cell cycle progression while proto-oncogenes which help in cell division and reduce cell death."
    },
    {
        "id": 314,
        "Question": "Name the genes which directly inhibit cell growth or promote cell death.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gatekeeper genes",
            "b) Caretaker genes",
            "c) Checkpoints",
            "d) Transcription factors"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Burkitt’s lymphoma caused by the translocation of the part of a gene derived by the over-expression of proto-oncogenes. Translocation takes place between the segments of chromosome 8 and chromosome 14."
    },
    {
        "id": 315,
        "Question": "If DNA is damaged, which of the following gene arrest cell cycle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rb",
            "b) p53",
            "c) Hedgehog receptor",
            "d) p16"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answerer: c\nExplanation: Retinoblastoma is an eye cancer which is caused by the deletion in chromosome number 13. Wilms tumor caused due to deletion in chromosome 11 and leukemia is caused by the translocation between the segments of chromosomes."
    },
    {
        "id": 316,
        "Question": "Name the chemical carcinogen which causes prostate cancer.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Radon",
            "b) Arsenic",
            "c) Cadmium",
            "d) Asbestos"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Gatekeeper genes are tumor suppressor genes which inhibit cell growth and promote cell death. They act directly on cell and their activity restrict tumor cell proliferation."
    },
    {
        "id": 317,
        "Question": "Name the type of cell division in which daughter cells receive an exact copy of chromosomes from parent cell?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mitosis",
            "b) Cleavage",
            "c) Interphase",
            "d) Meiosis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Basically eukaryotes have two types of cell division, mitosis, and meiosis. Meiosis is reductional division while mitosis is equational division and the number of chromosomes in parent and daughter cells remain same. "
    },
    {
        "id": 318,
        "Question": "Who coined the term mitosis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Robert Hook",
            "b) Walther Flemming",
            "c) Farmer and Moore",
            "d) F. Twort"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Walther Flemming in 1882 introduced the term mitosis. It is the process where one round of DNA replication is trailed by a single round of chromosomal segregation. It generates two genetically identical cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 319,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a microtubule organizing center?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Centrosome",
            "b) Kinetochore",
            "c) G2 phase",
            "d) Centrioles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Microtubule organizing center (MTOC) is centrosome, present outside the nuclear membrane. It regulates the cycle of cell division as well as microtubule formation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 320,
        "Question": "Among the following, which one is not the substage of mitosis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Prophase",
            "b) Metaphase",
            "c) Anaphase",
            "d) Nucleation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Mitosis starts with the nuclear division called karyokinesis followed by cytokinesis. This phase is further divided into four substages: prophase, metaphase, anaphase, and telophase.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 321,
        "Question": "Name the protein which holds two sister chromatids?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Securin",
            "b) Separase",
            "c) Cohesin",
            "d) APC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: SMC (Structural Maintenance of Chromosome) protein cohesin hold together the sister chromatids at centromere while separase is ubiquitous cysteine protease which degrades cohesin during anaphase."
    },
    {
        "id": 322,
        "Question": "Which of the following microtubule pulls the chromosomes towards pole?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Astral",
            "b) Polar",
            "c) Kinetochore",
            "d) Centrioles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Kinetochore microtubule is a mitotic spindle which attaches to chromosome at the specific site called kinetochores. It pulls the two sister chromatids at the opposite pole during anaphase."
    },
    {
        "id": 323,
        "Question": "Spindle fiber attached to the chromosome by a process known as_________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Congression",
            "b) Binding",
            "c) Alignment",
            "d) Search and capture"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Plant cells do not have centrosomes and astral microtubule at their poles. In plant cells, mitotic spindle formed from MTOC originate from nuclear envelop itself."
    },
    {
        "id": 324,
        "Question": "What is congression?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Attachment of microtubule to chromosomes",
            "b) Attachment of two sister chromatids",
            "c) The endpoint of the spindle pole",
            "d) The midpoint of two spindle poles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Search and capture is a process by which plus end of microtubule search the kinetochore site at the chromosome and attach to it. These microtubules radiate from the MTOC of the poles."
    },
    {
        "id": 325,
        "Question": "In which of the following phase, sister chromatids move towards opposite poles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Telophase",
            "b) Anaphase",
            "c) Prophase",
            "d) Metaphase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The arrangement of chromosomes at the center of the poles or at the metaphase plate, which is a midpoint and this midpoint is called congression."
    },
    {
        "id": 326,
        "Question": "Which of these proteins is responsible for depolymerization of microtubule?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kin I kinesin",
            "b) CENP-E",
            "c) Dynein",
            "d) Actin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The sister chromatids are attached to the kinetochore tubule at the metaphase state and start moving towards the opposite poles at anaphase stage. At anaphase, the sister chromatids split apart and move to opposite poles of the spindle."
    },
    {
        "id": 327,
        "Question": "Name the medication which hinders the shortening of the microtubule.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Colchicine",
            "b) Cytochalasin",
            "c) Taxol",
            "d) Vinblastine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: CENP-E, Kin I kinesin, and dynein are the motor proteins which contain kinetochores. Out of them only Kin I kinesis is responsible for depolymerization of microtubule from its plus end while dynein generates poleward forces toward its minus end."
    },
    {
        "id": 328,
        "Question": "Mark the common feature between eukaryotes and prokaryotes.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shape of DNA",
            "b) Number of chromosomes",
            "c) A prokaryotic cell is similar to a eukaryotic organelle",
            "d) Cell wall"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In general, prokaryotes differs from the eukaryotic organism in every sense except its organelles i.e. mitochondria and chloroplast. It has to be believed that these organelles have been derived from bacteria as they share many common features (endosymbiotic theory)."
    },
    {
        "id": 329,
        "Question": "Which of the following gene deduced the evolutionary relationship between the taxonomic groups?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 16S rRNA",
            "b) 23S rRNA",
            "c) 5S rRNA",
            "d) 18S rRNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: 16S ribosomal RNA acts as a signature sequence and is present in all the cells. These are approximately 1500bp in length. The organism of one taxonomic group has different conserved sequences than the other group. "
    },
    {
        "id": 330,
        "Question": "Name the scientist who proposed the phylogenetic tree for living things.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Carlo Urbani",
            "b) Louis Pasteur",
            "c) Robert Koch",
            "d) Carl Woese"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Carl Woese proposed the reorganization of five kingdoms into three kingdoms, based on the ribosomal RNA signature sequences. He placed protista, fungi, plants, and animals into a single group called eukaryotes."
    },
    {
        "id": 331,
        "Question": "The largest bacteria which can be visible by unaided eye is_______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thiomargarita namibiensis",
            "b) Lactobacillus",
            "c) Mycoplasma",
            "d) Pseudomonas"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Thiomargarita namibiensis and epulopiscium fishelsoni are the largest bacteria of 600 micrometers in length and 75 micrometers in diameter and are easily visible to eyes."
    },
    {
        "id": 332,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT the basic shape of the bacteria?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rod shape",
            "b) Square shape",
            "c) Comma shape",
            "d) Spiral shape"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are four basic shapes of bacteria: rod shape is bacillus bacteria, comma shaped is vibrio bacteria, spiral shape is spirilla, and sphere shape of coccus."
    },
    {
        "id": 333,
        "Question": "What is sarcinae?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cocci group of bacteria",
            "b) Chainlike group of bacteria",
            "c) Cubelike group of bacteria",
            "d) Grapelike cluster of bacteria"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The division of bacteria into multiple groups form different structures like the chainlike division is called streptococci; the grapelike cluster is called staphylococci. Similarly, a group of eight bacteria into the cubelike structure is called sarcinae."
    },
    {
        "id": 334,
        "Question": "Which of the following bacteria is pleomorphic?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mycobacteria",
            "b) Streptococcus",
            "c) Pseudomonas",
            "d) Corynebacterium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Pleomorphic bacteria lack a single characteristic shape. Most of the bacteria are of monomorphic while corynebacterium is pleomorphic and has many shapes."
    },
    {
        "id": 335,
        "Question": "Name the acid present in the cell wall of bacteria which helps in retaining its color during the acid-fast test?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mycolic acid",
            "b) Teichoic acid",
            "c) Malic acid",
            "d) Tartaric acid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Bacterial staining is of three types: simple, differential, and specialized. Gram staining is a differential staining procedure used to differentiate bacterial species into gram positive and gram negative."
    },
    {
        "id": 336,
        "Question": "Which of the following organisms have thick peptidoglycan in their cell wall?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gram-negative bacteria",
            "b) Gram-positive bacteria",
            "c) Yeast",
            "d) Molds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Mycolic acid is present in the cell wall of acid-fast bacteria which helps in retaining its color during the acid-fast test while non acid-fast bacteria decolorized after reacting with acid-alcohol.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 337,
        "Question": "Name the area of a bacterial cell which contains a bacterial chromosome.",
        "Options": [
            "a) DNA",
            "b) Nucleus",
            "c) Nucleoid",
            "d) Cell wall"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Nucleoid is the region of the bacterial cell which lacks a limiting membrane and contains the bacterial chromosome. BacteriaI circular dsDNA molecule is associated with polyamines instead of histone proteins."
    },
    {
        "id": 338,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the nucleotide associated protein?",
        "Options": [
            "a) HSP",
            "b) HU",
            "c) H-NS",
            "d) IHF"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Nucleoid associated proteins are of four types which facilitates compaction of chromosomal DNA by bending, bridging, and wrapping i.e. HU is heat unstable protein, H-NS is histone-like nucleoid structuring, IHF stands for integration host factor, and SMC is structural maintenance protein."
    },
    {
        "id": 339,
        "Question": "Which nucleoid protein assisted in condensation of DNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) SMC",
            "b) IHF",
            "c) HU",
            "d) H-NS"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: H-NS protein helps in condensation of DNA by first binding with the DNA and then these proteins bind with each other and form an aggregate of four or more H-NS units."
    },
    {
        "id": 340,
        "Question": "Name the group of bacteria which uses histone to condense DNA molecule?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spirochetes",
            "b) Archaebacteria",
            "c) Mycoplasma",
            "d) Cyanobacteria"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Prokaryotes like E.coli has only one single circular DNA molecule composed of entire genome while rest contains multiple linear or circular DNA. Like, vibrio cholerae contains two circular chromosomes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 341,
        "Question": "Extrachromosomal DNA present in prokaryotes is called_______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cocci group of bacteria",
            "b) Chainlike group of bacteria",
            "c) Plasmid",
            "d) Grapelike cluster of bacteria"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Archaebacteria is a group of prokaryotes which resembles eukaryotes in some aspect and differs from the bacterial group. Archaeans uses eukaryotes like histones to condense their DNA molecules."
    },
    {
        "id": 342,
        "Question": "Name the plasmid which makes host cell resistance to the antibiotic.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hfr",
            "b) F-plasmid",
            "c) Col plasmid",
            "d) R-plasmid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Plasmids are extrachromosomal, autonomous, and self-replicating DNA molecule that maintains discrete genetic element in bacteria. Most plasmids are negatively supercoiled, circular dsDNA molecules but linear plasmids have also been reported."
    },
    {
        "id": 343,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT the property of plasmid?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rolling circle replication",
            "b) Narrow host range",
            "c) Two closely related plasmids cannot coexist in the same cell",
            "d) Encodes gene products that are essential for growth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: R plasmid stands for resistance plasmid which makes cell resistant to antibiotics. They have genes which code for enzymes that are capable of destroying or modifying antibiotics."
    },
    {
        "id": 344,
        "Question": "Name the type of plasmid which has no identified function or phenotypic properties?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cryptic plasmid",
            "b) R-plasmid",
            "c) High-frequency recombination",
            "d) Col plasmid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Plasmids can have narrow as well as broad host range as when it exists only in a limited number of closely related bacteria, it shows narrow host range while if it transferred to and maintained in a large number of bacteria, it shows broad host range."
    },
    {
        "id": 345,
        "Question": "Which of the following plasmid found in eukaryotes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Col plasmid",
            "b) 2μ circle",
            "c) F-plasmid",
            "d) Hfr"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cryptic plasmids do not code for genes that contribute any phenotypic properties or identified functions. They have no clear use for organisms in which they were identified.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 346,
        "Question": "Name the type of bacteria which uses Co2 as a sole source of carbon for growth.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Organotrophs",
            "b) Heterotrophs",
            "c) Autotrophs",
            "d) Lithotrophs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Bacterial nutrition divides bacteria into different classes, on the basis of carbon sources these are divided into two classes i.e. autotrophs and heterotrophs. Autotrophs use carbon dioxide as a sole source of carbon while heterotrophs utilize organic carbon."
    },
    {
        "id": 347,
        "Question": "Name those bacteria which obtain energy from chemical compounds?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chemotrophs",
            "b) Phototrophs",
            "c) Organotrophs",
            "d) Heterotrophs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Living organisms need a source of energy for survival, bacteria has been divided into two categories on the basis of the source of energy i.e. phototrophs which need light as their energy source and chemotrophs obtain energy from the oxidation of chemical compounds."
    },
    {
        "id": 348,
        "Question": "Name the type of bacteria which uses reduced inorganic substances as an electron source?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Autotrophs",
            "b) Chemotrophs",
            "c) Organotrophs",
            "d) Lithotrophs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Bacteria which uses reduced inorganic substances as their electron sources are called lithotrophs while organotrophs are the bacterial class which utilizes organic compounds as their electron source."
    },
    {
        "id": 349,
        "Question": "Which of the following bacteria does not belong to photolithoautotrophy nutritional class?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thiomargarita namibiensis",
            "b) Purple sulfur bacteria",
            "c) Blue-green bacteria",
            "d) Green sulfur bacteria"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Photolithoautotrophy is the class of the bacteria which utilize CO2 as a carbon source, light energy as the energy source, and inorganic hydrogen as the electron source."
    },
    {
        "id": 350,
        "Question": "Purple and green non-sulfur bacteria belongs to which of the following classes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Photolithoautotrophy",
            "b) Photoorganohetrotrophy",
            "c) Chemolithoautotrophy",
            "d) Chemoorganohetrotrophy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Purple and green non-sulfur bacteria use light energy as an energy source, organic carbon source, and organic hydrogen as the source of an electron."
    },
    {
        "id": 351,
        "Question": "Nitrifying bacteria belongs to the nutritional class of_______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chemoorganoautotrophy",
            "b) Photolithoautrophy",
            "c) Chemolithoautotrophy",
            "d) Photoorganohetrotrophy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Nitrifying bacteria include species of Nitrosomonas, Nitrococcus, Nitrobactor, and Nitrococcus. These are chemolithoautotrophic organisms which get energy by oxidation of inorganic nitrogen compounds."
    },
    {
        "id": 352,
        "Question": "Which of the following species falls under the category of hydrogen-producing bacteria?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thiobacillus thiooxidans",
            "b) Nitrosomonas europaea",
            "c) Nitrobacter winogradskyi",
            "d) Alkaligenes eutrophus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Alkaligenes eutrophus are gram-negative, aerobic, and rod-shaped bacteria and is classified as hydrogen-producing bacteria."
    },
    {
        "id": 353,
        "Question": "Which of these is NOT a selective media?",
        "Options": [
            "a)  Blood agar",
            "b) Eosin methylene blue agar",
            "c) MacConkey agar",
            "d) Mannitol salt agar"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A complex media is undefined in which the exact chemical composition of the medium is not known while the synthetic medium is the culture medium whose exact chemical composition should be known."
    },
    {
        "id": 354,
        "Question": "Name the protein which plays an important role in cell division?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Actin",
            "b) FtsZ",
            "c) HSP",
            "d) HU"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Selective media are those which prevent the growth of other types of bacteria and promote the growth of only desired species. "
    },
    {
        "id": 355,
        "Question": "What is the basic taxonomic unit?",
        "Options": [
            "a) RNA",
            "b) Phylogenetic tree",
            "c) Species",
            "d) Cell"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Species are the basic taxonomic unit; it is assigned to a genus. In eukaryotes, the species are the group of similar organisms which reproduce. Bacterial species identified as a group of organisms having similar phenotypic properties."
    },
    {
        "id": 356,
        "Question": "What is numerical taxonomy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Determine phenetic relationships among organisms",
            "b) Determine phylogenetic relationships",
            "c) Determine numbers of phylogenetic tree",
            "d) Determine evolutionary tree on the number of genus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Numerical taxonomy was given by Sokal and Sneath. It determines the relationships among organisms on the basis of their phenetic system. It is summarized with a tree diagram called dendrogram."
    },
    {
        "id": 357,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not used to determine DNA relatedness in the phylogenetic system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thermal stability of related DNA",
            "b) Genome size",
            "c) GC content",
            "d) Amino acid sequences"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: DNA relatedness can be determined by following five factors: GC content, genome size, the thermal stability of related DNA sequences, DNA relatedness when the condition is optimal for DNA reassociation, and DNA relatedness when the condition is superoptimal for DNA reassociation."
    },
    {
        "id": 358,
        "Question": "The collective study of genotypic, chemotaxonomic, and phenotypic method is________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polyphasic approach",
            "b) Numerical taxonomy",
            "c) Bacterial taxonomy",
            "d) Phylogenetic approach"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Polyphasic approach is a grouping of organisms on the basis of the physiological, morphological, and biochemical feature. It is a most popular approach currently for classifying bacteria."
    },
    {
        "id": 359,
        "Question": "What is the causative agent of Q-fever?",
        "Options": [
            "a) R. typhi",
            "b) Coxiella burnetii",
            "c) Plasmodium",
            "d) Mycobacterium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Coxiella brunetii is gram-negative, non-motile, and obligate intracellular parasites which belong to the class of rickettsias. These organisms grow and reproduce within a host cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 360,
        "Question": "Name the bacteria which are responsible for the odor of moist soil.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mycoplasma",
            "b) Borelia burgdorferi",
            "c) Streptomyces",
            "d) Cyanobacteria"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Streptomyces belongs to the class of actinomycetes, which are strict aerobes, non-pathogenic and bear the nonmotile conidia. Streptomyces produces a volatile substance i.e. geosmin which gives an odor of moist soil."
    },
    {
        "id": 361,
        "Question": "Name the causative agent of syphilis.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mycobacteria",
            "b) Streptococcus",
            "c) Pseudomonas",
            "d) Treponema palladium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Treponema palladium is an example of the spirochete, which causes syphilis. Spirochetes are gram-negative, helical shape, and chemoheterotrophic bacteria which exhibit creeping or crawling movements."
    },
    {
        "id": 362,
        "Question": "Mark the INCORRECT statement about cyanobacteria.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gram-negative bacteria",
            "b) Photolithoautotrophic organism",
            "c) They do not have a fully functional citric acid cycle",
            "d) Reproduce only by binary fission"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cyanobacteria are gram-negative, oxygenic photosynthetic organisms. It can reproduce by binary fission as well as budding and multiple fission."
    },
    {
        "id": 363,
        "Question": "The ability of an organism to resist infections by the pathogens is called___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Infection",
            "b) Hypersensitivity",
            "c) Immunity",
            "d) Allergy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Immunity is the ability of an organism to resist infections with the help of the immune system. Immunity is further divided into two categories, i.e. innate immunity and adaptive immunity."
    },
    {
        "id": 364,
        "Question": "Which of the following compounds is NOT found in tears?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lysozyme",
            "b) Lactoferin",
            "c) IgA",
            "d) IgE"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Innate immunity is the natural immunity, which is present for the birth and it operated against any foreign molecules and pathogens. It provides the first line of defense and is not specific in nature."
    },
    {
        "id": 365,
        "Question": "Name the cytokines which released in response to virus infection?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Interferons",
            "b) Monokines",
            "c) Lymphokines",
            "d) Interleukins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: IgE participates in hypersensitivity reactions, but not present in tears. Tears are the secretion of lacrimal gland and also know as lacrimal fluid consists of lysozyme, lactoferrin, and IgA."
    },
    {
        "id": 366,
        "Question": "Name the group of pattern recognition molecules which functions exclusively as a signaling receptor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CRP",
            "b) Toll-like receptor",
            "c) MBL",
            "d) LPS"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Monokines, lymphokines,  interleukins, and interferons are cytokines which are of low molecular weight soluble protein or glycoprotein. Interferon is cytokines produced by cells in response to virus infections."
    },
    {
        "id": 367,
        "Question": "Name the first cell which recruited at the place of infection.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nk cells",
            "b) Basophils",
            "c) Nutrophils",
            "d) Macrophages"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Toll-like receptor functions exclusively as a signaling receptor and is a pattern recognition molecule. It was identified as a protein involved in the formation of dorso-ventral polarity in developing fly embryos."
    },
    {
        "id": 368,
        "Question": "Name the nerve stimulator which is responsible for the pain of the inflammation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bradikinins",
            "b) Prostaglandin",
            "c) Histamines",
            "d) Kinins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Neutrophils are second major type of phagocytic cell which is found in abundance in blood and have short life span."
    },
    {
        "id": 369,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT the characteristics of a good antigen.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Large in size",
            "b) Foreignness",
            "c) Highly complex",
            "d) Reproduce only by binary fission"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Kinins are the principal mediator of inflammatory response which is present in blood plasma in an inactive form. It causes vasodilation and increased permeability of capillaries."
    },
    {
        "id": 370,
        "Question": "Which of the following antibody gives a primary immune reaction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) IgG",
            "b) IgM",
            "c) IgA",
            "d) IgE"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A good antigen is defined by its complexity and size, plus its foreignness and dosage. Large size and highly complex antigen are considered as good and more responsive."
    },
    {
        "id": 371,
        "Question": "Which of these is NOT  a characteristic feature of adaptive immunity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Immunogenic memory",
            "b) Antigen no-specific",
            "c) Self/ non-self recognition",
            "d) Diversity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The first class of antibody which provide a primary immune response is IgM followed by IgG. When the same antigen attack again, the secondary immune response generated which is provided by IgG.   "
    },
    {
        "id": 372,
        "Question": "Which of the following cell is a multipotent cell?",
        "Options": [
            "a) T-cell",
            "b) B-cell",
            "c) HSC",
            "d) Monocytes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hematopoitic stem cell (HSC) can give rise to a number of cells by following two pathways and known as a multipotent cell. One pathway gives lymphoid progenitor cell while others give myeloid progenitor cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 373,
        "Question": "Mark the one, which is NOT a lymphoid progenitor cell.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Monocyte",
            "b) B-cell",
            "c) T-cell",
            "d) NK cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Monocyte is a myeloid progenitor cell and is a part of white blood cells. B-cells, T-cells, and NK cells are lymphoid progenitor cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 374,
        "Question": "What is the origin of B-cell?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pancreas",
            "b) Liver",
            "c) Thymus",
            "d) Bone marrow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The origin and maturation of B-cell take place in the bone marrow itself while in birds B-cells originate from bone marrow but mature in the bursa of fabricius."
    },
    {
        "id": 375,
        "Question": "Chediak-Higashi syndrome is caused due to deficiency of_________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nutrophils",
            "b) Nk cells",
            "c) Basophils",
            "d) Mast cell"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: NK cells are natural killer cells, which use perforin and granzyme to kill the target cell. They can destroy malignant and virus infected cells even without the prior exposure to antigen, hence they can kill their target even without specific antigen."
    },
    {
        "id": 376,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT polymorphonuclear leukocytes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Eosinophils",
            "b) Mast cell",
            "c) Macrophages",
            "d) Basophils"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Chediak-Higashi syndrome is an autosomal recessive disorder which is caused by the deficiency of NK cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 377,
        "Question": "Which of the following cells has a high affinity receptor for IgE?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dendritic cell",
            "b) Mast cells",
            "c) Eosinophils",
            "d) Basophils"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Polymorphonuclear leukocytes are those that have irregular-shaped nuclei with more than two lobes. Their cytoplasmic matrix is rich in substances which can kill microorganisms and increase inflammation."
    },
    {
        "id": 378,
        "Question": "Name the macrophages which are associated central nervous system.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alveolar macrophages",
            "b) Kupffer cell",
            "c) Mesangial",
            "d) Microglial cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Basophils are non-phagocytic cells, which releases substance that causes an allergic responses. These substances are histamine, prostaglandins, serotonins etc. It has a high affinity for IgE."
    },
    {
        "id": 379,
        "Question": "Name the molecule which constitutively expressed on the dendritic cell?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Class I MHC",
            "b) Class II MHC",
            "c) APC",
            "d) Antigen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Macrophages are phagocytic in nature and is derived from blood monocytes. They have a variety of forms like kupffer cells in the liver, mesangial in the kidney, and alveolar macrophages in the lung. "
    },
    {
        "id": 380,
        "Question": "Name the dendritic cell, which does not function as antigen presenting cell?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Follicular dendritic cell",
            "b) Langerhans cell",
            "c) Myeloid dendritic cell",
            "d) Lymphoid dendritic cell"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Dendritic cells arise from both myeloid and lymphoid lineages. Inspite of their differences, they all express high level of class II MHC and act as an antigen presenting cells.   "
    },
    {
        "id": 381,
        "Question": "Major Histocompatibility Complex is a tight cluster of linked___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Carbohydrates",
            "b) Proteins",
            "c) Genes",
            "d) Lipid molecules"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: MHC is polygenic in nature, i.e. several genes control the expression of the MHC molecule. These are cell surface proteins which are present with peptide on antigen presenting cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 382,
        "Question": "What is the name of MHC in humans?",
        "Options": [
            "a) HLA",
            "b) H2",
            "c) Adjuvants",
            "d) Haplotype"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Genes for MHC are located on the short arm of chromosome 6 in humans. In human, it is also known as human leukocyte antigens (HLA). MHC is glycoproteins which are expressed on all nucleated cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 383,
        "Question": "Which of the following polypeptide is important for the expression of MHC I on the cell membrane?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Interferons",
            "b) β2-microglobin",
            "c) Lymphokines",
            "d) Interleukins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: MHC is polymorphic in nature and shows genetic polymorphism by expressing different alleles of a gene. Different individuals have different types of MHC genes. MHC genes are expressed as codominantly."
    },
    {
        "id": 384,
        "Question": "Which of these are non-professional antigen presenting cells?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Macrophages",
            "b) Dendritic cells",
            "c) Fibroblast",
            "d) B lymphocytes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: β2-microglobin is encoded by chromosome 15, it is always attached to α3 subunit of MHC I molecules through non-covalent interactions. It does not have a tail."
    },
    {
        "id": 385,
        "Question": "Name the cell which receives antigen presented by MHC molecule.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nk cells",
            "b) B-cells",
            "c) T-cells",
            "d) Macrophages"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Antigen presenting cells (APC) is of two types i.e. professional and non-professional antigen presenting cells. Professional antigen presenting cells are B-lymphocytes, dendritic cells, and macrophages while non-professional APCs are fibroblast, epithelial cells, glial cells etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 386,
        "Question": "Name the class of MHC which is recognized by CD4 TH cell.",
        "Options": [
            "a) MHC cannot recognize T cells",
            "b) MHC III",
            "c) MHC I",
            "d) MHC II"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  MHC molecules present processed antigen to T-cells as T-cell receptor does not recognize free antigen, it will recognize only those antigens which are bound to MHC molecules."
    },
    {
        "id": 387,
        "Question": "Which MHC molecule recognizes CD8 TC cells?",
        "Options": [
            "a) MHC I",
            "b) MHC II",
            "c) MHC III",
            "d) HLA-C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: CD4 is a monomeric single chain which recognizes MHC II molecule and is present on T helper cell. It consists of a core extracellular domain and has three critical serine residues on a cytoplasmic tail."
    },
    {
        "id": 388,
        "Question": "Name the part of processed antigen that binds to the MHC molecule and recognized by T-cells?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Immunoglobulin",
            "b) Agretope",
            "c) Epitope",
            "d) Chaperone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: CD8 is a co-receptor of T-cell and is present on the T cytosolic cell. It is a hetrodimer of α and β chains and recognizes MHC I molecule."
    },
    {
        "id": 389,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is INCORRECT about superantigens?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Viral or bacterial proteins",
            "b) Endogenous by nature",
            "c) Unique binding ability",
            "d) Activate a large number of T-cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Agretope is the part of processed antigen that is attached to MHC molecule and exposed to T-cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 390,
        "Question": "Synthesis of antibodies takes place by which of the following cells?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bone marrow cells",
            "b) T-cells",
            "c) B-cells",
            "d) Lymph"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Antibodies are also called immunoglobulin, the antigen- binding glycoproteins, which are exclusively synthesized by B-cells and in billions of forms with different amino acid sequences and different antigen binding sites."
    },
    {
        "id": 391,
        "Question": "The basic structure of antibodies are______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Y-shaped",
            "b) X-shaped",
            "c) Linear",
            "d) Hyperbolic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The simple antibody structure has two identical antigen-binding sites forming a Y-shaped molecule. These antigen-binding sites are present on the tip of each arm of the Y."
    },
    {
        "id": 392,
        "Question": "Name the heavy chain of immunoglobulin G.",
        "Options": [
            "a) μ",
            "b) ε",
            "c) α",
            "d) γ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Immunoglobulin has five isotopes with different heavy chains, i.e. IgM has a μ heavy chain, IgE has ε, IgA has α, and IgG has a γ heavy chain."
    },
    {
        "id": 393,
        "Question": "What is the name of the hypervariable region of immunoglobin, which is responsible for its diversity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CDR",
            "b) Hinge region",
            "c) Epitope",
            "d) Agretope"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: CDR is complementarity determining regions which impart the diversity in the variable region of both heavy and light chains. These are three small hypervariable regions and remaining part is called framework region."
    },
    {
        "id": 394,
        "Question": "Who discovered the structure of immunoglobulin by treating it with beta-mercaptoethanol?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nisonoff",
            "b) Edelman",
            "c) Porter",
            "d) Whittekar"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Edelman discovered that when immunoglobulin treated with beta-mercaptoethanol, it will fall apart into four chains, i.e. two identical light chain and two large heavy chains. This result was considered to propose a structure of immunoglobulin."
    },
    {
        "id": 395,
        "Question": "Which of the following amino acid is found in the hinge region?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alanine",
            "b) Aspargine",
            "c) Proline and cysteine",
            "d) Phenylalanine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hinge region is found in IgG, IgA, and IgD to provide flexibility in its structure. These regions are rich in proline and cysteine and basically found between two Fab arms of the Y-shaped antibody.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 396,
        "Question": "Which immunoglobulin can pass through placenta?",
        "Options": [
            "a) IgD",
            "b) IgE",
            "c) IgM",
            "d) IgG"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: IgG is the only antibody which can pass through the placenta, except IgG2 all other subtypes of IgG can cross the placenta and transfer immunity from mother to fetus."
    },
    {
        "id": 397,
        "Question": "Name the class of immunoglobulin which has a pentameric structure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) IgE",
            "b) IgG",
            "c) IgA",
            "d) IgM"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: IgM is the first antibody to produce during the primary response to antigen and it is also the first antibody which is made by the developing B-cells. It is composed of five units and formed pentameric structure with a J-chain."
    },
    {
        "id": 398,
        "Question": "Which of these immunoglobulins is present in external secretion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) IgG",
            "b) IgM",
            "c) IgA",
            "d) IgE"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: IgA is the predominant immunoglobulin which is present in the external secretion such as saliva, breast feed, tears, and mucus. It constitutes 10-15% of total immunoglobin in serum.   "
    },
    {
        "id": 399,
        "Question": "Name the class of immunoglobulin which takes part in hypersensitivity reaction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) IgG",
            "b) IgE",
            "c) IgA",
            "d) IgM"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: IgE mediates hypersensitivity reaction which is responsible for the symptoms of hay fever, asthma, and anaphylactic shock. It includes degranulation of basophils and mast cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 400,
        "Question": "Which of the following is responsible for B-cell activation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Infection",
            "b) Antibody",
            "c) Antigen",
            "d) Allergy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The activation of mature B-cell is done by antigen. When antigen come in contact with B-cells, it undergoes clonal proliferation and divided into memory cells and plasma cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 401,
        "Question": "What is the meaning of thymus independent B-cell activation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Without the participation of T-cell",
            "b) Do not mature in the thymus",
            "c) Thymus would not take part in its activation",
            "d) Affinity maturation takes place in the thymus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In thymus independent B-cell pathway, antigen activates B-cell without the participation of TH cell. Response generated by thymus independent antigens only generate IgM and do not give rise to memory."
    },
    {
        "id": 402,
        "Question": "Which of the following acts as a coreceptor for B-cell activation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CD28",
            "b) IL-2",
            "c) IgA",
            "d) CD19"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: CD19, CD81, and CD21 are present on the B-cell membrane and known as a B-cell coreceptor. These receptors are used to determine a cell’s identity and for transducing signals."
    },
    {
        "id": 403,
        "Question": "Out of these, which transcription factor does not take part in B-cell activation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Abl",
            "b) NF- kB",
            "c) Jun",
            "d) Fos"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Transcription factors like NF-AT, CREB, JUN, FOS, and AP-1  promote gene expression required for B-cell proliferation into a plasma cell and the memory cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 404,
        "Question": "Hybridoma technology is used to produce___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Interferons",
            "b) Monoclonal antibodies",
            "c) Antibodies",
            "d) Immune response"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is a method which is used for the production of hybridoma of B-cells. This hybridoma B-cell later used for the production of monoclonal antibodies. Monoclonal antibodies are highly specific against a single epitope of the antigen."
    },
    {
        "id": 405,
        "Question": "Name the drug which is used to isolate hybridoma cells from the media?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Amphetamine",
            "b) Opium",
            "c) Aminopterin",
            "d) Cocaine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Aminopterin inhibits dHFR enzyme and block denovo pathway of nucleotide synthesis, which further allow the survival of only hybridoma cells and B-cells in HAT media."
    },
    {
        "id": 406,
        "Question": "Name the most commonly used monoclonal antibody for treatment of breast cancer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bradikinins",
            "b) Prostaglandin",
            "c) Erbutir",
            "d) Herceptin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Monoclonal antibodies are specific against the particular antigen and these are used to treat the cancer as they release their toxins in the growing cells which interfere with their cellular processes. Herceptin is particularly for breast cancer while erbutir is for colorectal cancer."
    },
    {
        "id": 407,
        "Question": "Mark the one which is NOT used in generating antibody diversity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Combinatorial V(D)J joining",
            "b) Juntional and insertional diversification",
            "c) Somatic hypermutation",
            "d) Binary fission"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Different classes of antibodies have variable amino acid sequences at the N-terminal end which interacts with different types of antigens. Four theories have been proposed for generating antibody diversity. "
    },
    {
        "id": 408,
        "Question": "Which of the tracing is NOT the role of T-cell receptor complex?",
        "Options": [
            "a) α and β chain",
            "b) CD3",
            "c) CD19",
            "d) CD40L"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: CD19 is a co-receptor of B-cell receptor complex while T-cell receptor complex consists of antigen recognizing α and β chains, expressed on the surface of T-cell in noncovalent association with CD3 molecule. CD40L and CD28 are co-stimulatory molecules."
    },
    {
        "id": 409,
        "Question": "Name the syndrome occurs in children due to deficiency of the thymus.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acromegaly",
            "b) Gigantism",
            "c) Cushing syndrome",
            "d) DiGeorge syndrome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: CD3 is present with antigen recognizing α and β chain of TCR; these molecules do not bind with antigen instead of transduce signals after the activation."
    },
    {
        "id": 410,
        "Question": "Which of the following steps is NOT involved in the activation of T-cell?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Double positive cell converts to single positive T-cell",
            "b) Foreign peptide bound to MHC provide signals",
            "c) CD28 of TCR interacts with B7 of APC",
            "d) CD23 has ITAM, which transducer signals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Thymus is required for the development of T-cells. Children which are born without thymus undergo adverse effects of not having matured T-cells; this syndrome is known as DiGeorge syndrome."
    },
    {
        "id": 411,
        "Question": "Name the cytokines which act as a T-cell growth factor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) IL-3",
            "b) IL-2",
            "c) IL-4",
            "d) IL-5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The conversion of double positive cells to a single positive cell is thymic selection process in which T-cell mature with the interaction of MHC and develops the tolerance to self-antigen."
    },
    {
        "id": 412,
        "Question": "Cytokinin which acts as a growth factor of B-cell is________",
        "Options": [
            "a) IFNγ",
            "b) IL-10",
            "c) IL-13",
            "d) TNFβ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cytokines released by T-helper cells and have several functions like IL-2 act as T-cell growth factor while IL-4 and IL-5 help in B-cell activation, IL-3 involved in hematopoiesis and secreted by both TH1 and TH2 subset of T-helper cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 413,
        "Question": "Mark the correct role of cytosolic T-cells.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Help in B-cell activation",
            "b) Produce cytotoxin",
            "c) Proliferate T-cell",
            "d) Kill the target cell"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: IL-13 is secreted by TH2 and act as B-cell growth factor while IL-10 inhibits macrophages, while IFNγ and TNFβ secreted by TH1 and used to activate macrophages and inflammatory responses."
    },
    {
        "id": 414,
        "Question": "Name the major constituents of cytotoxic T-lymphocyte?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lysozyme",
            "b) Lymph",
            "c) Protein",
            "d) Perforin and granzyme"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cytotoxic T-cell (CTL) once activated it initiate killing of target cells by attaching to it. After interaction with a target cell, it undergoes conjugate formation with the help of calcium. The killing action is performed by cytotoxic substances contained in granules of T-cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 415,
        "Question": "Which one of the following is NOT covered under Taxonomy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alpha taxonomy",
            "b) Beta taxonomy",
            "c) Delta taxonomy",
            "d) Gamma taxonomy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Taxonomy has been divided into three level alpha, beta, and gamma. Alpha taxonomy deals with the organism, beta taxonomy involve identification of biological classes while gamma taxonomy includes the study of evolutionary patterns."
    },
    {
        "id": 416,
        "Question": "Organizing taxonomic information in logical classification is called_________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Systematics",
            "b) Phenetic",
            "c) Phylogenetic",
            "d) Dendogram"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Systematics is the process where taxonomic information of organisms is organized into a logical framework. Taxonomy and systematic are together referred to as systematic biology."
    },
    {
        "id": 417,
        "Question": "Name the philosopher who first classified organisms?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Whittekar",
            "b) Carl woese",
            "c) Linnaeus",
            "d) Aristotle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Aristotle was a Greek philosopher, who first classified organisms as either plant or animals. Modern biological classification has given five kingdoms."
    },
    {
        "id": 418,
        "Question": "Name the organization which provides rules for naming animals.",
        "Options": [
            "a) ICZN",
            "b) ICN",
            "c) ICBN",
            "d) IBM"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Nomeclature of organisms is done according to some particular standards like ICBN is international Code of Botanical nomenclature which deals with the naming of plants, algae, and fungi while ICZN is the International Code of Zoological nomeclature which provides rules for naming animals. "
    },
    {
        "id": 419,
        "Question": "Who is considered as the father of taxonomy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aristotle",
            "b) Linnaeus",
            "c) Earnst Haeckel",
            "d) Whittaker"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Linnaeus is a Swedish botanist who first proposed the system of binomial nomenclature and is considered as the father of taxonomy. According to this nomenclature, the first name is the genus name followed by the name of the species."
    },
    {
        "id": 420,
        "Question": "What is tautonym?",
        "Options": [
            "a) These are the repeated sequences",
            "b) It is a name of fish",
            "c) Identical name of genus and species",
            "d) It is a name of the genus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Tautonym are those where the name of genus and species are identical like Katla katla is the name of fish which belongs to the genus Katla."
    },
    {
        "id": 421,
        "Question": "What is the term given to a duplicate specimen of original type?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lectotype",
            "b) Holotype",
            "c) Isotype",
            "d) Neotype"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Classification is the arrangement of steps represents a category terms rank or taxonomic category. Each organism is classified according to the seven taxonomic ranks."
    },
    {
        "id": 422,
        "Question": "Which of these is an example of homoplasy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Presence and absence of hair",
            "b) Wings of birds and bats",
            "c) Forelimbs of humans",
            "d) Leg of a dog and flipper of a dolphin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A nomenclature type is a particular specimen of an organism to which its scientific name is attached. Type should be placed in a museum or herbarium research collection. Isotype is duplicate of holotype, the holotype is an original specimen. "
    },
    {
        "id": 423,
        "Question": "Who proposed five kingdom systems?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ernst Mayr",
            "b) R.H. Whittaker",
            "c) Robert Hook",
            "d) Aristotle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Robert H. Whittaker in 1969 proposed a five kingdom classification, i.e. Monera, Protista, Fungi, Plantae, and Animalia. Prokaryotes placed in separate kingdom Monera."
    },
    {
        "id": 424,
        "Question": "Which of these eukaryotes is a single-celled organism?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Protists",
            "b) Fungi",
            "c) Monera",
            "d) Plantae"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Protists are mainly unicellular eukaryotic organism (some are multicellular), possess single cell. Due to the great diversity of this kingdom, protists are difficult to characterize."
    },
    {
        "id": 425,
        "Question": "Which of the following is considered as fungus-like protists?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cynobacteria",
            "b) Protozoa",
            "c) Algae",
            "d) Slime molds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Protists have been divided into three categories, i.e. plant-like, animal-like, and fungi-like. Plant-like protists are protozoa, animal-like are known as protozoa, and fungi-like protists are water molds and slime molds."
    },
    {
        "id": 426,
        "Question": "Name the causative agent of Leishmaniasis.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Leishmania donovani",
            "b) Trypnosoma brucei",
            "c) Trichomonas vaginalis",
            "d) Entamoeba histolytica"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Leishmaniasis is also known as kala azar and is caused by Leishmania donovani (Mastigophora). Trypnosoma brucei causes African sleeping sickness which is transmitted by Tsetse fly. Trichomonas vaginalis causes Trichomoniasis and amoebiasis is caused by Entamoeba histolytica."
    },
    {
        "id": 427,
        "Question": "Which of the following disease is caused by Trypanosoma palladium?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Balantidiasis",
            "b) Syphilis",
            "c) Giardiasis",
            "d) Malaria"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Trypanosoma palladium causes syphilis, it is a spirochete bacterium. Malaria is caused by Plasmodium and is carried by mosquitoes. Balantidiasis is caused by Ciliophora and Giardiasis is caused by Giardia lambila."
    },
    {
        "id": 428,
        "Question": "Which of these photosynthetic protists have whirling whips?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slime molds",
            "b) Euglenophyta",
            "c) Dinoflagellates",
            "d) Diatoms"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Dinoflagellates are unicellular and flagellated organisms which are mainly found in the marine ecosystem. Flagella show spinning type locomotion so, they are known as whirling whips."
    },
    {
        "id": 429,
        "Question": "Frustle is the name of cell wall present in______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slime molds",
            "b) Cyanobacteria",
            "c) Dinoflagellates",
            "d) Diatoms"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Diatoms are unicellular algae, which have glass-like wall made up of silicon dioxide embedded in the matrix. Their cell wall is a unique type and is known as frustle which is divided into epitheca and hypotheca."
    },
    {
        "id": 430,
        "Question": "Which of the following class has been shifted from kingdom fungi to protists?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oomycetes",
            "b) Slime molds",
            "c) Diatoms",
            "d) Euglenophyta"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Mixotrophic is the mode of nutrition in which an organism uses both autotrophic and heterotrophic mode of nutrition. When sunlight is available, they show autotrophic but in absence, they become heterotrophic by absorbing nutrient from their environment."
    },
    {
        "id": 431,
        "Question": "Name the causative agent of late blight of potato.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cyanobacteria",
            "b) Dictyostelium discoideum",
            "c) Phytophthora infestans",
            "d) Diatoms"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Oomycetes means egg fungus, it includes water molds, downey mildew, and the white rust. Unlike fungi, they do not have a cell wall made up of chitin so, the oomycetes has been shifted from kingdom fungi to the kingdom protists."
    },
    {
        "id": 432,
        "Question": "Which of the following does NOT belong to the class of Cryptogamae (plant without seeds)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bryophytes",
            "b) Thallophyta",
            "c) Angiosperm",
            "d) Ptrediophytes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Plantae have photosynthetic nutrition and these are multicellular eukaryotes. It has been broadly classified into Cryptogamae means plant without seeds and Phanerogamae which means a plant with seeds."
    },
    {
        "id": 433,
        "Question": "Chlamydomonas is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Green algae",
            "b) Red algae",
            "c) Brown algae",
            "d) Lichens"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Green algae is also known as chlorophyta. These are photosynthetic algae contain chlorophyll a and b with carotenoids. "
    },
    {
        "id": 434,
        "Question": "Which of the following class of algae consists of alginic acid in their cell wall component?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Green algae",
            "b) Red algae",
            "c) Lichens",
            "d) Brown algae"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Brown algae or pheophyta is marine or fresh water algae. It consists of mainly chlorophyll a, and c along with fucoxanthin and carotenoids. Their cell wall consists of cellulose, sulfated polysaccharides, and alginic acid."
    },
    {
        "id": 435,
        "Question": "Which of the following spores is motile in nature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zoospores",
            "b) Oomycetes",
            "c) Aplanospores",
            "d) Hepdnaspores"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Haploid spores are produced from diploid spores by the process of meiosis. It will produce either motile spores or nonmotile spores. Motile spores are called zoospores while nonmotile spores are aplanospores."
    },
    {
        "id": 436,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a seedless vascular plant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gymnosperm",
            "b) Bryophytes",
            "c) Pteridophytes",
            "d) Angiosperm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Bryophytes are also known as amphibian of plants. They have jacketed and multicellular sex organs. Female sex organ is called archaegonia which first appeared in bryophyte and is of flask shaped."
    },
    {
        "id": 437,
        "Question": "Which of the following is also known as fruitless plants?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pteridophyte",
            "b) Bryophytes",
            "c) Angiosperm",
            "d) Gymnosperm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Pteridophytes are seedless plants with vascular structure, long lived and highly branched. Their life cycle is dominated by sporophyte. They also produce haploid spores by meiosis."
    },
    {
        "id": 438,
        "Question": "Double fertilization is a characteristic feature of which of these groups of plants?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chlorophyta",
            "b) Thallophyta",
            "c) Angiosperm",
            "d) Bryophytes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Gymnosperm is vascular plants whose seeds are not covered by the ripened ovary (fruit). These are basically woody plants and considered as fruitless plants."
    },
    {
        "id": 439,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT the part of four whorls of flower leaves?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Calyx",
            "b) Corolla",
            "c) Androcium",
            "d) Stem"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Angiosperms are flowering plants which are a major group of plants. Double fertilization is the characteristic of angiosperm plants, produce embryo as well as endosperm."
    },
    {
        "id": 440,
        "Question": "Melia, a flower has a pistil of two or more fused carpels, which of the following condition describe this?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One carpel",
            "b) Fused carpel",
            "c) Fused androcium",
            "d) One androcium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A flower has four types of structures called four whorls i.e. nonessential whorls (Calyx and Corolla) and essential whorls (gynocium and androcium). "
    },
    {
        "id": 441,
        "Question": "11. Match the correct columns.<div class=\"hk1_style-wrap4\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap3\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap2\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap\"><div class=\"hk1_style\"><div class=\"text\"><pre class=\"de1\"> 1 - Adelphous                            A - Anther of different stamen is infused state\n 2 - Syngansious                          B - Filament of different stamen is fused\n 3 - Synandrous                           C - Stamen is attached to the petals\n 4 - Epipelalous                          D - Anther and filament both are fused</pre></div></div></div></div></div></div>",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1-B, 2-A, 3-D, 4-C",
            "b) 1-D, 2-C, 3-A, 4-B",
            "c) 1-C, 2-A, 3-B, 4-D",
            "d) 1-A, 2-D, 3-B, 4-C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Gynoecium is divided into simple and compound. Simple gynoecium is made up of only one carpel e.g. pea. Compound gynoecium is the one in which pistil of two or more carples is fused e.g. Melia."
    },
    {
        "id": 442,
        "Question": "Which of the following condition is TRUE for Calotropis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Epiphyllous",
            "b) Gynandrous",
            "c) Epipetalous",
            "d) Synandrous"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sometimes a flower’s part is fused or attached to each other and this condition is known as coalescence of parts. It involves sepal, petal, stamen, and carpel."
    },
    {
        "id": 443,
        "Question": "Which of the following phylum is known for its asymmetrical body shape?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mollusca",
            "b) Arthropoda",
            "c) Annelida",
            "d) Porifera"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: These are multicellular life forms that have bodies brimming with pores and channels enabling water to circulate through them, comprising of jam like structure sandwiched between two thin layers of cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 444,
        "Question": "Name the phylum which has a single opening for taking food and throwing out faeces?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Coelenterate",
            "b) Porifera",
            "c) Annelida",
            "d) Aschelminthes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Organisms of this phylum have a single opening known as hypostome, used for both taking food and throwing out of faeces."
    },
    {
        "id": 445,
        "Question": "Name the organism which has flame-cell in its excretory system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Corals",
            "b) Ctenophora",
            "c) Roundworm",
            "d) Flatworm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A flame-cell is a specific excretory cell found in the easiest freshwater spineless creatures, including flatworm."
    },
    {
        "id": 446,
        "Question": "Which of the following is causative agent of Trichionosis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Trichinella spiralis",
            "b) Oxytricha trifallax",
            "c) Morus nigra",
            "d) Agrodiaetus shahrami"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Trichinosis is a disease caused by the roundworm Trichinella spiralis or another Trichinella species. Side effects incorporate the runs, stomach issues, muscle torments, and fever."
    },
    {
        "id": 447,
        "Question": "Intestinal fluke disease is caused by phylum__________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ctenophora",
            "b) Platyhelminthes",
            "c) Annelida",
            "d) Aschelminthes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Fasciolopsis is a family of trematodes. Just a single animal varieties are perceived: Fasciolopsis buski. It is a prominent parasite in people and in pigs."
    },
    {
        "id": 448,
        "Question": "Which organism has segmental nephridia for excretion and osmoregulation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Platyhelminthes",
            "b) Aschelminthes",
            "c) Annelida",
            "d) Arthropoda"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The nephridium is an invertebrate organ which happens in sets and plays out a capacity like the vertebrate kidney. Nephridia expel metabolic waste from their body. They are available in various invertebrate lines. "
    },
    {
        "id": 449,
        "Question": "Which of the following phylum has a water vascular system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Plantae",
            "b) Mollusca",
            "c) Echinodermata",
            "d) Hemichordata"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Moulting, otherwise called sloughing, shedding, or in numerous spineless creatures, ecdysis, is the way in which a creature routinely pushes off a piece of its body (however, not generally, an external layer or covering), either in particular circumstances of the year, or in particular focuses in its life cycle."
    },
    {
        "id": 450,
        "Question": "Name the phylum which is characterized by the presence of notochord.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chordata",
            "b) Hemichordata",
            "c) Echinodermata",
            "d) Mollusca"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Presence of water vascular system in echinodermata helps them in a capture, and transport of food and locomotion also helps in respiration. "
    },
    {
        "id": 451,
        "Question": "Name the first vertebrate which possessed amniotic egg?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Amphibia",
            "b) Aves",
            "c) Reptilia",
            "d) Mammalia"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  The notochord is a hollow nerve chord present at the dorsal site of organisms. Presence of notochord is the special character of the chordata. "
    },
    {
        "id": 452,
        "Question": "Which of the following is known as scavengers in the marine ecosystem?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lamprey",
            "b) Hagfish",
            "c) Scoliodon",
            "d) Pristis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The amniotic egg was a developmental creation that enabled the principal reptiles to colonize dry land in excess of 300 million years back. Fishes and creatures of land and water must lay their eggs in water and along these lines can’t live a long way from water. Be that as it may, on account of the amniotic egg, reptiles can lay their eggs about anyplace on dry land."
    },
    {
        "id": 453,
        "Question": "Who is known as the Father of Genetics?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Erich Tschemark",
            "b) Carl Correns",
            "c) Gregor Johann Mendel",
            "d) Hugo de Vries"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Gregor Johann Mendel was an Austrian monk, who is known as the Father of Genetics. He published the principle of inheritance in 1856 which are popularly known as Mendel’s law. The rest of the three biologist rediscovered Mendel’s work in 1900."
    },
    {
        "id": 454,
        "Question": "Mendel discovered factors which remain its identity in a hybrid, these factors are _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Genes",
            "b) Alleles",
            "c) DNA",
            "d) Chromosomes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Mendel discovered that individual traits retain their physical identity during hybrid formation when inherited as discrete factors. These factors are known as genes, which is also a unit of heredity."
    },
    {
        "id": 455,
        "Question": "Which of the following specimen was chosen by Mendel for his experiment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Drosophila",
            "b) Fly",
            "c) Rat",
            "d) Pisum sativum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Pisum sativum is commonly known as a garden pea. Mendel chose this species due to its various advantages."
    },
    {
        "id": 456,
        "Question": "Mark the INCORRECT statement about Pisum sativum?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Long life cycle",
            "b) Easy hybridization",
            "c) Bisexual flower",
            "d) Well-defined discrete characters"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Long life cycle is incorrect as pea has a relatively short life cycle and easy to cultivate. It also undergoes self fertilization process."
    },
    {
        "id": 457,
        "Question": "What is an allele?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Characteristics of an organism",
            "b) Alternate forms of genes",
            "c) Homologous chromosomes",
            "d) Pair of centrioles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Alleles are the alternate forms of genes present at the corresponding position on homologous chromosomes and maintain the same characteristics."
    },
    {
        "id": 458,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT Mendel’s law of inheritance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Law of dominance",
            "b) Law of segregation",
            "c) Law of hetrozygous",
            "d) Law of independent assortment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There are basically two types of genetics, one is forward genetics where the genotype is detected from the phenotype and the second one is reverse genetics where genotype inferred the phenotype of an organism."
    },
    {
        "id": 459,
        "Question": "Out of the following, which law is also known as the law of purity of gametes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Law of co-dominance",
            "b) Law of independent assortment",
            "c) Law of segregation",
            "d) Law of dominance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Law of hetrozygous is not the law of inheritance proposed by Mendel. Mendel had given three laws of inheritance which included law of dominance, law of segregation of gametes, and the law of independent assortment."
    },
    {
        "id": 460,
        "Question": "Name the cross by which law of independent assortment inferred.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dihybrid cross",
            "b) Monohybrid cross",
            "c) Test cross",
            "d) Back cross"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Law of segregation is also known as law of purity of gametes as gametes are always remained pure by separating the genes or factors at the time of gamete formation."
    },
    {
        "id": 461,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an example of incomplete dominance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) AB blood group",
            "b) Mirabilis jalapa",
            "c) Shape of crown in poultry",
            "d) Mouse coat colour"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Dihybrid cross is the cross which involves the analysis of two independent traits. This law shows that during gametogenesis, assortment of one pair of genes is independent to the other pair."
    },
    {
        "id": 462,
        "Question": "The Phenomenon of two or more than two genes affecting the expression of each other is called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Crossing over",
            "b) Pairing",
            "c) Gene interaction",
            "d) Linkage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Mendel described every character is influenced by the particular expression of the gene, but when the characters are controlled by the combination of more than one gene, called gene interaction."
    },
    {
        "id": 463,
        "Question": "Which of the following ratio shows complementary gene interaction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 9:7",
            "b) 15:1",
            "c) 1:2:1",
            "d) 9:3:3:1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Complementary gene interaction is first discovered by William Bateson and Reginald Punette in 1906. 9:7 ratio shows the 9 offspring have both dominant genes, while 7 is having either one dominant or both recessive."
    },
    {
        "id": 464,
        "Question": "Which of the following does not show Mendel’s law of inheritance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Masking gene interaction",
            "b) Epistasis",
            "c) Supplementary gene interaction",
            "d) Codominance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Codominance is the phenomenon where both the alleles of the gene pair in a heterozygote are expressed and resulting in offspring which is neither dominant nor recessive. Example: AB blood group."
    },
    {
        "id": 465,
        "Question": "What is epistasis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Type of linkage",
            "b) Masking or modifying gene effect",
            "c) Upper portion of a chromosome",
            "d) Group of genes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Two true varieties of white flowered plant crossed and result in purple color progeny which shows that there must be some enzyme secreted by both the dominant alleles which contributed in the color of the flowers."
    },
    {
        "id": 466,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT the type of epistasis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dominant",
            "b) Recessive",
            "c) Collabrative",
            "d) Supplementary"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is a non-allelic suppression which involves two pairs of alleles. It can suppress both dominant or recessive alleles."
    },
    {
        "id": 467,
        "Question": "Choose the correct ratio, which shows the masking gene interaction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12:3:1",
            "b) 9:3:4",
            "c) 1:2:1",
            "d) 9:7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Epistasis can be of many types based on the ability of an allele in masking and modification of gene effects. It can be of dominant, recessive, complementary or supplementary."
    },
    {
        "id": 468,
        "Question": "Name the phenomenon where two genes have the same expression of the character?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pleiotropy",
            "b) Phenocopy",
            "c) Penetrance",
            "d) Expressivity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Masking gene interaction is also recognized as dominant epistasis. Here, dominant allele of one gene can mask the effect of either allele of the second gene."
    },
    {
        "id": 469,
        "Question": "What is psudoallele?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Allele with similar function",
            "b) Allele with similar structure",
            "c) Alleles with similar function and structure",
            "d) Alleles with similar function and different structure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pleiotropy is the condition where either a single gene has multiple functions in the body or two genes have the same expression of the single character. "
    },
    {
        "id": 470,
        "Question": "Name the effect which shows the change in expression of alleles of the gene due to a specific environmental condition.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pleiotropy",
            "b) Linkage",
            "c) Phenocopy",
            "d) Penetrance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When two types of allele have similar functions but different structures, it is called pseudoallele. These genes located in close proximity."
    },
    {
        "id": 471,
        "Question": "The tendency of two or more than two genes to stay together during inheritance is called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Genetics",
            "b) Gene interaction",
            "c) Crossing over",
            "d) Linkage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Linkage is the tendency of two or more than two genes to stay together during the inheritance. It exists in two forms i.e. cis and trans."
    },
    {
        "id": 472,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is NOT true regarding linkage group?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Group of physically linked genes",
            "b) Represent a haploid number of chromosomes",
            "c) Shown by linkage map",
            "d) Linkage groups are not correlated with each other"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The linkage group refers to the group of genes physically linked together. The number of linkage group represents the haploid number of chromosomes in a species, i.e. the number of linkage group can be correlated as the number of homologous pairs."
    },
    {
        "id": 473,
        "Question": "What is the unit of linkage map?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Morgan",
            "b) Centi-morgan",
            "c) Centimeter",
            "d) Angstrom"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The linkage map is the representation of all the genes of a linkage group on a single line in the same order in which they are present on the chromosome."
    },
    {
        "id": 474,
        "Question": "What is the maximum percentage of recombination frequency between two genes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 75%",
            "b) 100%",
            "c) 50%",
            "d) 25%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The linkage maps are constructed by using recombination frequencies between genes which is determined by the test cross. The distance is measured from centi-morgan (cM), it represents the unit of the map."
    },
    {
        "id": 475,
        "Question": "Name the phenomenon which can break the occurrence of linkage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Crossing over",
            "b) Linkage",
            "c) Reconstruction",
            "d) Breakage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Recombination frequency is the measure of genetic linkage; it should not exceed 50%. The maximum limit of recombination is 50%."
    },
    {
        "id": 476,
        "Question": "Failure in which of the following phenomenon would result in linkage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Law of dominance",
            "b) Law of segregation",
            "c) Law of independent assortment",
            "d) Law of separation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Linkage can be broken by the process of homologous recombination (crossing over) which occurs at the pachytene stage of prophase I."
    },
    {
        "id": 477,
        "Question": "Name the organism whose first genetic map was made?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rat",
            "b) Arabidopsis",
            "c) Fly",
            "d) Drosophila"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Alignment of chromosomes in metaphase one will give two gametes, but a failure of independent assortment would result in the linkage of genes on the chromosomes."
    },
    {
        "id": 478,
        "Question": "Two genes are 70cM apart, calculate the recombination frequency?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50%",
            "b) 100%",
            "c) 25%",
            "d) 23%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: T.H. Morgan first studied linkage in Drosophila malanogester in which genes on a chromosome are linked (systemic gene)."
    },
    {
        "id": 479,
        "Question": "Name the sites of DNA, which have a high probability of crossing over?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cold spots",
            "b) Hot spots",
            "c) Covalent bond",
            "d) Hydrophobic bond"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Recombination frequency is the measure of genetic linkage. Recombination frequency should not exceed 50%. The maximum limit of recombination is 50%."
    },
    {
        "id": 480,
        "Question": "Genes of sex linked characters are located on the ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chromosome 18",
            "b) Chromosome 13",
            "c) Chromosome 14",
            "d) Sex chromosome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The characters are said to be sex linked if their genes are located on the sex chromosome. According to modern genetics, the x-chromosome linked character is called sex-linked character while y-linked characters are called male limited characters."
    },
    {
        "id": 481,
        "Question": "Which of the following is X-linked recessive disorder?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Color blindness",
            "b) Sickle cell anemia",
            "c) PTC tasting",
            "d) Albinism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the case of sex linkage reciprocal cross do not yield identical results, but it shows a criss-cross inheritance pattern, i.e. male transmits its sex linked genes to all daughters who in turn transmit them to half of their male progeny."
    },
    {
        "id": 482,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is NOT true regarding Partial sex linkage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The X-Y chromosome pair during meiosis",
            "b) Pairing occurs in the terminal region",
            "c) The inheritance pattern in the PAR region show sex-linkage",
            "d) PAR stands for the pseudo autosomal region"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In humans, three proteins in the cons cells act as color sensors, the two color sensors are encoded by X-linked genes while one is encoded by a gene located on the seventh autosome."
    },
    {
        "id": 483,
        "Question": "Identify the disease which causes excessive production of uric acid.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Duncan muscular dystrophy",
            "b) Lesch-Nyhan syndrome",
            "c) Hunter syndrome",
            "d) Hemophilia"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The inheritance pattern of the genes present in such terminal regions (PAR) of the sex chromosome is not like that of sex-linked genes but it resembles that of autosomal genes."
    },
    {
        "id": 484,
        "Question": "Which of the following characteristics does not belong to the Hunter syndrome?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Muscular deterioration",
            "b) Abnormal hairiness",
            "c) Mental retardation",
            "d) Long protruding tongue"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Lesch-Nyhan syndrome is an X-linked disorder which is the example of congenital hyperuriemic (excessive production of uric acid). It causes HGPRT (Hypoxanthine Guanine Phosphoribosyl Transferase) gene defective."
    },
    {
        "id": 485,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT a sex-limited role?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pitch of voice",
            "b) Musculature",
            "c) Baldness",
            "d) Milk production"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Hunter syndrome is an X-linked recessive disorder where the affected person have long protruding tongue and mental retardation while muscular deterioration occurs in another disorder called Duncan muscular dystrophy."
    },
    {
        "id": 486,
        "Question": "Which of the following disease is characterized by excessive trinucleotide repeats (CAG)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cystic fibrosis",
            "b) PTC tasting",
            "c) Dwarfism",
            "d) Huntington’s disease"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Baldness is a sex-influenced character, not a sex-limited character. Sex-limited characters are those whose development is limited to only one of the two sexes."
    },
    {
        "id": 487,
        "Question": "What is pedigree analysis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Record of inheritance pattern",
            "b) Linkage map",
            "c) Quantitative genetic",
            "d) Polygene analysis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Huntington’s disease is an autosomal disorder which is caused by excessive trinucleotide repeats, approx 50 to 100 times more than normal condition."
    },
    {
        "id": 488,
        "Question": "Name the principle on which pedigree analysis work?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Regression",
            "b) Probability",
            "c) Random mating",
            "d) ANOVA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pedigree is a record of inheritance of certain genetic traits for two or more than two generations presenting in the form of a diagram. "
    },
    {
        "id": 489,
        "Question": "Traits which show continuous variation is referred as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Genetic disorders",
            "b) Phenotypic variation",
            "c) Quantitative traits",
            "d) Qualitative traits"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: On quantitative inheritance, the phenotype of an individual depends upon the number of dominant alleles involved. Here, all the genes show additive effects on the gene."
    },
    {
        "id": 490,
        "Question": "Which of the following factor does not contribute to quantitative traits?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polygenes",
            "b) Environmental",
            "c) Genetic",
            "d) Carbohydrate content"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: QTL (quantitative trait loci) is the chromosomal site at which a group of genes affecting quantitative traits is located. Example: height, weight etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 491,
        "Question": "Who explained the multifactorial hypothesis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ronald Fisher",
            "b) Darwin",
            "c) Mendel",
            "d) Nilsson-Ehle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Quantitative inheritance is more complex inheritance than Mendelian inheritance as these are influenced by polygenes, genetic factors, and environmental factors."
    },
    {
        "id": 492,
        "Question": "Which of the following describes the dissimilarity in the traits due to the variation in genetic factors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polygenic",
            "b) Heritability",
            "c) Quantitative trait loci",
            "d) Maternal effect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Fisher hypothesis states that a particular trait is the result of the combined influence of genetic and environmental factors."
    },
    {
        "id": 493,
        "Question": "Which of the following describes the inheritance controlled by cytoplasmic genes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Extranuclear inheritance",
            "b) Heritability",
            "c) Environmental factors",
            "d) Complex trait"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Heritability is a concept of variation which arises due to genetic factors. Often, this term also used to show a resemblance of parents to their offsprings."
    },
    {
        "id": 494,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT true for cytoplasmic inheritance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reciprocal cross is always different",
            "b) Unequal contribution from male and female gametes",
            "c) It follows a Mendelian pattern of inheritance",
            "d) Do not show segregation for traits"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The cytoplasmic inheritance arises due to plasma genes located in cell organelles. The first time evidence for the cytoplasmic inheritance was presented by coherence in Mirabilis jalapa."
    },
    {
        "id": 495,
        "Question": "What is a petite mutant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Defective mitochondrial function of yeast",
            "b) Plastid function mutant",
            "c) Dwarfism",
            "d) Maternal effect genes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Plasma gene inheritance or cytoplasmic inheritance does not follow the Mendelian pattern of inheritance thus it comes under Non-Mendelian inheritance."
    },
    {
        "id": 496,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT the type of petite mutant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nuclear",
            "b) Neutral",
            "c) Suppressive",
            "d) Polygene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Mutation responsible for the defective mitochondrial function, produce mutant yeast called petite mutant."
    },
    {
        "id": 497,
        "Question": "Name the effect which shows the determination of character by the genotype of a female parent?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cytoplasmic male sterility",
            "b) Probability",
            "c) Random mating",
            "d) Maternal effect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Petite mutant are of three types, one is a nuclear petite mutant, which has a nuclear gene mutation, second is a neutral petite mutant, which do not have mitochondrial DNA, and the third one is a suppressive petite mutant. "
    },
    {
        "id": 498,
        "Question": "What is Cytogenetics?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Genetic disorders",
            "b) Phenotypic variation",
            "c) Study of chromosomes",
            "d) Qualitative traits"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cytogenetics is the study of the function, structure, and abnormalities of the chromosomes. It is the combination of cytology and genetics."
    },
    {
        "id": 499,
        "Question": "The diagram which shows the arrangement of metaphasic chromosomes according to their position of centromere is called________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Histogram",
            "b) Karyogram",
            "c) Dendrogram",
            "d) Ideogram"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Tijo and Levan (1956) of Sweden had discovered that human cells consist of 23 pairs of chromosomes or 46 chromosomes."
    },
    {
        "id": 500,
        "Question": "Which of the following designation has given to human female chromosomes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) XX",
            "b) XY",
            "c) XO",
            "d) ZZ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Ideogram is a photograph or a diagram of all Metaphasic chromosome arranged in homologous pair as per decreasing order of their centromeres."
    },
    {
        "id": 501,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT the dye-based chromosome banding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Giemsa",
            "b) Reverse",
            "c) Centromere",
            "d) Metacentric"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Humans consist of two similar chromosomes(XX) for female sex chromosome and two dissimilar chromosome (XY) in male."
    },
    {
        "id": 502,
        "Question": "Name the term which defines the presence or absence of extra copies of a few chromosomes.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Extranuclear inheritance",
            "b) Aneuploidy",
            "c) Euploidy",
            "d) Diploid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Chromosome banding is a differential staining procedure which separates the chromosome along the longitudinal axis. The most common banding procedure is dye-staining, which is of four types, i.e. giemsa, centromere, reverse, and quinacrine."
    },
    {
        "id": 503,
        "Question": "Alteration in which of the following chromosome shows Down syndrome?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sex chromosome",
            "b) 18",
            "c) 21",
            "d) 13"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Ploidy is defined as the numerical changes in chromosome numbers. It is basically of two types, euploidy involve a complete set of a chromosome, while aneuploidy refers to the presence and absence of a few copies of chromosomes but not a whole set."
    },
    {
        "id": 504,
        "Question": "Mark the INCORRECT statement about Edward’s syndrome.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Trisomy of chromosome 18",
            "b) Mental and motor retardation",
            "c) Dwarfism",
            "d) Clenched hand and overlapping fingers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Down syndrome is an autosomal aneuploidy disorder in human beings. The presence of an extra chromosome in 21st number of chromosome makes total chromosome number 47."
    },
    {
        "id": 505,
        "Question": "Which of the following is CORRECT for Turner syndrome?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slanting eyes",
            "b) Autosomal aneuploidy",
            "c) Suppressive",
            "d) Retarded sexual development"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Edward’s syndrome is the second most common autosomal aneuploidy, which involves trisomy in chromosome 18. "
    },
    {
        "id": 506,
        "Question": "Which of the following chromosomal aberration shows pseudodominance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Deletion",
            "b) Duplication",
            "c) Inversions",
            "d) Translocation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Turner syndrome is sex chromosomal aneuploidy, which is characterized by the absence of an X chromosome making total chromosome number 45. These are females with retarder sexual development."
    },
    {
        "id": 507,
        "Question": "C-value in genome represents___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Genetic disorders",
            "b) Phenotypic variation",
            "c) Amount of DNA present in the genome",
            "d) Qualitative traits"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The measure of DNA display in the genome of animal varieties is known as a C-value, which is characteristics of every species."
    },
    {
        "id": 508,
        "Question": "Name the phenomenon which shows the lack of correlation in genome size and genetic complexity.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Histogram",
            "b) Karyogram",
            "c) Dendrogram",
            "d) C-value paradox"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: All eukaryotes and prokaryotes dependably have a DNA genome, while viruses may either have a DNA genome or RNA genome."
    },
    {
        "id": 509,
        "Question": "What is the genome size of yeast?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12",
            "b) 120",
            "c) 170",
            "d) 3,300"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In higher eukaryotes there is no connection between expanded genome size and multifaceted nature. This absence of the relationship between genome size and genetic complexity is called C-value paradox."
    },
    {
        "id": 510,
        "Question": "How does genome complexity of denatured DNA measure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Giemsa staining",
            "b) Reverse chromatography",
            "c) Denaturation kinetics",
            "d) Renaturation kinetics"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Genome size of eukaryotes varies accordingly, i.e. genome size of yeast is 12, mustard plant has size 120kb, fruit fly have 170kb, and humans have 3,300kb genome."
    },
    {
        "id": 511,
        "Question": "Which of the following equation shows DNA renaturation reaction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sec 60",
            "b) Cot1/2",
            "c) Tan 30",
            "d) Cot 40"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Genome’s complex nature is the aggregate length of various arrangements of DNA. It can be estimated through the renaturation kinetics of denatured DNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 512,
        "Question": "Name the sequences which are present in more than one copy in a haploid genome?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nonrepetitive DNA",
            "b) Highly repetitive DNA",
            "c) Repetitive DNA",
            "d) Minisatellite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Renaturation of DNA depends upon the random collision of the reciprocal strands and follow second order kinetics. A DNA renaturation (reassociation) response is given by the Cot1/2."
    },
    {
        "id": 513,
        "Question": "What is alphoid DNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Large size DNA",
            "b) Sequences that are unique",
            "c) DNA repeats found in centromere region",
            "d) Highly repetitive DNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Repetitive DNA are the sequences that are present in the haploid genome and are of multiple copies."
    },
    {
        "id": 514,
        "Question": "Mark the INCORRECT statement about minisatellites.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tendemly repetited DNA",
            "b) Form clusters up to 20kb in length",
            "c) Shorter clusters",
            "d) Found in the centromere region"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Alphoid DNA is a human satellite DNA, which is mainly found in the centromere region. "
    },
    {
        "id": 515,
        "Question": "Where does microsatellite DNA present in the chromosomes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dispersed throughout the chromosome",
            "b) At the telomere end",
            "c) At the centromere",
            "d) Mainly at metacentric region"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Minisatellites are mainly found at or close to telomere region. Alphoid DNA is mainly found in the centromere region."
    },
    {
        "id": 516,
        "Question": "Structure of DNA and protein found in the nucleus of eukaryotic cells___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nucleic acid",
            "b) Nucleosome",
            "c) Chromatin",
            "d) Tetraplex"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Chromatin consists of single dsDNA in a coiled and condensed form which is an organized structure of DNA and proteins."
    },
    {
        "id": 517,
        "Question": "Which of the following is less condensed, less stained portion of chromatin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Metaphase",
            "b) Interphase",
            "c) Heterochromatin",
            "d) Euchromatin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Centromere is the region in the eukaryotic chromosome where kinetochore is assembled and sister chromatids are held together. In some cases, centromere can also be located at the end of the chromosomes."
    },
    {
        "id": 518,
        "Question": "Name the part of a chromosome where t-loop is found.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Telomere",
            "b) Centromere",
            "c) Acromere",
            "d) Tetraplex"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Less stained and less condensed portion of chromatin is euchromatin while a darkly stained and highly condensed region of chromatin is heterochromatin."
    },
    {
        "id": 519,
        "Question": "Name the unit of replication?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DNA",
            "b) Gene",
            "c) Replicon",
            "d) Chromosome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: T-loop is found at the end of the chromosome or at the telomere region. It is responsible for the stability of the chromosomal ends."
    },
    {
        "id": 520,
        "Question": "Which of the following phase is involved in the conversion of chromatin to chromosome?",
        "Options": [
            "a) S- phase",
            "b) M- phase",
            "c) G2- phase",
            "d) G1- phase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Replicon is the unit of replication, which consists of its own origin of replication. Single chromatin has more than one replicon."
    },
    {
        "id": 521,
        "Question": "Name the basic structural unit of chromatin, which is described by R.Kornberg?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Scaffold protein",
            "b) Solenoid",
            "c) 30nm fiber",
            "d) Nucleosome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In G0 phase of non-dividing cells DNA exists as chromatin while in M-phase chromatin is converted to chromosome which is more condensed."
    },
    {
        "id": 522,
        "Question": "What are protamines?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Large size DNA",
            "b) Sequences that are unique",
            "c) Histone like protein found in fish sperm",
            "d) Highly repetitive DNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Nucleosome is the first level of DNA packing structure which is composed of beads-on-a-string structure. R.Kornberg in 1974 described the basic structure of chromatin."
    },
    {
        "id": 523,
        "Question": "Name the protein, which maintained the condensed structure of chromosomes.",
        "Options": [
            "a) HSP",
            "b) SMC",
            "c) Collagen",
            "d) Elastin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Protamine is a polypeptide basically composed of arginine and is present instead of histones in the sperm of fish and some other organisms.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 524,
        "Question": "Mark the process which does not involve in histone modification?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acetylation",
            "b) Methylation",
            "c) Phosphorylation",
            "d) Dehydration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: SMC stands for structural maintenance of chromosome protein, which maintained condensed structure of chromosomes."
    },
    {
        "id": 525,
        "Question": "Double-helix structure of DNA is discovered by___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gobind Khurana",
            "b) Nirenberg",
            "c) Watson and Crick",
            "d) Darwin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In 1953, Watson and Crick worked out on the double – helix structure of DNA and find out the complementary nature of two strands."
    },
    {
        "id": 526,
        "Question": "What is a mode of replication in E.coli?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Intermediate",
            "b) Dispersive",
            "c) Conservative",
            "d) Semiconservative"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The two strands of DNA are separated without breakage of a covalent bond and its base sequence act as the template strand to synthesize a new complementary strand."
    },
    {
        "id": 527,
        "Question": "What is the origin of replication?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Particular site at which DNA replication starts",
            "b) Site which prevents initiation",
            "c) Random location on the DNA",
            "d) Site at which replication terminated"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Meselson and Stahl in 1958 conducted an experiment and demonstrated the semiconservative replication of DNA in E.coli."
    },
    {
        "id": 528,
        "Question": "How many numbers of replicon is found in E.coli?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Five replicon",
            "b) Two replicon",
            "c) Single replicon",
            "d) Multiple replicon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Origin of replication is particular sites on DNA as replication does not start at random sites. Replication starts from a particular site and proceeds bidirectionally or unidirectionally till the terminus site."
    },
    {
        "id": 529,
        "Question": "Which of the following protein does not involve in the initiation of replication?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DnaA",
            "b) SSB (Single strand binding protein)",
            "c) DnaB",
            "d) DnaF"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: E.coli is monorepliconic and have single replicon while eukaryotic cells contain many replication origins on a single chromosome and called multirepliconic."
    },
    {
        "id": 530,
        "Question": "Which of the following protein is required for connecting Okazaki fragments?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Scaffold protein",
            "b) Helicase",
            "c) Primase",
            "d) DNA gyrase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In eukaryotic replication, more than 20 proteins take part out of that the initiation of replication takes place in the presence of helicase, primase, SSB, DnaC, DnaA."
    },
    {
        "id": 531,
        "Question": "Name the protein, which is used for termination of replication?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DnaC",
            "b) SSB",
            "c) Tus protein",
            "d) DNA polymerase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: After initiation, the chain elongation and joining of Okazaki fragments take place by DNA gyrase, DNA ligase, DNA polymerase."
    },
    {
        "id": 532,
        "Question": "Which of the following would relax negatively supercoiled DNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DNA gyrase",
            "b) Type I topoisomerase",
            "c) Collagen",
            "d) Elastin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Tus protein is terminus binding protein which is used for termination of replication.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 533,
        "Question": "Name the protein, which is responsible for the formation of RNA primer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Topoisomerase",
            "b) Gyrase",
            "c) Helicase",
            "d) Primase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Negatively supercoiled DNA can be relaxed by topoisomerase I. It creates the nick in one strand of DNA and rotates freely to resolve supercoiling."
    },
    {
        "id": 534,
        "Question": "Rearrangement of DNA that involves the breakage and reunion of DNA is called___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Replication",
            "b) Recombination",
            "c) Translation",
            "d) Transcription"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Recombination is the process of rearrangement of DNA of breakage and reunion and it can change the genomic configuration."
    },
    {
        "id": 535,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT true about homologous recombination?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Exchange of homologous segments",
            "b) Exchange takes place between two homologous DNA molecules",
            "c) It is also termed as general recombination",
            "d) It involves a direct exchange of sequences of DNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Recombination was first recognized as the process which is responsible for crossing over in the meiosis. It is a large scale rearrangement of DNA molecules."
    },
    {
        "id": 536,
        "Question": "Which of the following is site specific recombination?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Modification",
            "b) Transposition",
            "c) Holiday junction",
            "d) Retrotransposons"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Homologous recombination involves a reciprocal exchange of sequences of DNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 537,
        "Question": "Who proposed holiday model for homologous recombination?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gobind Khurana",
            "b) Louis Pasteur",
            "c) Robin Holiday",
            "d) Niels Bohr"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:b\nExplanation: Transposition is the process of recombination, which allows one DNA sequence to inserted in another without taking care of sequence homology."
    },
    {
        "id": 538,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT a recombination system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) RecBCD",
            "b) RecE",
            "c) RecF",
            "d) DnaF"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Robin Holiday in 1964, proposed an appealing scheme for recombination called holiday model or hetroduplex model. "
    },
    {
        "id": 539,
        "Question": "Name the phenomenon of allele replacement during recombination and DNA repair?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Replication",
            "b) Mutation",
            "c) Transversion",
            "d) Gene conversion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Homologous recombination was first described in bacterial systems. The three different recombination systems are RecF, RecE, and RecBCD."
    },
    {
        "id": 540,
        "Question": "Name the protein, which is involved in homologous recombination in E.coli?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Topoisomerase",
            "b) Gyrase",
            "c) Helicase",
            "d) RecBCD enzyme"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation:  Gene conversion is the phenomenon of changing allele forms during recombination and DNA repair."
    },
    {
        "id": 541,
        "Question": "The correction of changes in DNA by a set of process known as___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Replication",
            "b) DNA repair",
            "c) Translation",
            "d) Transcription"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: DNA repair is the correction process which is used to maintain genetic stability."
    },
    {
        "id": 542,
        "Question": "Name the repair system for UV mediated damage of DNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Exchange of homologous segments",
            "b) DNA glycosylase",
            "c) Nucleotide excision repair",
            "d) Photoreactivation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Genome cannot maintain its essential cellular function if the DNA is damaged. So, for the accurate functioning, a set of correction processes are used known as DNA repair."
    },
    {
        "id": 543,
        "Question": "Which of the following enzyme is used in photoreactivation process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DNA ligase",
            "b) DNA photolyase",
            "c) DNA polymerase",
            "d) Primase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Exposure to UV radiation can cause pyrimidine dimer which is repaired by a light dependent direct system called photoreactivation."
    },
    {
        "id": 544,
        "Question": "Name the repair system which involves the removal of the damaged segment of DNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Recombinational repair",
            "b) Direct repair",
            "c) Excision repair",
            "d) Mismatched repair"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: DNA photolyase participates in the DNA repair system when the damage takes place by UV radiation."
    },
    {
        "id": 545,
        "Question": "Name the enzyme which initiates base excision repair process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) RNA polymerase",
            "b) DNA polymerase",
            "c) DNA photolyase",
            "d) DNA glycosylase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Excision of the damaged site comes under the excision repair system. It is of two types, base excision repair and nucleotide excision repair."
    },
    {
        "id": 546,
        "Question": "Which of the following enzyme works in the nucleotide excision repair?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DNA photolyase",
            "b) ABC exinuclease",
            "c) DNA glycosylase",
            "d) RecA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: DNA glycosylase cleaves N-glycosidic bonds which liberates altered base and generates apurinic or an apyrimidic site."
    },
    {
        "id": 547,
        "Question": "Mark the one, which is NOT a subunit of ABC exinuclease?",
        "Options": [
            "a) UvrA",
            "b) UvrB",
            "c) UvrC",
            "d) UvrF"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: ABC excinuclease involves the removal of short, usually 12 nucleotide segment. This system is best studied in E.coli."
    },
    {
        "id": 548,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT the function of the enzyme systems involved in mismatch repair?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Recognize mismatched base pair",
            "b) Gene conversion",
            "c) Determine incorrect base from a mismatch",
            "d) Excise incorrect base and carry out repair system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: ABC exinuclease binds at the site of lesion for the purpose of excision. It consists of three subunits i.e, UvrA, UvrB, and UvrC.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 549,
        "Question": "Mark the one, which is CORRECT for SOS repair.",
        "Options": [
            "a) RecA protein participates",
            "b) A free radical mechanism is involved",
            "c) The repair enzyme functions only once",
            "d) No bases or nucleotides are removed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Gene conversion is the phenomenon of changing allele forms during recombination and DNA repair."
    },
    {
        "id": 550,
        "Question": "The process of formation of RNA is known as___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Replication",
            "b) DNA repair",
            "c) Translation",
            "d) Transcription"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Transcription is a process of formation of the transcript or RNA with the help of RNA polymerase."
    },
    {
        "id": 551,
        "Question": "Mark the statement which is INCORRECT about the transcription unit?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a transcribed segment of DNA",
            "b) Eukaryotes have monocistronic transcription unit",
            "c) Prokaryotes also have a monocistronic transcription unit",
            "d) Immediate product of transcription is primary transcript"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Transcription occurs unidirectionally and synthesized RNA chain from 5’  to 3’ direction."
    },
    {
        "id": 552,
        "Question": "Name the site where upstream sequences located?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Prior to start point",
            "b) After the startpoint",
            "c) Right border of DNA",
            "d) In the middle of DNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Transcription unit is the transcribed segment of DNA. If the transcription unit carries information of one gene, it is called monocistronic while a set of adjacent genes when transcribed as a unit called polycistronic."
    },
    {
        "id": 553,
        "Question": "Which of the following is TRUE for the RNA polymerase activity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DNA dependent DNA synthesis",
            "b) Direct repair",
            "c) DNA dependent RNA synthesis",
            "d) RNA dependent RNA synthesis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Start point is the first base pair from which transcription starts. Upstream sequences are located prior to the start point while sequences after the start point are called downstream of it."
    },
    {
        "id": 554,
        "Question": "Who discovered RNA polymerase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Samuel B. Weiss",
            "b) Nirenberg",
            "c) Watson and Crick",
            "d) Darwin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: RNA polymerase is also known as DNA dependent RNA polymerase enzyme and it involves a synthesis of RNA from DNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 555,
        "Question": "Which of the following ensure stable binding of RNA polymerase at the promoter site?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DNA photolyase",
            "b) Sigma factor",
            "c) DNA glycosylase",
            "d) RecA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Samuel B. Weiss and Jerard Hurwitz in 1960 discovered RNA polymerase. RNA polymerase is also known as DNA dependent."
    },
    {
        "id": 556,
        "Question": "What is the work of the sigma factor in transcription?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Helicase action",
            "b) Transcription initiation",
            "c) Transcription elongation",
            "d) Transcription termination"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sigma factor decreases the binding of the core enzyme to non-specific DNA sequences and increases binding to the promoter."
    },
    {
        "id": 557,
        "Question": "Name the sigma factor which is used for promoter recognition?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sigma 32",
            "b) Sigma 70",
            "c) Sigma 60",
            "d) Sigma 40"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sigma factor is only involved in transcription initiation not in elongation. The sigma factor is released from the core enzyme when the transcript reaches more than 8-9 nucleotide.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 558,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used to describe the time taken by RNA polymerase to leave the promoter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Promoter clearance time",
            "b) Abortive initiation",
            "c) Elongation factor",
            "d) Mean time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are 7 different types of sigma factors have been reported in E. coli but the most common is sigma 70."
    },
    {
        "id": 559,
        "Question": "How many base pairs of DNA is transcribed by RNA polymerase in one go?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5-6",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 7-8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Promoter clearance time is the time taken by RNA polymerase core enzyme to leave the promoter. More the efficient promoter sequences, lesser would be the promoter clearance time."
    },
    {
        "id": 560,
        "Question": "Which of the following transcription termination technique has RNA dependent ATPase activity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Intercalating agents",
            "b) Rho dependent",
            "c) Rho independent",
            "d) Rifampcin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The RNA polymerase core enzyme moves along the template strand at uneven base i.e, moves over 7-8 base pairs in one go."
    },
    {
        "id": 561,
        "Question": "Name the one intrinsic terminator of transcription.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Intercalating agents",
            "b) Rho independent",
            "c) Rho dependent",
            "d) Acridine orange"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The rho factor functions as a Hexamer and has an RNA binding site and is responsible for the termination of transcription. It has RNA dependent ATPase activity."
    },
    {
        "id": 562,
        "Question": "Mark the one, which is NOT the transcription inhibitor in eukaryotes.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rifampicin",
            "b) Acridine dye",
            "c) Actinomycin D",
            "d) Rho factor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Rho independent transcription termination is also known as intrinsic terminators and about 50% of E. coli genes have these types of terminators. "
    },
    {
        "id": 563,
        "Question": "The process of modification of pre mRNA is known as___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Replication",
            "b) DNA repair",
            "c) Translation",
            "d) RNA processing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: RNA processing is the modification of pre-rRNA, pre-tRNA, and pre-Mrna. RNA processing rarely occurs in prokaryotes, but it is a regular feature of eukaryotes."
    },
    {
        "id": 564,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT the step of mRNA processing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5’ capping",
            "b) Splicing of introns",
            "c) Polyadenylation",
            "d) RNA silencing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Transcription and translation take place in different compartments i.e, transcription takes place in the nucleus while translation occurs in the cytoplasm."
    },
    {
        "id": 565,
        "Question": "Which of the following form 5’cap?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5’   ——>    5’ PPP linkage",
            "b) 5’   ——>    3’ PPP linkage",
            "c) 3’   ——>    3’ PPP linkage",
            "d) 3’   ——>    5’ NPP linkage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: mRNA processing occurs only in eukaryotes, it involves 5’capping, slicing of introns, polyadenylation, and RNA editing before transported to the cytoplasm, where they are translated to the ribosome."
    },
    {
        "id": 566,
        "Question": "Choose the INCORRECT statement about 5’ cap.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Recognized by the transport protein",
            "b) Provide stability to RNA",
            "c) Participate in the translation initiation",
            "d) Increase the life span of RNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A GTP is added to the 5’ end of the RNA with an unusual 5’   ——>    5’ PPP linkage. The guanine would be methylated further and forms 5’ cap."
    },
    {
        "id": 567,
        "Question": "Which of the following group of introns form stable lariat structure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Group I intron",
            "b) Group II intron",
            "c) Nuclear intron",
            "d) Group III intron"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Life span of mRNA is increased by poly ‘A’ tail i.e, polyadenylation. It also imparts the stability of RNA by protecting from ribonucleases."
    },
    {
        "id": 568,
        "Question": "Name the type of intron which needs spliceosomes to be spliced?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Group I intron",
            "b) Group IV intron",
            "c) Nuclear intron",
            "d) Group II intron"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Removal of group II intron from RNA is in the form of stable lariat while group III intron removed as an intermediate lariat."
    },
    {
        "id": 569,
        "Question": "Name the term where a single pre-mRNA is processed into a number of products?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alternate splicing",
            "b) Polyadenylation",
            "c) Capping",
            "d) Intron removal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The nuclear intron is the most common introns in nuclear mRNA. They need SnRNP supramolecular structure to be spliced. The supramolecular structure is called spliceosome."
    },
    {
        "id": 570,
        "Question": "Following RNAse are used for RNA processing except one, mark that?",
        "Options": [
            "a) RNAse P",
            "b) SnRNP",
            "c) RNAse E",
            "d) RNAse G"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When a single pre-mRNA molecule is processed in more than two ways to yield more than one mature RNA, it is called alternate splicing."
    },
    {
        "id": 571,
        "Question": "Conversion of messages carried by mRNA into amino acid sequences is called___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Replication",
            "b) DNA repair",
            "c) Translation",
            "d) Transcription"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Translation is the process of conversion mRNA base sequences into amino acid sequences."
    },
    {
        "id": 572,
        "Question": "The following set of RNA is required in the translation process except one, mark the INCORRECT?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Si RNA",
            "b) rRNA",
            "c) mRNA",
            "d) tRNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Peptidal transferase activity is performed by rRNA. tRNA functions in bringing amino acid to the ribosome."
    },
    {
        "id": 573,
        "Question": "What is the size of the prokaryotic ribosome?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 80S",
            "b) 70S",
            "c) 40S",
            "d) 60S"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Three types of RNA are required to perform cooperative functions in protein synthesis i.e, mRNA carries a genetic message, tRNA, and rRNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 574,
        "Question": "Name the sequence of RNA, which is recognized by a small subunit of the ribosome.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rho utilization site",
            "b) Downstream sequence",
            "c) Upstream sequence",
            "d) Shine Dalgarno sequence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The size of prokaryotic ribosome is 70S and it consists of two subunits large (50S) and small (30S)."
    },
    {
        "id": 575,
        "Question": "Which of the following is considered as a start codon?",
        "Options": [
            "a) AUG",
            "b) GUG",
            "c) UAG",
            "d) AGG"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In prokaryotes, Shine Dalgarno sequences are found near the initiation codon and it is complementary to the sequences present on the small subunit of the ribosome."
    },
    {
        "id": 576,
        "Question": "Mark the one, which is NOT a stop codon?",
        "Options": [
            "a) UAA",
            "b) UAG",
            "c) UGA",
            "d) GGA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Start codon refers to the first base of sequences from which reading begins and proceed 3 nitrogenous bases at a time."
    },
    {
        "id": 577,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true to the nature of the genetic code?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Codon is triplet",
            "b) Codons are commaless",
            "c) Codons are overlapping",
            "d) Codons are universal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Out of total codons, there are three non-sense codons or stop codon i.e, UAA (ochre), UAG (Amber), and UGA (opal)."
    },
    {
        "id": 578,
        "Question": "Who explained the wobble hypothesis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Darwin",
            "b) Watson and Crick",
            "c) Samuel B. Weiss",
            "d) Nirenberg"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Codons are non-overlapping in nature, commaless, and there is no punctuation mark between them. Codons are universal as well, except mammalian mitochondria and some bacteria."
    },
    {
        "id": 579,
        "Question": "Which of the following recognize a specific amino acid and its cognate t-RNA molecule?",
        "Options": [
            "a) t-RNA synthetase",
            "b) Ribososme",
            "c) r-RNA",
            "d) Topoisomerase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In 1966, Watson and Crick proposed the degeneracy wobble hypothesis. Wobble hypothesis explained the ability of an anticodon to base pair with more than one codon."
    },
    {
        "id": 580,
        "Question": "Name the inhibitor which blocks translation in both prokaryotes as well as eukaryotes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chlorophenicol",
            "b) Tetracycline",
            "c) Puromycin",
            "d) Streptomycin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The t-RNA synthetase enzyme recognizes a specific amino acid and its cognate t-RNA molecules. There are 20 different enzymes, which are categorized into 2 classes."
    },
    {
        "id": 581,
        "Question": "Which of the following inhibitor block translation in eukaryotes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cyclohexamine",
            "b) Tetracycline",
            "c) Puromycin",
            "d) Streptomycin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Puromycin is an analog of the amino acyl t-RNA, which causes premature termination of polypeptide."
    },
    {
        "id": 582,
        "Question": "Name the drug which inhibits the initiation step of translation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cyclohexamine",
            "b) Tetracycline",
            "c) Ricin",
            "d) Streptomycin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cyclohexamine inhibits peptidal transferase activity in eukaryotes while chlorophenicol inhibits peptidal transferase in prokaryotes."
    },
    {
        "id": 583,
        "Question": "Damage and errors in DNA cause___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mutation",
            "b) DNA repair",
            "c) Translation",
            "d) Transcription"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: All the types of errors during DNA replication and damages caused by exposure to radiation or carcinogens leads to mutation."
    },
    {
        "id": 584,
        "Question": "Mark the INCORRECT statement about mutation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mutation is predestined",
            "b) Major source of evaluation",
            "c) Usually deleterious and recessive",
            "d) It is a reversible process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Somatic mutation is not transmitted to sexual progeny while germinal mutation transmitted to sexual progeny."
    },
    {
        "id": 585,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT a type of reverse mutation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Back mutation",
            "b) Intergenic suppressor mutation",
            "c) Intragenic suppressor mutation",
            "d) Missense mutation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Mutations are the ultimate source of all genetic variations and without which all the genes could exist in only one form."
    },
    {
        "id": 586,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT true for loss of function mutation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Usually recessive",
            "b) Most common mutation",
            "c) Increases the activity of the gene",
            "d) Null allelic mutation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Reverse mutation occurs at the same or different sites of forward mutation and restores wild phenotype."
    },
    {
        "id": 587,
        "Question": "Name the term given to the type of mutation which depends on the conditions of the environment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Forward mutation",
            "b) Reverse mutation",
            "c) Conditional lethal mutation",
            "d) Gain of function mutation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Loss of function mutation either reduce or abolishes the activity of a gene. On the contrary mutation that increases the activity of the gene is called a gain of function mutation."
    },
    {
        "id": 588,
        "Question": "What is the detection technique of auxotrophs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spread plating",
            "b) Replica plating",
            "c) Streaking",
            "d) Pouring"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In conditional lethal mutation, lethality depends on the conditions of the environment. Examples of conditional lethal mutations are auxotrophs, temperature sensitive mutants, and suppressor mutation."
    },
    {
        "id": 589,
        "Question": "Name the type of mutation in which the cause of mutation is not known?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spontaneous mutation",
            "b) Suppressor mutation",
            "c) Nonsense mutation",
            "d) Mis-sense mutation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Auxotrophs is a conditional lethal mutation in which mutants need essential metabolites for proper growth."
    },
    {
        "id": 590,
        "Question": "Addition or deletion of bases causes which kind of mutation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Transversion",
            "b) Frameshift mutation",
            "c) Transition",
            "d) Transcription"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Spontaneous mutation is those for which the cause of mutation is not known. These types of mutations arise due to a tautomeric shift in nitrogenous bases of DNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 591,
        "Question": "Which of the following chemical mutagen affects only replicating DNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acridine dye",
            "b) Alkylating agent",
            "c) Deaminating agent",
            "d) Base analog"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Frameshift mutation is a point mutation involves the addition or deletion of bases while substitution of bases causes transition or transversion."
    },
    {
        "id": 592,
        "Question": "Haploid spermatids modified into motile spermatozoa by the process called___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mutation",
            "b) DNA repair",
            "c) Translation",
            "d) Spermiogenesis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Primary spermatocyte undergo meiosis and produces spermatids. Spermiogenesis is the process by which haploid spermatids modified to motile spermatozoa."
    },
    {
        "id": 593,
        "Question": "What is the site of spermatogenesis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Seminiferous tubules",
            "b) Epididymes",
            "c) Vasa deference",
            "d) Rete testis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Spermatids are connected by a cytoplasmic bridge, thus considered as functionally diploid and genetically haploid."
    },
    {
        "id": 594,
        "Question": "Which of the following is considered as the source of testosterone?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rete testis",
            "b) Leyding cell",
            "c) Tunica albuginea",
            "d) Scrotum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Seminiferous tubule is the site of spermatogenesis while Vasa deference and epididymes help in sperm maturation."
    },
    {
        "id": 595,
        "Question": "Name the milk ejection hormone?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inhibin",
            "b) Prolactin",
            "c) Oxytocin",
            "d) FSH"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Interstitial cells or leyding cell are the sources of testosterone, located between the seminiferous tubule within a lobule."
    },
    {
        "id": 596,
        "Question": "Which of the following provide negative feedback for the release of testosterone?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inhibin",
            "b) LH",
            "c) FSH",
            "d) GnRH"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Oxyticin is released from the posterior pituitary due to the stimulants like sucking by the baby and is considered as milk ejection hormone."
    },
    {
        "id": 597,
        "Question": "Name the hormone which is secreted during puberty?",
        "Options": [
            "a) GnRH",
            "b) FSH",
            "c) Oxytocin",
            "d) Relaxin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Whenever concentration of testosterone and ABP increases beyond the threshold level, inhibin inhibits the anterior pituitary and decreases the release of FSH and LH."
    },
    {
        "id": 598,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT secreted from corpus luteum?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Progesterone",
            "b) Inhibin",
            "c) Relaxin",
            "d) FSH"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: FSH is Follicular Stimulating Hormone which stimulates the beginning of puberty and induces primary oocyte to complete its meiosis."
    },
    {
        "id": 599,
        "Question": "Where does sperm acquire its motility?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Seminiferous tubules",
            "b) Epididymes",
            "c) Vasa deference",
            "d) Rete testis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Corpus luteum is the chief source of progesterone, which prepares a female for the gestation period by increasing the thickness of endometrium and also by increasing its vascularisation."
    },
    {
        "id": 600,
        "Question": "Which of the following secrete spermatozoa activating substances?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Epididymes",
            "b) Seminal fluid",
            "c) Prostate gland",
            "d) Seminal vesicle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sperm acquire its motility in the epididymis after residing here for 18-24 hours."
    },
    {
        "id": 601,
        "Question": "What is the pattern of cleavage in mammals?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Radial",
            "b) Spiral",
            "c) Rotational",
            "d) Bilateral"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Seminal vesicle secretes spermatozoa activating substances like fructose, citrate, and prostaglandins."
    },
    {
        "id": 602,
        "Question": "An enzyme which synthesis, DNA from RNA is called___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) DNA polymerase",
            "b) RNA polymerase",
            "c) Nucleases",
            "d) Reverse transcriptase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Reverse transcriptase was discovered by Howard Temin at the University of Wisconsin, also known as RNA directed DNA polymerase which synthesis DNA from RNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 603,
        "Question": "Name the bacterium from which Taq DNA polymerase derived?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thermus aquaticus",
            "b) Salmonella",
            "c) Cyanobacteria",
            "d) E.coli"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Kornberg enzyme is DNA polymerase I, which have exclusively both 3’ -5’ and 5’-3’ exonuclease activity. It also has 5’-3’ polymerase activity."
    },
    {
        "id": 604,
        "Question": "Name the enzyme which degrades DNA molecule by breaking its phosphodiester bonds?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DNA polymerase",
            "b) Nucleases",
            "c) Ligase",
            "d) Reverse transcriptase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Taq polymerase derived from thermostable bacteria called thermus aquaticus.it is basically used in PCR and have the ability to withstand with 90°C temperature."
    },
    {
        "id": 605,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT an endonuclease?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mung bean nuclease",
            "b) S1 nuclease",
            "c) Terminal deoxynucleotidal transferase",
            "d) RNase A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Nucleases are the enzymes which break phosphodiester bonds of DNA that link one nucleotide to another. Nucleases are of two types i.e., endonucleases and exonucleases."
    },
    {
        "id": 606,
        "Question": "Which of the following endonuclease has been purified from Aspergillus oryzae?",
        "Options": [
            "a) S1 nuclease",
            "b) RNase H",
            "c) RNase A",
            "d) Mung bean nuclease"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Endonuclease are those which break internal phosphodiester bonds of DNA while exonuclease removes nucleotide from the end of the DNA. Examples: mung bean nuclease, S1 nuclease, Rnase A, and RNase H."
    },
    {
        "id": 607,
        "Question": "Name the enzyme which degrade dsDNA after recognizing specific nucleotide sequences?",
        "Options": [
            "a) RNase H",
            "b) Restriction endonuclease",
            "c) DNA polymerase",
            "d) Ligases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: S1 nuclease has been derived from Aspergillus oryaze and used to degrade single strand RNA and DNA but does not affect ds DNA or DNA-RNA hybrid."
    },
    {
        "id": 608,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT the property of restriction enzymes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Recognizes palindromic sequences",
            "b) Two fold axial symmetry",
            "c) Recognize specific site according to DNA sources",
            "d) Cut down randomly"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Restriction endonuclease is also called restriction enzymes and works on the specific nucleotide sequence called restriction site. These enzymes restrict the entry of foreign DNA into bacteria."
    },
    {
        "id": 609,
        "Question": "Which of the following type of restriction enzyme does not require ATP for cleavage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Type I",
            "b) Type II",
            "c) Type III",
            "d) Type IV"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Restriction enzyme recognizes specific restriction sites which are independent of DNA sources."
    },
    {
        "id": 610,
        "Question": "Name the restriction enzyme which recognizes different sequences, but produces same ends?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DAM methylase",
            "b) Isoschizomers",
            "c) Neoschizomers",
            "d) Isocaudomers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: On the basis of properties restriction enzymes has been divided into type I, type II, and type III. Type I and Type III require ATP and magnesium while Type II requires only magnesium."
    },
    {
        "id": 611,
        "Question": "Which enzyme join DNA molecules together?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polymerase",
            "b) Nucleases",
            "c) Ligases",
            "d) Linkers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Isocaudomers recognizes different sequences but produces same ends while Isoschizomers recognizes the same sequences and cut in the same pattern."
    },
    {
        "id": 612,
        "Question": "Circular DNA used for cloning  is called___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) DNA polymerase",
            "b) RNA polymerase",
            "c) Phagosome",
            "d) Plasmid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Plasmid is the circular bacterial DNA, which carries genes which are useful but not essential for survival. These are said to be extrachromosomal DNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 613,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT a cloning vector?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bacterial plasmid",
            "b) Cosmids",
            "c) Bacteriophage",
            "d) E.coli"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Origin of replication is the segment of DNA that is recognized by the replication enzymes. Absence of replication origin leads to the failure of replication. "
    },
    {
        "id": 614,
        "Question": "Cloning vector has the following properties, except one?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Contain genetic marker for selection",
            "b) Ability to replicate",
            "c) Multiple restriction site for entry of DNA",
            "d) Contain nonessential DNA to optimize cloning"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cloning vectors are DNA molecules that are used to transport sequences between the host and the donor. Most of the vectors are genetically engineered. "
    },
    {
        "id": 615,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT the characteristics of the plasmid?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Replicate independently in a host cell",
            "b) Selectable marker gene",
            "c) Contain single cloning site",
            "d) Small in size"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cloning vector has a single and unique restriction site for the entry of DNA and facilitate cloning. Cloning vector is used to amplify single molecule of DNA into multiple copies."
    },
    {
        "id": 616,
        "Question": "Which of the following is TRUE for YAC?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Recognizes palindromic sequences",
            "b) Two fold axial symmetry",
            "c) Recognize specific site according to DNA sources",
            "d) Derived from DNA of the Yeast"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: These vectors are used to clone DNA that varies in size from several base pairs to several thousand base pairs. It contains multiple cloning sites."
    },
    {
        "id": 617,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT an example of Lambda phages?",
        "Options": [
            "a) EMBL3",
            "b) M13",
            "c) λgt10",
            "d) λZAP"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: YAC stands for Yeast Artificial Chromosome that is derived from the DNA of the yeast and is ligated to bacterial plasmid by genetic engineering."
    },
    {
        "id": 618,
        "Question": "Name the vector system used for plant transformation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Agrobacterium",
            "b) Cosmids",
            "c) M13 phage",
            "d) Resistance plasmid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: M13 is an example of philamentous phages while the rest is Lambda phages. Lambda phages are double stranded DNA phages that replicate in E.coli, follows either lysogenic or lytic mode."
    },
    {
        "id": 619,
        "Question": "Name the first vector used for a mammalian cell?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lambda phage",
            "b) SV40",
            "c) M13",
            "d) EMBL3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Agrobacterium tumefaciens is a powerful vector system for plant transformation. It is used to transfer genes from bacteria to plant in the form of T-DNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 620,
        "Question": "Which of the following cloning vector is used for insect and having a DNA genome?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cosmid",
            "b) P-element",
            "c) SV40",
            "d) Baculovirus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: SV40 is a small virus cloning vector that infects monkey (simian). Mammalian cell was first cloned using SV40 vector."
    },
    {
        "id": 621,
        "Question": "The process by which bacterial cell uptake DNA is called___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gene expression",
            "b) Transformation",
            "c) Transcription",
            "d) Translation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Transformation is the process of transfer DNA from a donor cell to a host cell. It is common in both bacterial cell and plant cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 622,
        "Question": "Which of the following chemical is used in chemical transformation method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cu",
            "b) FeSO4",
            "c) SO2",
            "d) CaCl2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Electroporation is the method which uses a short pulse of electric charge and allows the uptake of DNA from donor to host cell. "
    },
    {
        "id": 623,
        "Question": "Which of the following method creates pores in the membrane?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gene gun",
            "b) Chemical transformation",
            "c) Electroporation",
            "d) Agrobacterium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In order to increase the competency of a bacterial cell, chemical transformation method is used. Use of calcium chloride (CaCl2) can precipitate the surface of the cell membrane and make it more competent. "
    },
    {
        "id": 624,
        "Question": "Which of the following particles is used in the gene gun method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Iron particles",
            "b) Aluminum particles",
            "c) Silver particles",
            "d) Gold particles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Electroporation is the method of transformation which creates pores in the membrane that allows molecules, ions, water to pass through it."
    },
    {
        "id": 625,
        "Question": "Which of the following shows the location of the inserted genes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Palindromic sequences",
            "b) Resistance gene",
            "c) Restriction site",
            "d) Marker gene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Gene gun fires gold particles coated with the foreign DNA to the plant genome. Some of these particles pass through plant nucleus and integrate with the plant chromosome."
    },
    {
        "id": 626,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT true for agrobacterium?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Horizontal gene transfer",
            "b) Gram positive bacteria",
            "c) Causes tumor in plants",
            "d) Transfer DNA in plants"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Marker genes allow determining which plant contains the inserted gene. The selection of plant with desired gene is done by screening."
    },
    {
        "id": 627,
        "Question": "Name the disease caused by Agrobacterium in plants?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Crown gall disease",
            "b) Black knot",
            "c) Downy Mildew",
            "d) Early Blight"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Agrobacterium is a gram negative bacterium which is used to transfer DNA into the plant. It was first discovered by H. J. Conn in the tumor of a plant."
    },
    {
        "id": 628,
        "Question": "The map of the chromosome which shows identifiable sites is called___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gene expression",
            "b) Genome sequencing",
            "c) Chromosome walking",
            "d) Genome map"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Genome map shows identifiable landmarks on a chromosome. These maps are of two types: genetic map and physical map."
    },
    {
        "id": 629,
        "Question": "What is chromosome walking?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hybridization technique",
            "b) Sequencing technique",
            "c) Genetic marker",
            "d) Chemical degradation technique"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Genetic map describes the location of genetic markers according to the frequency of recombination, while physical map gives the distance of DNA base pairs."
    },
    {
        "id": 630,
        "Question": "What is the unit of a genetic map?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Centimeter",
            "b) Nanometer",
            "c) Angstrom",
            "d) Centimorgan"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Chromosome walking is a hybridization technique which uses an overlapping probe of the neighboring region of chromosome for the purpose of cloning. "
    },
    {
        "id": 631,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is NOT true for genetic markers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A gene or a DNA sequence",
            "b) Associated with a particular trait",
            "c) Anything can be used as a genetic marker",
            "d) The first genetic map was prepared was of fruit fly"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Genetic map is measured in terms of centimorgan (cM) which describes the position of genetic markers, i.e., gene loci by the frequency of recombination."
    },
    {
        "id": 632,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT a DNA marker?",
        "Options": [
            "a) RAPD",
            "b) Hormone",
            "c) RFLP",
            "d) AFLP"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Genes were the first markers which were used to prepare the first genetic map. There are basically three types of genetic markers, i.e., morphological, biochemical, and DNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 633,
        "Question": "What is the full form of RFLP?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Restriction Fragment Length Polymorphisms",
            "b) Random Fragment Length Polymorphism",
            "c) Restriction Find in Length of DNA Polymer",
            "d) Restriction Fragment Length Polymers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: DNA markers are those which shows the variations in the sequence of DNA. A Hormone is a biochemical marker."
    },
    {
        "id": 634,
        "Question": "Which of the following technique is used for the amplification of DNA fragments?",
        "Options": [
            "a) AFLP",
            "b) RFLP",
            "c) RAPD",
            "d) SSLP"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: RFLP is Restriction Fragment Length Polymorphism is a hybridization based molecular marker, which is used for the identification of DNA sequence polymorphism for genetic mapping."
    },
    {
        "id": 635,
        "Question": "Out of the following, which technique detect single nucleotide polymorphism?",
        "Options": [
            "a) RFLP",
            "b) AFLP",
            "c) SSLP",
            "d) SNP"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: RAPD is Random Amplification of Polymorphic DNA, which is used to amplify random DNA sequences from any species by the use of a single primer."
    },
    {
        "id": 636,
        "Question": "Name the mapping technique used to determine the position of restriction sites in a DNA molecule.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Genetic map",
            "b) Restriction mapping",
            "c) Biochemical markers",
            "d) DNA markers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: SNP detects the position of a single nucleotide in the DNA sequences. It is the most abundant molecular marker in the genome."
    },
    {
        "id": 637,
        "Question": "Introduction of foreign DNA in the genome is called___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gene expression",
            "b) Transgenesis",
            "c) Transfection",
            "d) Cell hybridization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Transgenesis is the introduction of foreign gene or DNA into the genome of other organisms so that it can be maintained in heritable manner."
    },
    {
        "id": 638,
        "Question": "When was the first transgenic animal produced?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1981",
            "b) 1971",
            "c) 1978",
            "d) 1986"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Genetically modified organisms are made through the alteration of genetic material while genetically engineered are those whose genetic material is modified through recombinant DNA technology."
    },
    {
        "id": 639,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is INCORRECT for gene knockout?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Non functional gene is introduced",
            "b) Make gene inoperative",
            "c) Introduction of functional gene in an organism",
            "d) It can be used to study the effect of loss of gene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ralph Brinster and Richard Palmiter in 1981 produced a first transgenic animal. They had introduced the gene for rat growth hormone in the fertilized egg of mice. "
    },
    {
        "id": 640,
        "Question": "Name the phenomenon where a single cell is able to reproduce the whole organism?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Transfection",
            "b) Gene knockin",
            "c) Transgenesis",
            "d) Animal cloning"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Gene knockout is different from the transgenesis as in this process, a nonfunctional gene is introduced in the place of functional gene and make it inoperative."
    },
    {
        "id": 641,
        "Question": "Which cloning technique is used to clone the whole organism?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DNA cloning",
            "b) Reproductive cloning",
            "c) Gene cloning",
            "d) Therapeutic cloning"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:d\nExplanation: Animal cloning is a phenomenon of producing an entire organism from the single cell of the parent. These are genetically identical in nature."
    },
    {
        "id": 642,
        "Question": "Name the mechanism which is used to correct the defective gene?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gene therapy",
            "b) Gene knockout",
            "c) Gene knock-in",
            "d) Restriction Fragment Length Polymers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Reproductive cloning was first used to clone Dolly the sheep, most famous cloned organism. In this process, the DNA of the donor is introduced into the egg of another organism."
    },
    {
        "id": 643,
        "Question": "Which of the following gene is responsible for the severe combined immunodeficiency disease?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Factor VIII",
            "b) CFTR",
            "c) ADA",
            "d) P53"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Gene therapy is the corrective mechanism which is used to supplement defective mutant allele with the functional one. It is responsible for the correction of the defective or abnormal gene."
    },
    {
        "id": 644,
        "Question": "Name the type of the method in which the cloned gene is directly transferred in the tissues of patients.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Virus mediated gene transfer",
            "b) In vitro gene transfer",
            "c) Ex vivo gene transfer",
            "d) In vivo gene transfer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: ADA stands for adenosine deaminase, deficiency of which causes severe combined immunodeficiency. It is most commonly found in bone marrow and T-cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 645,
        "Question": "The process of expression of foreign genes in a plant is called___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gene expression",
            "b) Transgenesis",
            "c) Genetic transformation",
            "d) Cell hybridization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Genetic transformation is the process of introducing, stably integration and expression of foreign genes in the plant. This whole process produces transgenic plants."
    },
    {
        "id": 646,
        "Question": "Name the strategy where two-plasmid system is used for the introduction of the gene?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Binary vector system",
            "b) Co-integration vector strategy",
            "c) Agrobacterium",
            "d) Selectable marker strategy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Unlike conventional breeding, only those genes are introduced in the plant which has agronomic importance, i.e., cloned genes without the cotransfer of the other undesirable gene."
    },
    {
        "id": 647,
        "Question": "Which of the following is considered as a visual marker?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Antibiotic marker",
            "b) Resistance marker",
            "c) Selectable marker",
            "d) Screenable marker"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Binary vector system, two plasmids are used to introduce t-DNA into the plants. Both plasmids complement each other when present together in a system. "
    },
    {
        "id": 648,
        "Question": "Name the marker gene of streptomycin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) HPT",
            "b) SPT",
            "c) PAT",
            "d) BXN"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Screenable marker gene is used for determining transformation efficiency, confirming transformation, and monitoring gene or protein activity."
    },
    {
        "id": 649,
        "Question": "Name the first transgenic virus resistant plant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rice",
            "b) Cotton",
            "c) Tobacco",
            "d) Tomato"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Selectable marker gene is used to confer resistance to antibiotics i.e., SPT is used for streptomycin, HPT is for hygromycin, and BXN is for bromoxynil."
    },
    {
        "id": 650,
        "Question": "Which of the following is supplemented with vitamin A in order to improve its nutritional quality?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cotton",
            "b) Potato",
            "c) Tomato",
            "d) Rice"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In 1986, tobacco was produced using virus resistance gene, i.e., tobacco mosaic virus (TMV) coat protein, which generates resistance against virus attack."
    },
    {
        "id": 651,
        "Question": "Name the enzyme which has silenced to delay the ripening process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polygalacturonase",
            "b) Glyphosate",
            "c) ADA",
            "d) P53"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The nutritional quality of rice has been improved by the addition of vitamin A (beta-carotene). This genetically engineered rice is called golden rice."
    },
    {
        "id": 652,
        "Question": "Name the technique which is used to enhance the life of a tomato.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Antisense technology",
            "b) In vitro gene transfer",
            "c) Ex vivo gene transfer",
            "d) Molecular farming"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Polygalacturonase is an enzyme which is responsible for ripening. By antisense technology, the gene which encodes for this enzyme has been silenced."
    },
    {
        "id": 653,
        "Question": "The growth of plant tissues in artificial media is called___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gene expression",
            "b) Transgenesis",
            "c) Plant tissue culture",
            "d) Cell hybridization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Plant tissue culture is a technique of growing root, shoot, tissues, and organs artificially in an ascetical medium which contain all the essential nutrients for the growth."
    },
    {
        "id": 654,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT the feature of plant cells?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Presence of centrioles",
            "b) The cell wall outside the cell membrane",
            "c) Cell-cell communication through plasmodesmata",
            "d) Consists of plastids"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A plant cell is a eukaryotic cell which has similar features as that of a typical eukaryotic cell but there are certain features which are unique to the plant cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 655,
        "Question": "Name the term given to the ability of single cells to divide and produce all the differentiated cell in the organism?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Unipotent",
            "b) Pluripotent",
            "c) Multipotent",
            "d) Totipotency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: MTOC is a microtubule organizing center, which is made up of centrioles and present in the animal cell but it is not present in plant cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 656,
        "Question": "Out of the following, which one is NOT the basic component of culture media used for plant cultivation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Complex mixture of salts",
            "b) Amino acids",
            "c) Serum albumin",
            "d) Sugar/ sucrose"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cell potency is their capability to differentiate into other cell types. Totipotency is the ability of the single cell in an organism to divide and produce all other cells by differentiation."
    },
    {
        "id": 657,
        "Question": "Mark the INCORRECT statement about agar, a gelling agent in plant tissue culture medium?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Not digested by plant enzymes",
            "b) It does not use in microprapogation work",
            "c) It does not react with media constituents",
            "d) Remain stable at incubation temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Four basic components used in culture media for plant tissue cultivation are: Essential elements and mineral ions, amino acids, sugar, and a gelling agent."
    },
    {
        "id": 658,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT a plant growth regulator?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Auxin",
            "b) Cytokinins",
            "c) Abcisic acid",
            "d) Polyphenols"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Agar is obtained from seaweeds, and it is a most preferred gelling agent due to its advantageous properties. It is also used in some micropropagation work."
    },
    {
        "id": 659,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the main effect of cytokines in the tissue culture system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Adventitious shoot formation",
            "b) Induction of somatic embryos",
            "c) Adventitious root formation",
            "d) Shoot elongation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Plant growth regulators are the compound which at very low concentration can modify plant growth and its morphogenesis. Polyphenols are not considered as plant growth regulators but they are produced due to the plant defense mechanism."
    },
    {
        "id": 660,
        "Question": "Which one of them is NOT the main effect of polyamines in the tissue culture system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Promotion of tuber and bulb formation",
            "b) Adventitious root formation",
            "c) Promotion of shoot formation",
            "d) Somatic embryogenesis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cytokines promote shoot formation while it inhibits the formation of roots. It also promotes cell division and callus formation."
    },
    {
        "id": 661,
        "Question": "Which of the following plant hormone control fruit ripening?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ethylene",
            "b) Auxin",
            "c) Gibbrellins",
            "d) Abscisis acid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Polyamines does not promote tuber and bulb formation, but it supports root and shoot formation and also somatic embryogenesis. The promotion of bulb and tumor formation is done by jasmonic acid."
    },
    {
        "id": 662,
        "Question": "The growth of animal cells in vitro in a suitable culture medium is called___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gene expression",
            "b) Transgenesis",
            "c) Plant tissue culture",
            "d) Animal cell culture"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Animal cell culture is the process of growing cell in vitro in a suitable culture medium which contains a mixture of nutrients and growth factors."
    },
    {
        "id": 663,
        "Question": "Name the type of culture which is prepared by inoculating directly from the tissue of an organism to culture media?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Primary cell culture",
            "b) Secondary cell culture",
            "c) Cell lines",
            "d) Transformed cell culture"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cells derived from kidney tissues are anchorage dependent primary cell culture which requires another surface for attachment and survival."
    },
    {
        "id": 664,
        "Question": "What is a cell line?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Multilayer culture",
            "b) Transformed cells",
            "c) Multiple growth of cells",
            "d) Sub culturing of primary culture"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Primary cell culture is the direct inoculation of the tissues of an organism into a culture medium without going prior to cell proliferation."
    },
    {
        "id": 665,
        "Question": "Name the organism on which first cell line was observed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) E.coli",
            "b) Sheep",
            "c) Mouse",
            "d) Drosophila"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cell line is defined as the sub culturing of primary cell culture. It can be a finite cell line or a infinite cell line."
    },
    {
        "id": 666,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the characteristics of a normal cell?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Anchorage independent",
            "b) Continuous cell lines",
            "c) Dependent on external growth factor",
            "d) No contact inhibition"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: First cell line observed was mouse fibroblast L cell which was derived from connective tissues of mouse by exposing it to a chemical carcinogen."
    },
    {
        "id": 667,
        "Question": "Name the cell line of the human embryonic lung?",
        "Options": [
            "a) HeLa",
            "b) WISH",
            "c) L",
            "d) MRC-5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A normal cell needs external factors for its survival. It is anchorage dependent and have a finite number of cell lines."
    },
    {
        "id": 668,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT the part of growth medium for animal culture?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Starch",
            "b) Serum",
            "c) Carbon source",
            "d) Inorganic salts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: MRC-5 is the cell line of the human embryonic lung while HeLa is the cell line of human cervical carcinoma. L represents human connective tissue and WISH is the cell line of human amnion."
    },
    {
        "id": 669,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT the major function of the serum?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Promotion of tuber and bulb formation",
            "b) Stimulate cell growth",
            "c) Enhance cell attachment",
            "d) Provide transport proteins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Growth medium of an animal cell contains serum (5-20%), nitrogen sources, inorganic salts, carbon sources, growth factors, buffer in water and vitamins."
    },
    {
        "id": 670,
        "Question": "Embryo initiation is facilitated by___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) GA3",
            "b) BPA",
            "c) ABA",
            "d) 2,4 D"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: 2,4, D is used in higher concentration for embryo initiation while ABA is used for embryo maturation."
    },
    {
        "id": 671,
        "Question": "Which of the following culture is used for the production of primary and secondary metabolites?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cell suspension culture",
            "b) Callus culture",
            "c) Protoplast culture",
            "d) Somatic hybrid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cell suspension culture is a suspension of a single cell and few clumps of cells. It grows faster than callus culture."
    },
    {
        "id": 672,
        "Question": "Which of the following does not act as a fusogen in protoplast fusion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2,4 D",
            "b) Polyethylene glycol",
            "c) Calcium",
            "d) PVA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Fusogen is a glycoprotein which facilitates fusion of cell to cell membrane. It is merging of gamete genome and formation of an organism."
    },
    {
        "id": 673,
        "Question": "Increase amount of auxin in callus culture will promote which part of the plant tissue?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Multilayer tissues",
            "b) Meristem",
            "c) Shoot",
            "d) Root"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Callus culture is an unorganized, undifferentiated mass of cell in which differentiation process occurs. Increase in the ratio of auxin to cytokinin will promote rooting of the plant."
    },
    {
        "id": 674,
        "Question": "Name the asexual mode of embryo formation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Protoplast fusion",
            "b) Callus culture",
            "c) Somatic embryogenesis",
            "d) Protoplast culture"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Somatic embryogenesis is an asexual mode of embryo formation from somatic cells which develop directly into the whole plant."
    },
    {
        "id": 675,
        "Question": "Mark the INCORRECT statement about applications of the somatic embryogenesis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mass multiplication of germplasm",
            "b) Continuous cell lines",
            "c) Production of artificial seeds",
            "d) Production of primary and secondary metabolites"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Somatic embryogenesis is used for the production of artificial seeds and it also produces primary and secondary metabolites which are specific to seeds such as lipids in oil seeds."
    },
    {
        "id": 676,
        "Question": "Which method is used to overcome cytoplasmic male sterility?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Callus culture",
            "b) Artificial embryogengesis",
            "c) Somatic embryogenesis",
            "d) Cybrid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cybrid is the fusion of cytoplasm of two cells. It shows heterozygocity for cytoplasm genome. This method is used to overcome cytoplasmic male sterility."
    },
    {
        "id": 677,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is NOT true for artificial seeds?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Higher cost method for multiplication",
            "b) No transplantation is required",
            "c) Bactericide and fungicide can be given",
            "d) Artificial endosperm can be given"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Artificial seed production is high volume, low cost method for multiplication. Artificial endosperm can be given and it does not require transplantation."
    },
    {
        "id": 678,
        "Question": "Cohesion of water molecules is due to___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Diffusion",
            "b) Osmosis",
            "c) Gravitational force",
            "d) Surface tension"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cohesion is the property of water molecules which shows its hydrogen bonding. Surface tension is the phenomenon of holding together of water molecules."
    },
    {
        "id": 679,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT the property of water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nonpolar molecule",
            "b) Excellent solvent",
            "c) High heat of vaporization",
            "d) High specific heat"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Water is a polar molecule which is electrically neutral. It has a partial positive charge on each hydrogen and partial negative charge on each oxygen."
    },
    {
        "id": 680,
        "Question": "Name the term which is given for the movement of water through a semipermeable membrane?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Diffusion",
            "b) Osmosis",
            "c) Tonicity",
            "d) Transpiration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Osmosis is a specialized form of diffusion, which involves a passive movement of water from higher to lower concentration of water with the help of a semipermeable membrane."
    },
    {
        "id": 681,
        "Question": "What is the measure of the osmotic pressure gradient of solutions separated by a semipermeable membrane?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Water potential",
            "b) Ficks law",
            "c) Turgor pressure",
            "d) Tonicity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Osmotic pressure gradient of two solutions is measured by tonicity. There are three different types of tonicity which a solution can have with respect to other solution: isotonic, hypotonic, and hypertonic."
    },
    {
        "id": 682,
        "Question": "Name the condition in which protoplast of the plant cell shrinks away.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Turgid",
            "b) Plasmolysis",
            "c) Flaccid",
            "d) Rigid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Turgor pressure is the pressure exerted by the cell wall outwardly by expanding the protoplast."
    },
    {
        "id": 683,
        "Question": "Which of the following type of solution has lower levels of solutes than the solution?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Isotonic",
            "b) Hypertonic",
            "c) Hypotonic",
            "d) Anisotonic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Plamolysis is the condition of the cell which causes the shrinkage of protoplast, when the cell is placed in the hypertonic solution i.e., water moves out of the cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 684,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT the component of water potential?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Osmotic potential",
            "b) Pressure potential",
            "c) Gravitational potential",
            "d) Assimilation potential"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hypotonic is the condition of the cell where the solute level is higher as compared to the solution. Due to the hypotonic condition water moves inside the cell from the surrounding."
    },
    {
        "id": 685,
        "Question": "The primary site of water absorption is___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Phloem",
            "b) Xylem",
            "c) Shoot",
            "d) Root"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The absorption of water takes place from the radical root which is developed by the germination of seed and is called as the first root."
    },
    {
        "id": 686,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT the development zone of developing roots?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Radical zone",
            "b) Meristematic zone",
            "c) Elongation zone",
            "d) Maturation zone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Developing roots have been differentiated into three development zones i.e., meristematic zone. Maturation zone, and elongation zone."
    },
    {
        "id": 687,
        "Question": "Which of the following zone is also known as the root hair zone?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Radical zone",
            "b) Maturation zone",
            "c) Elongation zone",
            "d) Meristematic zone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The zone of differentiation, maturation zone is also known as the root hair zone. Root hairs are the extensions which increase the surface area and help in absorption of more water and soil nutrients."
    },
    {
        "id": 688,
        "Question": "Name of the protein, which is involved in the transfer of water across the cellular membrane?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Keratin",
            "b) Alanine",
            "c) Arginine",
            "d) Aquaporin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Aquaporins are the transport proteins which involve the transfer of water accompanied by some submicroscopic bulk flow."
    },
    {
        "id": 689,
        "Question": "What is field capacity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Water holding capacity of the crop",
            "b) Water holding capacity of soil",
            "c) Water holding capacity of roots",
            "d) Water utilization capacity of plant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Soil is the mixture of organic and inorganic materials, water, dissolved solutes and air. The complex nature of the soil depends on its type.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 690,
        "Question": "Name the term which describes the plant wilt beyond recovery?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Saturation",
            "b) Hypertonic",
            "c) Permanent wilting",
            "d) Root pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Field capacity is the water holding capacity of the root. It shows the maximum amount of water that a soil can hold after the free drainage."
    },
    {
        "id": 691,
        "Question": "Which pathway is used to transport water from the epidermis to a tracheary element of root?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Osmotic potential",
            "b) Pressure potential",
            "c) Symplastic pathway",
            "d) Apoplastic pathway"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The amount of water, soil hold at which plant goes flaccid beyond recovery is called the permanent wilting percentage."
    },
    {
        "id": 692,
        "Question": "Name the term given to the movement of water against gravitational force, from root to the aerial parts of the plant.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ascent of sap",
            "b) Root pressure",
            "c) Radial movement",
            "d) Field capapcity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Apoplastic pathway is the major pathway for the transport of water from the epidermis to a tracheal element of roots."
    },
    {
        "id": 693,
        "Question": "Loss of water from plants in the form of water vapour is called___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Surface tension",
            "b) Cohesion",
            "c) Ascent of sap",
            "d) Transpiration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Transpiration is the process by which aerial part of the plant (mainly leaves) looses water in the form of water vapour."
    },
    {
        "id": 694,
        "Question": "Mark the one, which is NOT the form of transpiration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Radical transpiration",
            "b) Cuticular transpiration",
            "c) Lenticular transpiration",
            "d) Stomatal transpiration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Transpiration is termed on the basis of its occurrence through the plant like stomata, cuticle, and lenticles and called as stomatal, cuticular, and lenticular transpiration."
    },
    {
        "id": 695,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is NOT true regarding the cuticles of the plant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wax like covering of leaves",
            "b) Cutin is the principal substance",
            "c) Polymer of long chain fatty acids",
            "d) It is mainly composed of the only cutin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cuticle is a layer of wax covering over a leaf and is primarily composed of both wax and cutin. It is meant to check transpiration."
    },
    {
        "id": 696,
        "Question": "What are lenticels?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Epidermal structure",
            "b) A wax layer of leaves",
            "c) Opening in the bark",
            "d) Channel to transfer water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Lenticels are the small opening in the bark of the plants, mainly in stem and root and allow the exchange of gases between the atmosphere and the inner cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 697,
        "Question": "How much percentage of total transpiration is done by stomata?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5-10",
            "b) 90",
            "c) 1-5",
            "d) 60"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Stomata is responsible for the exchange of gases between environment and plants and acts as a turgor operated valve.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 698,
        "Question": "Mark the one, which is NOT the characteristics of the guard cell?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thickened inner wall",
            "b) Connected end to end",
            "c) Does not have chloroplast",
            "d) Radial micellation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Stomatal transpiration accounts for 90% of total transpiration done by plants while cuticular transpiration is 5-10% and lenticular transpiration is 1-5%."
    },
    {
        "id": 699,
        "Question": "Which light modulates osmoregulation of guard cell?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Green",
            "b) Orange",
            "c) Red",
            "d) Blue"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The epidermal cells of guard cell show chloroplast. They have a thin outer wall and thick inner wall and constitute an important functional element of the plant."
    },
    {
        "id": 700,
        "Question": "What is guttation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Exudation of xylem sap",
            "b) Root pressure",
            "c) Radial movement",
            "d) Field capacity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Blue light activates proton pumping and stimulates the synthesis of osmotically active organic solutes and maintains the osmoregulation of guard cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 701,
        "Question": "Name the specialized pores from where guttation takes place.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stomata",
            "b) Hydathodes",
            "c) Guard cell",
            "d) Lenticels"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Guttation is the exudation of xylem sap from the leaves of the plants as the liquid droplets from the tip or edge."
    },
    {
        "id": 702,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is INCORRECT for transpiration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It occurs by stomata, lenticels, and cuticle",
            "b) Water comes out as water vapour",
            "c) It occurs in all plants",
            "d) Root pressure is involved"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Hydathodes are the specialized pores in the leaves from where exudation of sap takes place by positive hydrostatic root pressure."
    },
    {
        "id": 703,
        "Question": "Those elements whose absence prevent plants from completing its life cycle are called___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Micro element",
            "b) Macro element",
            "c) Nonessential elements",
            "d) Essential elements"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In order to grow and complete their life cycle plants need certain essential nutrients. The presence of these nutrients in the form of inorganic elements is called essential elements."
    },
    {
        "id": 704,
        "Question": "Which one of the following is NOT a criteria for an element to be called as essential?",
        "Options": [
            "a) These elements need not to take part in growth and development",
            "b) The function of an element must not be replaceable",
            "c) The element should be involved in plant metabolism",
            "d) A plant cannot complete its life cycle without these elements"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Essential elements have a specific physiological role in the growth and development of plants."
    },
    {
        "id": 705,
        "Question": "Who proposed the idea of essential mineral nutrients of the plant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Leonhart Fuchs",
            "b) Aristotle",
            "c) Arnon and Stout",
            "d) Carl Linnaeus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Arnan and Stout in 1939 first proposed the idea of essential mineral nutrients for the plants. There are about 17 elements which are considered as the most essential for angiospermic plants."
    },
    {
        "id": 706,
        "Question": "Name the technique which involves the growth of a plant by suspending their roots in the air?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Diffusion",
            "b) Osmosis",
            "c) Hydroponics",
            "d) Aeroponics"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Aeropinics is a technique in which the roots of a plant are suspended in the air and being sprayed with a nutrient solution."
    },
    {
        "id": 707,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a mineral nutrient?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Carbon",
            "b) Nitrogen",
            "c) Hydrogen",
            "d) Oxygen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Nitrogen is a mineral element as it is acquired by the plants in the form of inorganic ions from the soil while carbon, hydrogen, and oxygen are non-mineral elements."
    },
    {
        "id": 708,
        "Question": "Which of the following element is needed by plants in a very small quantity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Phosphorus",
            "b) Carbon",
            "c) Sodium",
            "d) Magnesium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Elements which are needed by plants for growth in a very small quantity is called micro element or trace element. Sodium, zinc, boron, etc. are some examples of the trace element."
    },
    {
        "id": 709,
        "Question": "Name the mineral element which is required by a plant in a great amount?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Calcium",
            "b) Cobalt",
            "c) Phosphorus",
            "d) Nitrogen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Nitrogen is required by plants in a great amount as its constituent amino acids, nucleic acid, amides, proteins, nucleotides, and coenzymes."
    },
    {
        "id": 710,
        "Question": "Deficiency of which mineral causes dark green coloration of the leaves?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Phosphorus",
            "b) Potassium",
            "c) Nitrogen",
            "d) Calcium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Phosphorus deficiency in plants can lead to the formation of dead tissues in the leaves which is called necrotic spots and causes dark green color of leaves."
    },
    {
        "id": 711,
        "Question": "Which of the following is deficiency symptom of magnesium?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chlorosis in young leaves",
            "b) Chlorosis in older leaves",
            "c) Spindly and woody stem",
            "d) Elongated stem"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Deficiency of magnesium causes chlorosis in older leaves first while chlorosis in younger leaves is caused by the deficiency of sulfur."
    },
    {
        "id": 712,
        "Question": "Which of the following class of enzyme does not need manganese for its efficient activity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dehydrogenase",
            "b) Decarboxylases",
            "c) Kinases",
            "d) Nitrogenase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Nitrogenase requires molybdenum for its activity while dehydrogenase, decarboxylases, and kinases require manganese forits efficient function."
    },
    {
        "id": 713,
        "Question": "Growth regulators, which control plant growth and development are called___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Secondary metabolites",
            "b) Macro element",
            "c) Nonessential elements",
            "d) Phytohormone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Phytohormones or plant hormones are the small organic compound which is synthesized by specific cells/tissues in low concentration and promote the growth and development of the plant."
    },
    {
        "id": 714,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT a plant hormone?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Corticosteroid",
            "b) Brassinosteroid",
            "c) Polyamines",
            "d) Salicylic acid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: During the growth, cells in plant increase in the volume and become highly vacuolated, this is basically due to the turgor pressure. Plant growth is defined as an irreversible increase in size or volume."
    },
    {
        "id": 715,
        "Question": "Name the plant in which auxin was first discovered?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mustard",
            "b) Pea",
            "c) Oats",
            "d) Rice"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Corticosteroid is an animal hormone, which is produced in the adrenal cortex of the vertebrates while brassinosteroid, polyamines and salicylic acid are plant hormones."
    },
    {
        "id": 716,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT a naturally occurring auxin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Indole 3-acetic acid (IAA)",
            "b) Indole 3-butyric acid (IBA)",
            "c) Phenyl acetic acid (PAA)",
            "d) 2,4-D"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Auxin is a first plant hormone which was discovered by Frits Went in the tip of the oats (Avena sativa) coleoptiles. "
    },
    {
        "id": 717,
        "Question": "Name the amino acid which acts as a precursor of auxin biosynthesis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Serine",
            "b) Tryptophan",
            "c) Valline",
            "d) Tyrosine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: 2, 4-D is an organic compound and is known as synthetic auxin which is marketed as a herbicide."
    },
    {
        "id": 718,
        "Question": "Mark the one, which is NOT a physiological effect of auxin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cell elongation",
            "b) Stem elongation",
            "c) Cell differentiation",
            "d) Rooting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The basic chemical structure similarity between indole 3-acetic acid and tryptophan proves the connection between them. The conversion of tryptophan to auxin takes place by tryptophan dependent pathway."
    },
    {
        "id": 719,
        "Question": "Name the site of Gibberellins synthesis",
        "Options": [
            "a) Endosperm",
            "b) Coleoptile tip",
            "c) Young leaves",
            "d) Scetullum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Stem elongation is the physiological effect of Gibberellins not Auxin. Auxin involves in cell elongation, rooting, and cell differentiation."
    },
    {
        "id": 720,
        "Question": "Gibberellin that is synthesized in the shoot transported to different parts of the plant by which medium?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Xylem",
            "b) Sieve tube",
            "c) Aleurone layer",
            "d) Phloem"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Biosynthesis of Gibberellins takes place in the apical tissues and young leaves of the plant. Sometimes root tissues also produce Gibberellins."
    },
    {
        "id": 721,
        "Question": " What is bolting?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Internode elongation",
            "b) Rooting",
            "c) Shooting",
            "d) Shoot apical meristem"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: After synthesis Gibberellins transported to rest of the plant by phloem but the Gibbrellins which synthesized in roots are transported to shoots by the xylem."
    },
    {
        "id": 722,
        "Question": " Which of the following plant hormone is responsible for seed germination?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Auxin",
            "b) Gibberellin",
            "c) Ethylene",
            "d) Abscisic acid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Bolting has defined as a phenomenon of Internode elongation just before the flowering of the plant. It is normally triggered by environmental signals."
    },
    {
        "id": 723,
        "Question": "Name the first naturally occurring cytokines.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Neoxanthin",
            "b) Xanthoxin",
            "c) Zeatin",
            "d) Isopentenyl adenine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Gibberellin activates vegetative growth of the embryo by promoting the utilization of reserve food which is stored in the endosperm."
    },
    {
        "id": 724,
        "Question": " Which of the following plant hormone causes a delay in leaf senescence?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Abscisic acid",
            "b) Ethylene",
            "c) Auxin",
            "d) Cytokines"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Zeatin was the first naturally occurring cytokines, which was isolated by Miller and Letham in 1955 from the corn."
    },
    {
        "id": 725,
        "Question": "Name the stress hormone of the plant.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Brassinosteroid",
            "b) Abscisic acid",
            "c) Cytokines",
            "d) Ethylene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Senescence is an aging process which is an energy driven genetic program. Presence of cytokines delay in leaf senescence."
    },
    {
        "id": 726,
        "Question": "Deficiency in which of the following hormone causes dwarfism in the plant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ethylene",
            "b) Abscisic acid",
            "c) Gibberellin",
            "d) Brassinosteroid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Abscisic acid is a plant stress hormone which was first identified as a compound responsible for abscission of cotton fruits."
    },
    {
        "id": 727,
        "Question": "Light dependent changes in plant’s growth and development apart from photosynthesis is known as___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Phytochrome",
            "b) Dark reaction",
            "c) Light reaction",
            "d) Photomorphogenesis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Photomorphogenesis is the process of growth and development of plants, which is completed in the presence of light."
    },
    {
        "id": 728,
        "Question": "Name the red light sensitive system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Phytochrome",
            "b) Cryptochrome",
            "c) Phototropin",
            "d) Xanthophyll"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There are two light sensitive systems involved in photomorphogenesis. One is the red light response and the other one is the blue light response. Red light sensitive system is known as phytochrome while blue light system is called as cryptochrome."
    },
    {
        "id": 729,
        "Question": "Name the pigment, which is responsible for red color light?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chlorophyll",
            "b) Bilirubin",
            "c) Chromophore",
            "d) Xanthophyll"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Chromophore is the bound pigment molecule which is responsible for the red colour light in the phtochrome."
    },
    {
        "id": 730,
        "Question": "Which of the following does NOT belongs to the phytochrome gene family?",
        "Options": [
            "a) PHY B",
            "b) PHY B",
            "c) PHY C",
            "d) PHY F"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: There are two classes of phytochrome i.e., Type I and Type II phytochromes. These phytochromes proteins encoded by the phytochrome gene family named PHY."
    },
    {
        "id": 731,
        "Question": "Name the blue light photoreceptor of the plant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Photochrome",
            "b) Cryptochrome",
            "c) Phototropin",
            "d) Vernalin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cryptochrome is a chromoprotein which works as a blue light photoreceptor of plants. It is a flavoprotein i.e., Flavin complexed with protein."
    },
    {
        "id": 732,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT the function of cytochromes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inhibition of stem elongation",
            "b) Stimulation of leaf expansion",
            "c) Seed germination",
            "d) Regulation of floral initiation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Seed germination is mediated by phytochromes while inhibition of stem elongation, stimulation of leaf expansion, and regulation of floral initiation is the function of cryptochrome."
    },
    {
        "id": 733,
        "Question": "Which of the following has a major role in the regulation of chloroplast movement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Phototropin",
            "b) Photoperiodism",
            "c) Cryptochrome",
            "d) Calcium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: CRY1 and CRY2 mediate gene expression and the circadian clock in response to light. These are the nuclear proteins found in Arabidopsis."
    },
    {
        "id": 734,
        "Question": "Name the term which defines the ability of the plants to measure the length of photoperiods?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Phototropin",
            "b) Photoperiodism",
            "c) Cryptochrome",
            "d) Gravitropism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Phototoropin acts as a blue light receptor, it is a flavoprotein which has a major role in regulation of chloroplast movement and photropism."
    },
    {
        "id": 735,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT the long day plant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spring barley",
            "b) Wheat",
            "c) Spinach",
            "d) Soybean"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Photoperiodism is defined as the ability of the plant to measure the length of the photoperiods. The length of the photoperiod varies between the species."
    },
    {
        "id": 736,
        "Question": "The movement in a plant caused as a result of differential growth is called___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tactic movement",
            "b) Tropic movement",
            "c) Turgor movement",
            "d) Growth movement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Plant movement is of two types: growth movement and turgor movement. Growth movement occurs by differential growth of plants while turgor movement is caused by changes in turgidity of the cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 737,
        "Question": "Name the term which is given to the plants that grow at right angles to the direction of gravity.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Diagravitropic",
            "b) Positive gravitropism",
            "c) Negaitve gravitropism",
            "d) Plagiogravitropic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Phototropic is the response of the plant towards a light. The shoots of the plant are positively phototropic while roots are negatively phototropic."
    },
    {
        "id": 738,
        "Question": "Which of the following controls the distribution of auxin in the roots?",
        "Options": [
            "a) LEAFY",
            "b) IAA",
            "c) PIN",
            "d) AP2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Diagravitropic plants are those in which organs of the plant grows at right angle of the gravity while organs that grows at some intermediate angle are called plagiogravitropic."
    },
    {
        "id": 739,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT a Nastic movement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Photonasty",
            "b) Theremonasty",
            "c) Seismonasty",
            "d) Phytonasty"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: PIN protein is essential to control the distribution of auxin in the root. PIN1 regulate transport from shoot to root. "
    },
    {
        "id": 740,
        "Question": "Name the term which defines the plant movement by touch?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Seismonasty",
            "b) Thigmonasty",
            "c) Nyctinasty",
            "d) Photonasty"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Nastic movement is plant movement which occurs due to environmental stimuli, but the direction of response is not dependent on the direction of stimulus."
    },
    {
        "id": 741,
        "Question": "Name the movement of the plant in response to a magnetic field?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Geotaxis",
            "b) Magnetotaxis",
            "c) Phototaxis",
            "d) Rheotaxis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Thigmonasty is the movement of plant organ induced by touch. Seismonasty defines the induction of movement by shaking."
    },
    {
        "id": 742,
        "Question": "Which of the following term defines the mechanical removal of the seed coat?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Germination",
            "b) Dormancy",
            "c) Scarification",
            "d) Scetullum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Tactic movement is dependent on the external stimulus. On the basis of different stimulus it is of many types, i.e., phototaxis, magnetotaxis, geotaxis etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 743,
        "Question": "Metabolic intermediates found in living system which are essential for growth and life  is called___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Saponins",
            "b) Tannins",
            "c) Secondary metabolite",
            "d) Primary metabolites"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Primary metabolites are the essential metabolic intermediates of the plants which help in the growth and development of the plant."
    },
    {
        "id": 744,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT the class of secondary metabolite.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Amino acids",
            "b) Terpenes",
            "c) Phenolics",
            "d) Alkaloids"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Primary metabolites are essential for plant growth while secondary metabolite is non-essential components of plant growth."
    },
    {
        "id": 745,
        "Question": "How many isoprene units, are there in sesquiterpenes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Amino acids are the example of primary metabolites. Plants secondary metabolites have been divided into four classes, i.e., phenolics, terpenes, glycosides, and alkaloids."
    },
    {
        "id": 746,
        "Question": "Which of the following does NOT take part in the biosynthesis of terpenes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mevalonic acid",
            "b) Methylerythritol phosphate",
            "c) Acetyl-COA",
            "d) Phenol"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Terpens has been classified on the basis of the number of isoprene units present in its structure. Sesquiterpenes composed of 3 isoprene units. "
    },
    {
        "id": 747,
        "Question": "Beta-carotene, a plant pigment falls under which of the following classes of terpenes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Triterpenes",
            "b) Teteraterpenes",
            "c) Diterpenes",
            "d) Polyterpenes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Biosynthesis of terpenes takes place by two pathways, i.e., mevalonic acid pathway and MEP pathway. Phenol does not take part in the synthesis of terpenes."
    },
    {
        "id": 748,
        "Question": "Name the class of secondary metabolites which is characterized by the presence of the hydroxyl group with an aromatic ring?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glycosides",
            "b) Phenolics",
            "c) Alkaloids",
            "d) Terpenes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Tetraterpenes consists of four isoprene units. Beta-carotene is a plant pigment which is responsible for red, yellow, and orange color."
    },
    {
        "id": 749,
        "Question": "Which of the following class does NOT belong to phenolic compounds?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Xanthone",
            "b) Lignans",
            "c) Gossypol",
            "d) Flavonoids"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Phenolics are the class of secondary metabolites which is known for the presence of aromatic ring structure along with the hydroxyl group. "
    },
    {
        "id": 750,
        "Question": "Name the phenolic compound present in tea?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flavonoids",
            "b) Lignans",
            "c) Stilbene",
            "d) Neolignans"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Phenolic compounds have been characterized by the number of carbon atom it contains. Except for gossypol all other are phenolic compounds. Gossypol is the example of terpenes."
    },
    {
        "id": 751,
        "Question": "Epicatechin gallate (ECG) is a type of flavonoid, found in which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Orange",
            "b) Green tea",
            "c) Berries",
            "d) Carrot"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Phenolic compound found in tea is catechin which belongs to the class of flavon 3-ol. Flavon 3-ol is the part of the flavonoid family."
    },
    {
        "id": 752,
        "Question": "Group of cells, which is similar in structure and function are structured into___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Organ system",
            "b) Muscles",
            "c) Bone",
            "d) Tissues"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Tissues are the group of cells which have similar structure and functions. Different tissues grouped together to form organs."
    },
    {
        "id": 753,
        "Question": "Name the tissues that are involved in the formation of membranes.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Epithelial tissue",
            "b) Nervous tissue",
            "c) Muscular tissue",
            "d) Connective tissue"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Tissue is the group of cells that have a common embryonic origin and have a similar structure and function to carry out specialized activities."
    },
    {
        "id": 754,
        "Question": "What is the name of the tissues which helps in protection and support of the body?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Muscular tissue",
            "b) Nervous tissue",
            "c) Connective tissue",
            "d) Epithelial tissue"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Epithelial tissues form a membrane which is used to cover and line the surface of glands and the body."
    },
    {
        "id": 755,
        "Question": "Name the tissues which detect changes inside and outside the body and respond by action potential?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Epithelial tissue",
            "b) Connective tissue",
            "c) Muscular tissue",
            "d) Nervous tissue"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Basic function of connective tissues is the protection of the body. There are various types of connective tissues which bind organ together, provide immunity to a pathogenic organism and store energy reserves as fat. "
    },
    {
        "id": 756,
        "Question": "Which of the following tissues helps in the movement of body structure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nervous tissue",
            "b) Muscular tissue",
            "c) Epithelial tissue",
            "d) Connective tissue"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Nervous tissue helps in maintaining homeostasis by detecting changes inside and outside the body and providing response in the form of nerve impulse or action potential."
    },
    {
        "id": 757,
        "Question": "Which of the following does not belong to the class of covering and lining epithelium?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Simple squamous epithelium",
            "b) Glandular epithelium",
            "c) Simple cuboidal",
            "d) Simple columnar"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Movement in body structure is supported by the muscular tissues. Muscular tissues form during embryonic development of the process of myogenesis."
    },
    {
        "id": 758,
        "Question": "Name the epithelium which consists of two or more than two layers of cells that protect the core tissues?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pseudostratified columnar epithelium",
            "b) Simple columnar epithelium",
            "c) Stratified epithelium",
            "d) Simple cuboidal epithelium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Glandular epithelium does not belong to the covering and lining epithelium but these are the separate class of epithelial tissues which is involved in the secretion. "
    },
    {
        "id": 759,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT true regarding glandular epithelium?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Secretion is done only by a group of cells",
            "b) Present in cluster form",
            "c) Takes part in the secretion",
            "d) Lie deep to the covering and lining epithelium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Stratified epithelium consists of more than two layers of the cells. It protects the underlying tissues at the location where it occurs."
    },
    {
        "id": 760,
        "Question": "Most abundant and widely distributed tissues of the body is___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Organ system",
            "b) Muscular tissue",
            "c) Nervous tissue",
            "d) Connective tissue"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Connective tissues are composed of two basic elements, i.e., cells and extracellular matrix. These tissues are widely distributed in the body."
    },
    {
        "id": 761,
        "Question": "Which of the following does not come under the category of loose connective tissue?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Elastic connective tissue",
            "b) Adipose tissue",
            "c) Areolar tissue",
            "d) Reticular connective tissue"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Connective tissues are highly vascular so that they have a rich blood supply, but the cartilage is avascular and does not have blood vessels."
    },
    {
        "id": 762,
        "Question": "Name the tissue, which stores triglycerides (fats)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Regular connective tissue",
            "b) Areolar tissue",
            "c) Adipose tissue",
            "d) Epithelial tissue"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Elastic connective tissue falls under the category of dense connective tissue while areolar, reticular, and adipose tissues are loose connective tissues."
    },
    {
        "id": 763,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT the function of areolar connective tissues?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Strength",
            "b) Elasticity",
            "c) Support",
            "d) Forms stroma of organs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Adipose tissues consist of adipocytes which stores fat in the form of triglycerides as a large, centrally located droplet followed by the nucleus and cytoplasm at the periphery. "
    },
    {
        "id": 764,
        "Question": "Mark the one, which is not the location of the hyaline cartilage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) End of long bones",
            "b) Menisci of the knee",
            "c) Anterior end of ribs",
            "d) Nose"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Stroma of organs are formed by the reticular connective tissues while strength, elasticity, and support are provided by the areolar connective tissues."
    },
    {
        "id": 765,
        "Question": "Among the following which one is not the location of smooth muscle cells?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Iris of the eye",
            "b) Airways to the lungs",
            "c) Heart wall",
            "d) Urinary bladder"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Hyaline cartilage consists of blue-white, shiny ground substance with collagen fibers. Fibrocartilage found in menisci of the knee."
    },
    {
        "id": 766,
        "Question": "Mark the one, which is NOT the location of endocrine glands?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pituitary gland",
            "b) Salivary gland",
            "c) Adrenal glands",
            "d) Thyroid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Heart wall is composed of cardiac muscle tissue while iris of the eye, airways to the lungs, and urinary bladder are controlled by smooth muscle cells. "
    },
    {
        "id": 767,
        "Question": "System of the body which coordinates and controls its activity is known as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Organ system",
            "b) Muscular system",
            "c) Nervous tissue",
            "d) Nervous system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Nervous system is the one which is responsible for all the activities of the body. It coordinates and controls the activities of the animal."
    },
    {
        "id": 768,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT the component of the PNS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Elastic connective tissue",
            "b) Cranial nerves",
            "c) Spinal nerves",
            "d) Ganglia"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Nervous system has two subdivisions, i.e., CNS and PNS. CNS or central nervous system consists of the brain and spinal cord while PNS or peripheral nervous system includes all nervous tissues outside the CNS."
    },
    {
        "id": 769,
        "Question": "Name the basic structural and functional unit of the nervous system.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Neuroglia",
            "b) Glial cells",
            "c) Neurons",
            "d) Perikaryon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Peripheral nervous tissue consists of all nervous tissue outside the central nervous system. The main components of PNS are spinal nerves and their branches, cranial nerves and their branches, sensory receptors, and ganglia."
    },
    {
        "id": 770,
        "Question": "Which of the following cells supports, nourishes, and protect the neurons?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nissl bodies",
            "b) Perikaryon",
            "c) Ganglia",
            "d) Glial cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Nervous system has been composed of two types of cells, i.e., neurons and neuroglia. Neurons are the basic functional and structural unit of the nervous system. "
    },
    {
        "id": 771,
        "Question": "What is the speed of nerve impulse?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 60 m/s",
            "b) 0.5 – 130 m/s",
            "c) 10-30 m/s",
            "d) 50 -150 m/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Glial cells (glia = glue)are also called neuroglia, these cells support, nourishes, and protect the neurons while ganglia are the cluster of cell bodies which found in the PNS."
    },
    {
        "id": 772,
        "Question": "What are Nissl bodies?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Golgi bodies",
            "b) Lysosomes",
            "c) Cluster of rough endoplasmic reticulum",
            "d) Mitochondria"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Nerve impulse or action potential is the electrical signals which travel through the membrane of the neurons. The speed of these signals ranges from 0.5 to 130 m/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 773,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT found in axon?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Endoplasmic reticulum",
            "b) Neurofibrils",
            "c) Mitochondria",
            "d) Microtubules"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Neurons are made up of three parts, i.e., cell body, dendrites, and axon. The cell body consists of ribosomes and a cluster of endoplasmic reticulum, which is known as Nissl bodies. "
    },
    {
        "id": 774,
        "Question": "Name the multipolar neuron which is located entirely within the central nervous system.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Motor neuron",
            "b) Efferent neuron",
            "c) Afferent neuron",
            "d) Interneuron"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Endoplasmic reticulum is not present in axons as it does not synthesize protein. An axon contains mitochondria, neurofibril, and microtubule and the cytoplasm of an axon is called axoplasm."
    },
    {
        "id": 775,
        "Question": "Out of the following, which one does not affect the speed of conduction of nerve impulse.",
        "Options": [
            "a) No. of ganglia",
            "b) Myelin sheath",
            "c) Axon diameter",
            "d) Temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Interneurons are the multipolar neurons, which are found within the CNS. Motor neurons are also known as efferent neurons, they transfer signals from the CNS to effector organs."
    },
    {
        "id": 776,
        "Question": "Organs involve in the sensation of the body is known as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Organ system",
            "b) Muscular system",
            "c) Nervous tissue",
            "d) Sensory organs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Those organs which include hearing, seeing, taste and smell are known as sensory organs. For ex: eye, ear, nose, skin, and tongue."
    },
    {
        "id": 777,
        "Question": "Which of the following is known as the “window of the brain”?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sensory organs",
            "b) Cranial nerves",
            "c) Eyes",
            "d) Ganglia"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There are number of receptors in the eye, the lens concentrates light on these receptors which thusly made a motivation. This drive goes to the cerebrum and produces pictures."
    },
    {
        "id": 778,
        "Question": "Which of the following helps in maintaining the shape of the eye?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Neuroglia",
            "b) Aqueous humor",
            "c) Vitreous humor",
            "d) Perikaryon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sensory organs are considered as the “window of the brain”. When external stimuli contacted with sensory receptors, it sends signals to the brain in the form of nerve impulse which results in the sensation."
    },
    {
        "id": 779,
        "Question": "Mark the INCORRECT statement about the lens?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Protein found in the lens are α, β, and γ crystalline",
            "b) Composed of water and proteins",
            "c) Mainly made up of water",
            "d) It has a blood supply"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Vitreous humor is a viscous mass that helps in maintaining the shape of the eye. The lens is surrounded by the aqueous humor from one side and vitreous humor from the other side."
    },
    {
        "id": 780,
        "Question": "What is Sclera?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cornea",
            "b) White part of the eye",
            "c) Red part of the eye",
            "d) Lens"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Though lens does not have a blood supply, it is active. Lens is basically made up of water and protein and many vertebrates have lens protein α, β, and γ crystalline."
    },
    {
        "id": 781,
        "Question": "Name the part of the eye, which is involved in focusing light on the retina?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sclera",
            "b) Iris",
            "c) Cornea",
            "d) Ciliary muscles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sclera is the white part of the eye which covers the entire eye except for cornea and is made up of collagen fibers and fibroblast."
    },
    {
        "id": 782,
        "Question": "Iris is found in which layer of the eyeball?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vascular tunic",
            "b) Retina",
            "c) Fibrous tunic",
            "d) Microtubules"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Fibrous tunic is composed of anterior cornea and posterior sclera. It is a surface coating of an eyeball. Transparent cornea covered colored iris and it helps in focussing light on the retina."
    },
    {
        "id": 783,
        "Question": "Among the following, which is one is more vascularized and pigmented.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cornea",
            "b) Iris",
            "c) Ciliary body",
            "d) Choroid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Eyeball is made up of three layers, i.e., fibrous tunic, vascular tunic, and retina. The middle layer of the eyeball is a vascular tunic. It consists of three parts: ciliary body, iris, and choroid."
    },
    {
        "id": 784,
        "Question": "Name the part of the eye which produces aqueous fluid that fills the front part of the eye.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ciliary body",
            "b) Cornea",
            "c) Vitreous humor",
            "d) Uvea"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Choroid is highly pigmented with melanin and vascularized structure which forms the posterior region of vascular tunic. It absorbs scattered light and also supplies blood."
    },
    {
        "id": 785,
        "Question": "In human ear, secretion of wax is done by___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cochlea",
            "b) Vestibule",
            "c) Basilar membrane",
            "d) Ceruminous glands"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Human ear has the number of sweat glands called ceruminous glands. These glands are present on the skin from exterior to interior part. The secretion of these glands called cerumen or wax."
    },
    {
        "id": 786,
        "Question": "Conversion of vibrations into compressed wave takes place in which part of human ear?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inner ear",
            "b) Middle ear",
            "c) Outer ear",
            "d) Exterior ear"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The human ear works as a transducer which converts sound energy into mechanical energy to a nerve impulse which further detected by the brain."
    },
    {
        "id": 787,
        "Question": "Name the light absorbing pigment present in the Rods?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Neuroglia",
            "b) Aqueous humor",
            "c) Rhodopsin",
            "d) Perikaryon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ear is broadly divided into three parts that are outer, middle, and inner. Sound wave goes through the outer ear gets converted to vibration by middle ear. Passing of vibration to inner ear further converts it in the form of compresses wave."
    },
    {
        "id": 788,
        "Question": "Name the G- protein, which takes part in vision?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ethylene",
            "b) Adenosine",
            "c) Acetylcholine",
            "d) Transducin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The light absorbing pigment present in the rods is rhodopsin and it is also a G-protein coupled receptor which upon activation activates transducin."
    },
    {
        "id": 789,
        "Question": "What is the absorption peak of green absorbing cones?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 565 nm",
            "b) 535 nm",
            "c) 768 nm",
            "d) 440 nm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Rhodopsin activates molecules of transducin which further activates an enzyme to break down cyclic GMP. The drop in cyclic GMP will open sodium channel which is responsible for vision."
    },
    {
        "id": 790,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT true for Rods?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Used for scotopic vision",
            "b) Loss causes night blindness",
            "c) Not very light sensitive",
            "d) Confer achromatic vision"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The color vision of our eye is dependent on the three types of cones, i.e., green absorbing, red absorbing cones, and blue absorbing cones. "
    },
    {
        "id": 791,
        "Question": "Name the tiny bone of the middle ear, which convert sound into vibration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stapes",
            "b) Malleus",
            "c) Incus",
            "d) Anvil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Rods are very light sensitive while cons are not that much light sensitive. Cons enable us to see colors by producing sharpest images."
    },
    {
        "id": 792,
        "Question": "Chemical messengers secreted by ductless glands are called___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lymph",
            "b) Platelets",
            "c) Plasma",
            "d) Hormones"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Hormones are the chemical messengers which are secreted by the ductless glands called endocrine glands. These glands are controlled by the endocrine system."
    },
    {
        "id": 793,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT an endocrine gland?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hypothalamus",
            "b) Pituitary",
            "c) Parathyroid",
            "d) Pancreas"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Endocrine glands are called ductless glands. They secrete their products directly into the bloodstreams and circulate in the body."
    },
    {
        "id": 794,
        "Question": "Which of this statement is INCORRECT regarding the function of hormones?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reproduction and sexual differentiation",
            "b) Maintenance of internal environment",
            "c) Maintain body temperature",
            "d) Development and growth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: All of them are endocrine glands except hypothalamus. Hypothalamus and thymus are not classified as an endocrine gland, but included in the endocrine system as they involve in the secretion of hormones."
    },
    {
        "id": 795,
        "Question": "Mark the one, which is NOT the precursor of the hormone?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Amino acids",
            "b) Cholesterol",
            "c) Phospholipids",
            "d) Proteins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hormones are released by specialized cells of the endocrine glands and act on distantly located target cells. A single hormone can contribute many functions and sometimes many hormones can perform a single function."
    },
    {
        "id": 796,
        "Question": "What is the precursor of steroid hormone?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Protein",
            "b) Cholesterol",
            "c) Carbohydrate",
            "d) Lipid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Chemically, hormone can be divided into two categories, i.e., lipid soluble and water soluble hormones."
    },
    {
        "id": 797,
        "Question": "Which of the is a fat soluble hormone?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Amine hormone",
            "b) Peptide hormone",
            "c) Thyroid hormone",
            "d) Protein hormone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cholesterol acts as a precursor of steroid hormone. DHEA is a natural steroid hormone which is synthesized from cholesterol."
    },
    {
        "id": 798,
        "Question": "Name the hormone which is synthesized from histidine amino acid?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Histamine",
            "b) Epinephrine",
            "c) Norepinephrine",
            "d) Dopamine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Thyroid is a lipid soluble hormone while amine, peptide, and protein hormones are water soluble, ranging from size 3 to over 200 amino acids."
    },
    {
        "id": 799,
        "Question": "Which of the following is protein hormone?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oxytocin",
            "b) Insulin",
            "c) TSH",
            "d) Antidiuretic hormone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Epinephrine, norepinephrine, and dopamine are amine hormones, which are synthesized by modifying amino acid tyrosine. "
    },
    {
        "id": 800,
        "Question": "Name the gland, which releases Neurohormone.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hypothalamus",
            "b) Pituitary",
            "c) Thyroid",
            "d) Pancreas"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Insulin and human growth hormones are protein hormone while oxytocin and antidiuretic hormones are peptide hormones. TSH or thyroid stimulating hormone has carbohydrate attached to the protein so it comes under glycoprotein hormone."
    },
    {
        "id": 801,
        "Question": "Name the hormone which takes part in the release of FSH and LH from the anterior pituitary.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Growth hormone",
            "b) GnRH",
            "c) Somatostatin",
            "d) TRH"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Neurohormone are those which changes their function according to their requirements like they can be releasing hormones or inhibiting hormone."
    },
    {
        "id": 802,
        "Question": "Which of the following is Growth hormone inhibiting hormone?",
        "Options": [
            "a) FSH",
            "b) TRH",
            "c) GHRH",
            "d) Somatostatin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: GnRH is Gonadotropin Releasing Hormone, which is responsible for the release of follicle stimulating hormone (FSH), and luteinizing hormone (LH)."
    },
    {
        "id": 803,
        "Question": "Mark the one, which is not inhibited by the effect of somatostatin.",
        "Options": [
            "a) GH",
            "b) TSH",
            "c) Glucagon",
            "d) Dopamine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Somatostatin works against the growth hormone (GHRH), so it is known as growth inhibiting hormone. It consists of two peptides of 14 and 28 amino acids and is released from neurosecretory nerves."
    },
    {
        "id": 804,
        "Question": "Name the hormone, which is released by the posterior pituitary.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oxytocin",
            "b) TSH",
            "c) ICSH",
            "d) Prolactin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Dopamine is prolactin inhibiting hormone (PIH), which inhibit the release of prolactin from the anterior pituitary. It also functions as a neurotransmitter."
    },
    {
        "id": 805,
        "Question": " Name the process of gaseous exchange in the body.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lymphatic system",
            "b) Respiration",
            "c) Cardiovascular system",
            "d) Respiratory system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Respiration is the process of gaseous exchange in the body while cardiovascular regulates the blood flow throughout the body."
    },
    {
        "id": 806,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT the function of the respiratory system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Regulate blood pH",
            "b) Helps in gaseous exchange",
            "c) Protection against blood loss",
            "d) Contains receptors for the sense of smell"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Respiratory system consists of all the organs which take part in the respiration. It includes bronchi, trachea, lungs, nose, larynx, and pharynx."
    },
    {
        "id": 807,
        "Question": "Which of this statement is TRUE for pulmonary respiration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Exchange of gases between alveoli of lungs and the blood",
            "b) Exchange of gases between blood and tissue cells",
            "c) Breathing between the atmosphere and the alveoli of the lungs",
            "d) Production of ATP"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Respiratory system helps in regulation of blood, pH, and also contain receptors of smell, produces vocal sound and filter inspired air while cardiovascular system protects against blood loss by the formation of blood clots."
    },
    {
        "id": 808,
        "Question": "Which of the following controls the normal breathing process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Amino acids",
            "b) Cholesterol",
            "c) Ventral respiratory group",
            "d) Dorsal respiratory group"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pulmonary respiration is the exchange of gases between the alveoli of the lungs and the blood in the capillaries. Exchange of gases between blood and tissue cell occurs in internal respiration."
    },
    {
        "id": 809,
        "Question": "Oxygen and hemoglobin bind in a reversible manner to form______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Carboxyhemoglobin",
            "b) Oxyhemoglobin",
            "c) Methoglobin",
            "d) BPG"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Ventral respiratory group contains both inspiratory and expiratory neurons and controlled forced breathing while dorsal respiratory group contains only inspiratory neurons control normal breathing."
    },
    {
        "id": 810,
        "Question": "How many oxygen molecules bound to hemoglobin to give 50% saturation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Oxyhemoglobin is formed by the combination of oxygen and hemoglobin. Oxygen binds to the hemoglobin in a reversible manner. 98% of oxygen is trapped inside RBC."
    },
    {
        "id": 811,
        "Question": "What is the name of the gland which secrete melatonin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pituitary gland",
            "b) Pineal gland",
            "c) Thyroid gland",
            "d) Hypothalamus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hemoglobin can bind with maximum 4 oxygen molecules, so for obtaining 50% saturation only 2 molecules of oxygen should be bound to hemoglobin."
    },
    {
        "id": 812,
        "Question": "The branch of science deals with blood, blood forming tissues and its disorders is called___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hemopoiesis",
            "b) Cardiovascular system",
            "c) Plasmology",
            "d) Hematology"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cardiovascular system consists of mainly three components: blood, heart, and blood vessels while Hematology is the branch of science which deals with the study of blood and its tissues."
    },
    {
        "id": 813,
        "Question": "Out of the following, which one is NOT the physical characteristics of the blood?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Volume is 15-16 liters in an average sized adult male",
            "b) Slightly alkaline pH",
            "c) Constitute 20% of extracellular fluid",
            "d) Provide 8% of total body mass"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The blood circulatory system of the human is closed, i.e., blood flow through veins and capillaries and without coming in direct contact with tissues and body cavity."
    },
    {
        "id": 814,
        "Question": "Blood helps in transportation of the following components, except one, identify that?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hormone",
            "b) Oxygen",
            "c) Heat",
            "d) Lymph"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Total 5-6 liters of blood is present in an average adult sized male, while a human female contains 4-5 liters of blood."
    },
    {
        "id": 815,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT a plasma protein?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Albumin",
            "b) Globulin",
            "c) Fibrinogen",
            "d) Fibronectin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Lymph has its own capillaries for transportation, it does not transport through the blood. Blood carries oxygen, carbon dioxide, nutrients, waste, heat, and hormones."
    },
    {
        "id": 816,
        "Question": "What is a serum in the blood?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Liquid portion of blood",
            "b) Plasma minus fibrinogen",
            "c) Tissue fluid within lymphatic vessel",
            "d) Formed elements and plasma"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Fibronectin is not a plasma protein, but it is an extracellular matrix protein which helps in binding collagen and fibrin. Albumin, globulin, and fibrinogen are plasma proteins."
    },
    {
        "id": 817,
        "Question": "Name the term which defines the amount of RBC present in the blood?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hemoglobin",
            "b) Hemopoiesis",
            "c) Hematocrit",
            "d) Myoglobin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Serum is plasma minus fibrinogen while plasma is the liquid portion of the blood. Lymph is the tissue fluid within the lymphatic vessels."
    },
    {
        "id": 818,
        "Question": "What is the site of hemopoiesis in an embryo?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Yolk sac",
            "b) Liver",
            "c) Thymus",
            "d) Spleen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hematocrit is the percentage of the RBC present in the blood, like if the value of hematocrit is 40 percent, then the volume of blood is 40% occupied by RBC."
    },
    {
        "id": 819,
        "Question": "Name the term given to abnormally low levels of white blood cells?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Leukocytosis",
            "b) Leucopenia",
            "c) Lymphocyte",
            "d) Thrombopoietin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Hemopoiesis first start in the yolk sac of an embryo and later in the liver, spleen, thymus, and lymph nodes of the fetus. "
    },
    {
        "id": 820,
        "Question": "Name the term given to the failure of bone marrow to produce RBC.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aplastic anemia",
            "b) Hemolytic anemia",
            "c) Thalassemia",
            "d) Hemorrhagic anemia"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Leucopenia is a condition when the count of white blood cells goes below 5000/microliter while leukocytosis is an increase in the number of WBC above 10,000 microliters."
    },
    {
        "id": 821,
        "Question": "Which type of anemia is responsible for the disease thalassemia?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aplastic anemia",
            "b) Hemolytic anemia",
            "c) Hemorrhagic anemia",
            "d) Iron deficiency anemia"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Aplastic anemia is the condition when bone marrow failed to produce RBC or red bone marrow gets destructed by any toxic chemicals or radiations."
    },
    {
        "id": 822,
        "Question": "Which of the following membrane is responsible for the protection of the heart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Epicardium",
            "b) Endocardium",
            "c) Myocardium",
            "d) Pericardium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Thalassemia is a type of hereditary disease where hemoglobin does not synthesize properly and results in the destruction of a large number of red blood cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 823,
        "Question": "ECG records electrical changes in which of the following layers of the heart, mark the correct option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Epicardium",
            "b) Pericardium",
            "c) Endocardium",
            "d) Myocardium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Pericardium surrounds the heart and protects it. It is composed of tough, dense, inelastic, and irregular connective tissues."
    },
    {
        "id": 824,
        "Question": "What is the pH of the saliva?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3-5",
            "b) 7-8",
            "c) 5.5-6.2",
            "d) 6.2-7.4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Saliva is a colorless viscous liquid which has a pH between 6.2 to 7.4. The enzyme present in saliva shows its optimal activity at pH 6.8."
    },
    {
        "id": 825,
        "Question": "Out of the following, which is a major secretory layer of the GI tract?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mucosa",
            "b) Submucosa",
            "c) Muscularis",
            "d) Serosa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Saliva contains amylase enzyme which digests the carbohydrate present in the food. It breaks down polysaccharides onto maltose, which is a disaccharide."
    },
    {
        "id": 826,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT the salivary protein?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lysozyme",
            "b) Mucus",
            "c) Phosphatase",
            "d) Amylase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: GI tract or Gastrointestinal tract is composed of four layers, i.e., mucosa, submucosa, muscularis, and serosa. Mucosa lines the lumen of the GI tract and is the major absorptive and secretory layer."
    },
    {
        "id": 827,
        "Question": "Name the type of secretory cell which secretes hydrochloric acid in the stomach?",
        "Options": [
            "a) D-cell",
            "b) G-cell",
            "c) Mucous cell",
            "d) Parietal cell"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Salivary proteins are those which are present in the saliva. It includes amylase, lysozyme, and mucus. "
    },
    {
        "id": 828,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT the function of the large intestine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Forming feces",
            "b) Absorb 90% of nutrients",
            "c) Defecating",
            "d) Absorbing some water, ions, and vitamins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Hydrochloric acid or gastric juice in the stomach is secreted by parietal cells while G-cell secretes gastrin and D-cells secrete somatostatin."
    },
    {
        "id": 829,
        "Question": "Which of the following gastric secretion phase prepares mouth and stomach for food?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Intestinal phase",
            "b) Gastric phase",
            "c) Cephalic phase",
            "d) Early phase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Large intestine does not absorb nutrients, but it absorbs some amount of water along with ions and vitamins. About 90% of nutrients are absorbed by the small intestine."
    },
    {
        "id": 830,
        "Question": "Which of the following kidney function is NOT true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Regulate blood volume and composition",
            "b) Synthesize glucose",
            "c) Regulate blood pressure",
            "d) Defend the body against disease"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Gastric secretion has been divided into three phases, i.e., gastric phase, cephalic phase, and intestinal phase. Cephalic phase refers to the increased secretion of HCl and pepsinogen, which prepares mouth and stomach for the food."
    },
    {
        "id": 831,
        "Question": "Out of the following, which is the first step in urine production?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glomerular filtration",
            "b) Tubular secretion",
            "c) Tubular reabsorption",
            "d) Urinary bladder store urine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Kidney is the primary organ of excretion, it removes the nitrogenous waste from the body and maintain homeostasis also. Kidneys also synthesize glucose and hormone, regulate blood pressure and maintain the volume and composition of blood."
    },
    {
        "id": 832,
        "Question": "What is the daily volume of glomerular filtrate in adult male and female?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50 liter in male and 90 liters in females",
            "b) 120 liter in male and 130 liters in females",
            "c) 180 liter in male and 150 liters in females",
            "d) 180 liter in male and 180 liters in females"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Right side kidney is slightly lower than the left side kidney as in right side some space has been occupied by the liver."
    },
    {
        "id": 833,
        "Question": "Which of the following hormone plays a major role in water reabsorption?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Somatostatin",
            "b) Relaxasin",
            "c) Oxytocin",
            "d) Vasopressin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Glomerular filtration is the first step in urine production where water and other solutes in the blood plasma moves across its wall and passes to renal tubule."
    },
    {
        "id": 834,
        "Question": "What is micturition?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Formation of feces",
            "b) Discharge of urine",
            "c) Defecating",
            "d) Formation of sperm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Average glomerular filtrate is 180 liter in male and 150 liters in female daily. More than 99% of the filtrate returns to the blood by tubular reabsorption and only 1-2 liter is excreted as urine.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 835,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT the characteristics of the normal urine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Yellow or amber color",
            "b) Mildly aromatic",
            "c) 3-4 pH",
            "d) 1.001 to 1.035 specific gravity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Vasopressin is also known as antidiuretic hormone, released from the posterior lobe of the pituitary gland. ADH absorbs more water into the blood and decreases the amount of urine."
    },
    {
        "id": 836,
        "Question": "The primary sex organ is known as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Regulate blood volume and composition",
            "b) Synthesize glucose",
            "c) Regulate blood pressure",
            "d) Gonads"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The reproductive system consists of primary sex organs, secondary sex organs, and accessory sex organs. Gonads are primary sex organs which produce gametes and hormones."
    },
    {
        "id": 837,
        "Question": "Name the site of sperm maturation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Epididymis",
            "b) Ductus deferens",
            "c) Spermatic cord",
            "d) Urethra"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The testes descend to scrotum to lower the temperature up to 3°C which is viable for sperm production, but cryptorchidism is the condition when the testes do not descend into the scrotum and remain in the abdominal cavity."
    },
    {
        "id": 838,
        "Question": "Which of the following produces the male sex hormone?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rete testis",
            "b) Seminiferous tubule",
            "c) Leydig cell",
            "d) Scrotum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Epididymis lies along the posterior border of testes. It is a site of sperm maturation, the process by which sperm gets its motility and ability to fertilize an ovum."
    },
    {
        "id": 839,
        "Question": " Which of the following is an energy source for the sperm?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Somatostatin",
            "b) Prostaglandin",
            "c) Proteins",
            "d) Fructose"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Male sex hormone, i.e., testosterone produces from the interstitial cells or Leydig cells. These cells are located between the seminiferous tubule inside the lobule. "
    },
    {
        "id": 840,
        "Question": "Mark the INCORRECT statement about prostate gland?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Located inferior to the urinary bladder",
            "b) Secretion is thin and milky colored",
            "c) Secretion is acidic in nature",
            "d) Function in increasing the mobility of the sperm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The fluid from the seminal vesicle contains fructose for an energy source, protein for coagulation reaction and prostaglandins for mobility and viability of the sperm."
    },
    {
        "id": 841,
        "Question": "The fluid from which of the following accessory gland neutralize the acidity in a vagina of the female?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Seminal vesicle",
            "b) Prostate gland",
            "c) Cowper’s gland",
            "d) Urethra"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Prostate gland lies inferior to urinary bladder and secrete alkaline fluid which is thin and milky color in appearance and it enhances the mobility of the sperm."
    },
    {
        "id": 842,
        "Question": "Out of the following, which hormone does not secret from corpus luteum?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Estrogen",
            "b) Progesterone",
            "c) Relaxin",
            "d) Testosterone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cowper’s gland or bulbourethal glands are small in size and located near the base of the penis. After getting sexual stimulation, these glands secrete alkaline fluid which neutralizes the acidity of the vagina."
    },
    {
        "id": 843,
        "Question": "Name the process by which most of the oogonia degenerated before the birth.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Atresia",
            "b) Zona pellucida",
            "c) Acrosome",
            "d) Granulose cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Corpus luteum is the yellow body which left after the procedure of ovulation. It secretes four hormones, i.e., progesterone, estrogen, relaxin, and inhibin. Testosterone is male hormone and it doesn’t discharge from the corpus luteum."
    },
    {
        "id": 844,
        "Question": "Name the hormone which is at peak during ovulation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Progesterone",
            "b) Estrogen",
            "c) FSH",
            "d) LH"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the female reproductive cycle, germ cell divides mitotically and produces millions of oogonia. Most of the oogonia will undergo degeneration by the process known as atresia."
    },
    {
        "id": 845,
        "Question": "The process which begins after the fertilization is known as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cleavage",
            "b) Spermiogenesis",
            "c) Organogenesis",
            "d) Embryogenesis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Embryogenesis is the process of multiplication of cells by mitosis and formation of tissues and organs of a living baby. It starts once the egg has been fertilized."
    },
    {
        "id": 846,
        "Question": "Name the type of fertilization where placenta formation does not occur.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ovoviviparous",
            "b) Oviparous",
            "c) Viviparous",
            "d) Segmentation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the nucleus of the sperm cell normal histones are replaced by a special class of packaging proteins known as protamins which makes the nucleus transcriptionally inactive."
    },
    {
        "id": 847,
        "Question": "Which of the following fertilization category is found in mammals?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ovoviviparous",
            "b) Oviparous",
            "c) Viviparous",
            "d) Segmentation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ovoviviparous is the condition where fertilization is internal but there is no placenta formation. Example: dog and fishes."
    },
    {
        "id": 848,
        "Question": " Mark the one, which is NOT an egg laying animal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Frogs",
            "b) Birds",
            "c) Reptiles",
            "d) Fishes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In viviparous, fertilization is internal and nourishment is provided through placenta by the uterine wall of the mother.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 849,
        "Question": "Which of the following is Alecithal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reptiles",
            "b) Amphibians",
            "c) Mammals",
            "d) Birds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Egg laying animals fall under the category of oviparous. Here fertilization can be internal or external. Fishes are not oviparous but ovoviviparous, they are not egg laying animals."
    },
    {
        "id": 850,
        "Question": "On the type of yolk distribution, which of the following is Telolecithal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Insects",
            "b) Mammals",
            "c) Amphibians",
            "d) Birds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Animals have been categorized according to the amount of yolk in the egg. Alecithal are those organisms which have no yolk in their egg, e.g. mammals."
    },
    {
        "id": 851,
        "Question": " Name the type of eggs which do not have any protective covers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Indeterminate",
            "b) Cleidoic eggs",
            "c) Determinate",
            "d) Noncleidoic eggs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: On the basis of yolk distribution, the egg has been divided into three types, i.e., isolecithal, telolecithal, and centrolecithal. Telolecithal are those in which heavy yolk is present at a vegetal pole and less yolk at the animal pole, e.g. amphibians."
    },
    {
        "id": 852,
        "Question": "Which of the following organism has cleidoic eggs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reptiles",
            "b) Fishes",
            "c) Amphibians",
            "d) Annelids"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Noncleidoic eggs laid in Water or develop inside the mother’s body. These eggs do not have any protective covering around them, e.g., amphibians, fishes, and mammals."
    },
    {
        "id": 853,
        "Question": "Which of the following has discoidal cleavage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Frog",
            "b) Human",
            "c) Insect",
            "d) Birds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cleidoic eggs are those which laid on land and have a leathery coat around them for the prevention of its dessication e.g., birds, and reptiles."
    },
    {
        "id": 854,
        "Question": "The study of living organisms with the environment is known as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ecosystem",
            "b) Environment",
            "c) Community",
            "d) Ecology"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Ecology is the study of the relationship between living organisms and the environment. It also deals with the interaction of living organisms with each other."
    },
    {
        "id": 855,
        "Question": "Which of the following describe the study of group of the population?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Synecology",
            "b) Autecology",
            "c) Biomes",
            "d) Community"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Population is the collection of individuals which belongs to the same species in a given region. The group of populations is called communities."
    },
    {
        "id": 856,
        "Question": "What is the climate pattern in areas of limited size or immediate surroundings of plant and animal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mixed climate",
            "b) Macroclimate",
            "c) Microclimate",
            "d) Segmented climate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Synecology is the study of the group of population, while Autecology is the study of the individual or single species under certain environmental condition."
    },
    {
        "id": 857,
        "Question": " Which of the following climatic zone lies around 40°- 60° latitude?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tropical",
            "b) Subtropical",
            "c) Arctic",
            "d) Temperate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Microclimate refers to the climatic condition of the immediate surroundings of plant and animals while Macroclimate is the climatic pattern over a large area or on local, global, and regional level."
    },
    {
        "id": 858,
        "Question": "A relatively dense layer of band which is found in the thermosphere is known as?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Troposphere",
            "b) Mesosphere",
            "c) Stratosphere",
            "d) Ionosphere"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Climatic zones are defined on the basis of variation in mean temperature along the latitude like tropical, subtropical, arctic, and temperate."
    },
    {
        "id": 859,
        "Question": "Which of the following parameter of light is NOT required by plants to grow?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wavelength of light",
            "b) Intensity of light",
            "c) Duration of light",
            "d) Color of light"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Thermosphere extends 1000 km above the earth’s crust. Ionosphere is a dense band of charged particles, specifically found in the thermosphere. "
    },
    {
        "id": 860,
        "Question": " What is pedology?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Study of the effect of light on plant growth",
            "b) Study of leaves",
            "c) Study of climate",
            "d) Study of soil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Light affects the process of growth in the plant like photosynthesis and reproduction. Wavelength and intensity of light play a major role in flower induction, plant movement, and seed germination and duration of light regulates flowering and fruiting."
    },
    {
        "id": 861,
        "Question": "Name the term which is used for the water present in the soil that can be utilized by the plants.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chresard",
            "b) Humus",
            "c) Gravitational water",
            "d) Capillary water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Soil is the uppermost layer of the earth. The study of soil has been divided into two types, i.e., pedology and edaphology. Edaphology deals with the effect of soil on other living organisms."
    },
    {
        "id": 862,
        "Question": "Name the type of water stored in the soil in the form of hydrated oxides of iron, silicon, and aluminium?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gravitational water",
            "b) Capillary water",
            "c) Hygroscopic water",
            "d) Chemically bound water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Chresard is the term given to the available water in the soil, which can be utilized by the plants. Water is basically present in the thin and narrow capillaries formed from the soil."
    },
    {
        "id": 863,
        "Question": "Vegetation of tropical deciduous forest falls under which of the following categories?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mesotherm",
            "b) Megatherm",
            "c) Microtherm",
            "d) Hekistotherm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Chemically bound water is not available for the plants as it is present in the form of hydrated oxides of iron, silicon, and aluminium."
    },
    {
        "id": 864,
        "Question": "Genetically different population with the same physical features is known as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ecosystem",
            "b) Ecads",
            "c) Community",
            "d) Ecotype"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Ecotype is a population which has different genetic features, but adapted to specific environmental condition and have similar physical features."
    },
    {
        "id": 865,
        "Question": "Name the group of species which exploit the abiotic and biotic resources in a similar way?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Guild",
            "b) Ecads",
            "c) Biomes",
            "d) Community"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Niche is not a place, but an idea. It is a summary of an organism’s requirement and tolerance. Habitat is a place where a particular organism lives."
    },
    {
        "id": 866,
        "Question": "Who proposed the term ecosystem?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Grinnel",
            "b) Turesson",
            "c) A.G. Tansley",
            "d) Lindeman"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Guild species are need not be taxonomically related, these are the species which exploit the resources in a similar way."
    },
    {
        "id": 867,
        "Question": " Name the organisms that manufacture organic compounds from simple inorganic compounds without using sunlight?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Detrivores",
            "b) Organotrophs",
            "c) Phototrophs",
            "d) Chemotrophs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A.G. Tansley has given the term ecosystem in 1935. Ecosystem comprises of all the biotic and abiotic components and their interactions."
    },
    {
        "id": 868,
        "Question": "Which of the following organism eats feces?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fungus",
            "b) Bacteria",
            "c) Earthworm",
            "d) Dung beetle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Chemotrophs is a kind of autotroph which manufacture organic compounds from simple inorganic compounds without the use of photosynthesis white phototrophs are those autotrophs which make their food by photosynthesis."
    },
    {
        "id": 869,
        "Question": "Which of the following type of productivity counts the total fixation of energy by photosynthesis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Secondary productivity",
            "b) Primary productivity",
            "c) NPP",
            "d) GPP"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Dung beetle belongs to the category of detritivores, who eat dead and decaying organic matter.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 870,
        "Question": "Hekistotherm vegetation is found in which of the following region?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High temperature",
            "b) Very low temperature",
            "c) High temperature with an alternating low temperature",
            "d) Low temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: GPP is gross primary productivity, which is a measure of total fixation of energy by means of photosynthesis."
    },
    {
        "id": 871,
        "Question": "Pyramid of numbers for grassland ecosystem is____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decreases",
            "b) Lateral",
            "c) Inverted",
            "d) Upright"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: For a grassland ecosystem, the pyramid of number is upright as the number of organisms decreases at it moves to a higher trophic level."
    },
    {
        "id": 872,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is CORRECT about the pyramid of energy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is always upright",
            "b) It is always inverted",
            "c) It doesn’t exist",
            "d) It varies with the trophic level"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Each trophic level consists of different species, pyramid of number describes the individuals of different species present at each trophic level."
    },
    {
        "id": 873,
        "Question": "Which of the following has a higher assimilation efficiency?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Omnivore",
            "b) Herbivore",
            "c) Carnivore",
            "d) Detrivores"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pyramid of energy doesn’t vary with the tophic level, but it always remains upright. It actually reflects the law of thermodynamics, which indicates that loss of energy at each trophic level will transfer to the next trophic level."
    },
    {
        "id": 874,
        "Question": " Which of the following ecosystem consists of forest, grassland and deserts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Artificial ecosystem",
            "b) Aquatic ecosystem",
            "c) Natural ecosystem",
            "d) Terrestrial ecosystem"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Carnivores have a high assimilation efficiency, but their production efficiency is lower than the herbivore."
    },
    {
        "id": 875,
        "Question": "Mark the one, which comes under a lotic ecosystem?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ocean",
            "b) Lake",
            "c) Pond",
            "d) River"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Ecosystems are of many types, out of which four most common ecosystems are: natural, terrestrial, aquatic, and artificial. Forest, grassland, and desert are examples of terrestrial ecosystem."
    },
    {
        "id": 876,
        "Question": "Which of the following is inter-tidal zone between land and open sea?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Benthic zone",
            "b) Pelagic zone",
            "c) Neritic zone",
            "d) Littoral"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Aquatic ecosystem has been broadly divided into fresh and marine water ecosystem. In fresh water lotic means running water, i.e., river while lentic ecosystem consists of lake and pond."
    },
    {
        "id": 877,
        "Question": "Which of the following zone lies at the bottom of the sea?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Littoral",
            "b) Benthic",
            "c) Neritic zone",
            "d) Pelagic zone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Ocean has been divided into many regions depending on the penetration of light. Littoral zone present at the shoreline between land and sea and also known as inter-tidal zone."
    },
    {
        "id": 878,
        "Question": "The collection of individuals which belongs to the same species when live together in a region is known as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Keystone species",
            "b) Community",
            "c) Guild",
            "d) Population"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A population is a group of individuals which belongs to the same species and living in the same region. Population ecology deals with the study of the population."
    },
    {
        "id": 879,
        "Question": "Name the term which defines the study of the characteristics and parameters of the population.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Demography",
            "b) Population ecology",
            "c) Population density",
            "d) Mortality"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Density is the representation of population size. It expressed the total number of individuals per unit area at a given time."
    },
    {
        "id": 880,
        "Question": "Which of the following term defines the ability of the individual in the population to produce new individuals?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dispersion",
            "b) Mortality",
            "c) Natality",
            "d) Population dispersal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The population is defined by the characteristics of the group rather than the individual. The study of the characteristics of the population is known as demography."
    },
    {
        "id": 881,
        "Question": " Which of the following survivorship curve is suitable for the organisms who breeds several times during the course of their life span?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Type IV",
            "b) Type III",
            "c) Type II",
            "d) Type I"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Natality is the ability of an individual to produce new individuals while mortality is the death of the individuals in the population."
    },
    {
        "id": 882,
        "Question": "Name those organisms who can breed only once in their lifetime?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dispersed",
            "b) Clumped",
            "c) Iteroparous",
            "d) Semelparous"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Type I survivorship curve is typically for those organisms who can breed several times during their life span. This strategy is referred to as iteroparous."
    },
    {
        "id": 883,
        "Question": "Which of the following structure can be seen in the diminishing population?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Upright",
            "b) Inverted",
            "c) Bell shaped",
            "d) Urn-shaped"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Semelparous are those organisms who can breed only once in their lifetime. It is a type of reproductive event and mainly represented by a type III survivorship curve."
    },
    {
        "id": 884,
        "Question": "A group of people coexist within space and time and interact with each other is known as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Keystone species",
            "b) Community",
            "c) Guild",
            "d) Population"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Diminishing population resulted in an urn-shaped structure. It shows the drastic reduction in the birth rate or population that is dying off."
    },
    {
        "id": 885,
        "Question": "Which of the following defines the separation of two different communities?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ecotone",
            "b) Edge effect",
            "c) Ecade",
            "d) Resistance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The community is the group of the population, which coexist within space and time and interact with each other either directly or indirectly."
    },
    {
        "id": 886,
        "Question": "What is an edge effect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Community complexity",
            "b) Community classification",
            "c) Increased diversity at the boundary of ecotone",
            "d) Community stability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Community refers only to the living population in the ecosystem and it does not involve non living component."
    },
    {
        "id": 887,
        "Question": "Which of the following is TRUE for the stabilized ecosystem?",
        "Options": [
            "a) P-R=1",
            "b) P/R < 1",
            "c) P/R > 1",
            "d) P/R =1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ecotone is a zone of vegetation which separates two different types of communities. It is also known as a transition zone."
    },
    {
        "id": 888,
        "Question": "Name the term which defines the ability of community return to its original state after being displaced?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dispersed",
            "b) Clumped",
            "c) Resistance",
            "d) Resilience"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Edge effect can be generally seen at the boundary of the Ecotone. It shows the maximum diversity at the transition boundary."
    },
    {
        "id": 889,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a diversity index?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Upright index",
            "b) Inverted index",
            "c) Bell shaped index",
            "d) Simpson’s index"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Ecosystem has been classified on the basis of community metabolism. The ratio of photosynthesis to respiration, i.e., P/R is equal to 1 for a stabilized ecosystem."
    },
    {
        "id": 890,
        "Question": "On an ecological time scale, the process of directional change in community composition is known as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Keystone species",
            "b) Succession",
            "c) Guild",
            "d) Population"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Succession is the universal process of change in community composition over an ecological time scale. It is a unidirectional change."
    },
    {
        "id": 891,
        "Question": "Which of the following selection pressure is obtained in late succession stage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) K- selection",
            "b) R- selection",
            "c) E-selection",
            "d) L- selection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the succession reaches to the point of relative stability, it is considered as the climax community. It marks the end point of the succession."
    },
    {
        "id": 892,
        "Question": "What is the entropy of the early succession community?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Medium",
            "b) Low",
            "c) High",
            "d) Very high"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Selection pressure has been categorized by the process of growth pattern, i.e., r-selection and k-selection. R-selection applies in early stage while k-selection in late stage."
    },
    {
        "id": 893,
        "Question": " Name the succession in which development of the biotic community starts after the destruction of an existing community?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Climax",
            "b) Seral",
            "c) Primary succession",
            "d) Secondary succession"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Entropy measures the degree of randomness. Early stage has high entropy while late stage has low entropy."
    },
    {
        "id": 894,
        "Question": "Which of the following succession processes describes the development of bare area without any form of life?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dispersed",
            "b) Clumped",
            "c) Ecesis",
            "d) Nudation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Succession happens in a bare area where no community existed before is known as a primary, community and the succession which is followed by the destruction of primary community is called secondary succession."
    },
    {
        "id": 895,
        "Question": "Which of the following factor is NOT responsible for autotrophic succession?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Climate",
            "b) Soil erosion",
            "c) Man",
            "d) Microorganisms"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Nudation is the first stage of succession where there is a development of the bare area by several external factors takes place."
    },
    {
        "id": 896,
        "Question": "Name the scientist who had described the term climax.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Linneus",
            "b) Clement",
            "c) Puri",
            "d) Cowles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The bare area in autotrophic succession develops by several factors like climatic, biotic, and topographic."
    },
    {
        "id": 897,
        "Question": "Name the type of community which is maintained by the man or his domestic animals.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Climatic",
            "b) Edaphic",
            "c) Disclimax",
            "d) Subclimax"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Clement had given the term climax to describe the idealized endpoint of succession. The climax is the final community which cannot be replaced further."
    },
    {
        "id": 898,
        "Question": "Who developed the polyclimax theory?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Daubenmire",
            "b) R.H Whittaker",
            "c) Clement",
            "d) Tansley"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Disclimax community is the stable community which is maintained by a man and his domestic animals. It is also known as disturbance climax."
    },
    {
        "id": 899,
        "Question": "Which of the following term is given to the process of successful establishment of the species?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ecesis",
            "b) Aggregation",
            "c) Nudation",
            "d) Competition"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Tansley developed the polyclimax theory which shows the mosaic vegetational climax controlled by soil moisture, nutrient and topography."
    },
    {
        "id": 900,
        "Question": "What is the effect on biodiversity when we move from pole to equator?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High",
            "b) Increases",
            "c) Decreases",
            "d) Remains same"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ecesis is considered as the complete as it describes the adjustment of the species and its successful establishment in any new area."
    }
]